<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="27"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[FOREWORD



                       Analysts of the knowledge society or knowledge economy characterize the
                       university not just as a generator of knowledge, an educator of young minds and
                       a transmitter of culture but also as a major agent of economic growth. It is both
                       a Research and Development laboratory and a mechanism through which the
                       nation builds its human capital to enable it to actively participate in the global
                       economy.


                       The UNESCO World Declaration on Higher Education for the Twenty-first Century
                       acknowledges that “knowledge creation, transmission and application are the
                       lifeblood of the knowledge-based economy” and higher education institutions
                       are among the primary entities tasked “to generate, transmit, disseminate and
                       apply knowledge.” They are thus a major component of the nation’s research
                       and innovation system. Moreover, from the perspective of education, vigorous
                       and high quality research underpins and nourishes degree-level learning
                       environments, especially for graduate and post-graduate programs; it provides
                       the inquisitive, critical  and independent regimen that develops intellectual
                       capability and advances the boundaries of knowledge and understanding.

                       The Commission on Higher Education is mandated to promote, direct and support
                       higher education institutions in performing their research and instruction
                       functions. With the objective of enabling our colleges and universities to produce
                       high quality research that will advance learning and national development, as well
                       as international comparability of the Philippine higher education system, the
                       National Higher Education Research Agenda was developed by CHED and
                       partner institutions/agencies.


                       The NHERA provides the policies, directions, priorities and thrusts of Philippine
                       higher education research in the medium to long term. Essentially, it encourages
                       networking among HEIs, with each network focusing on themes wherein the
                       members are or can be good at. It promotes partnerships/collaboration of HEIs
                       with other research institutions, local and foreign, as well as with industry and
                       private laboratories, for the conduct of research, and application of research
                       outputs.










                       Commission on Higher Education                                                 i]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[NHERA also includes a system of incentives and rewards for outstanding
                       performance in terms of:


                                 •   Producing and creating leading edge knowledge;
                                 •   applying that knowledge; and
                                 •   disseminating that knowledge to students and the wider community.


                       The first NHERA covered the period 1998-2008 including extension, this second
                       NHERA or NHERA-2  will be for the period 2009-2018. The initiatives under
                       NHERA-1 to  improve research capability and productivity among HEIs will be
                       sustained and new challenges will be addressed under NHERA-2 so that higher
                       education research could create appreciable impacts not only across all disciplines
                       of higher education but also in the more real-world socio-economic and cultural
                       milieu.






                                                                  EMMANUEL Y. ANGELES
                                                                                 Chairman











































                       ii                                                 Commission on Higher Education]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[INTRODUCTION




                       Background and Rationale




                       Research, as a major function in higher education, sets higher education apart
                       from basic education. In the Bologna Ministerial Meeting of 2007 the world
                       leaders in higher education explicitly stated: “The basis of research in higher
                       education is its independence and search for truth which justifies higher education’s
                       continued exercise of academic freedom”. Furthermore, the UNESCO World
                       Declaration on Higher Education for the Twenty-first Century accents the
                       important role of research in higher education viz: “State policies must promote
                       and develop research, which is a necessary feature of all higher education systems,
                       in all disciplines, including the human and social sciences and arts, given their
                       relevance for development”.


                       Research in higher education across all disciplines ensures the continued growth
                       and development of the entire higher education sector.


                       In the Philippine context, Republic Act No. 7722 known as the “Higher Education
                       Act of 1994”  mandates the Commission on Higher Education to perform the
                       following functions relative to research (Section 8, RA 7722):


                              b)     formulate and recommend development plans, policies, priorities and programs
                                     on research;
                              ...
                              e)     recommend to the executive and legislative branches, priorities and grants on
                                     higher education and research;
                              ...
                              i)     develop criteria for allocating additional resources such as research and program
                                     development grants, scholarships, and other similar programs; Provided, that
                                     these shall not detract from the fiscal autonomy  already enjoyed by colleges and
                                     universities;
                              ...
                               j)    direct or redirect purposive research by institutions of  higher learning to
                                     meet the needs of  agro-industrialization and  development;







                       Commission on Higher Education                                               iii]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[NHERA-1 (1998-2008)


                       In line with the said mandates, the following goals for higher education research
                       were set for NHERA-I:


                              •      Push the frontiers of knowledge across all the identified higher
                                     education disciplines  in the country;
                              •      Enhance instruction through original contributions in specialized
                                     disciplines thereby encouraging students to become themselves
                                     creative, innovative and productive individuals; and
                              •      Develop unifying theories or models which can be translated
                                     into mature technologies for the purpose of improving the
                                     quality of life of the Filipinos within the sphere of influence of
                                     academic institutions in the country.


                       Towards the attainment of these goals, nine priority clusters and 17 priority
                       disciplines were identified, with special emphasis on researches that are
                       multidisciplinary, leading edge scientific or technological, breakthrough or
                       pioneering, and/or policy oriented.  CHED supported the agenda with a budget
                       allocation of P376M for a period of 10 years, specifically to provide:


                              •      Conducive policy environment for the management and
                                     administration of research;
                              •      technical assistance for research; and
                              •      funding/financial assistance for research in higher education in
                                     the form of block  grants,  grants-in-aid and commissioned
                                     research.


                       Three years into the implementation of NHERA-1, the Zonal Research Center
                       component was added. This involved the establishment of twelve ZRCs in higher
                       education institutions that are known for their strong research tradition and
                       leadership. These ZRCs were tasked to help CHED in promoting research and
                       building research capacity in the higher education institutions within the zones
                       assigned to them and to bring closer to the HEIs the assistance necessary to
                       strengthen their research function.  Nine of these ZRCs operated for six years
                       while three operated for three years.


                       With the objective of facilitating the transfer and utilization of HEI research
                       outputs for  development, the Commission decided in 2005 to include an
                       Integrated Research Utilization Program in the NHERA. Under this program,



                       iv                                                 Commission on Higher Education]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[funding assistance was provided for the transfer, utilization/commercialization
                       of technologies developed by the HEIs.


                       Other additions to NHERA-1 are three programs for recognizing and rewarding
                       research productivity: the Research and Publication Award (REPUBLICA) which
                       was launched in 2004,  the Best Higher Education Institution Research Program
                       Award which was initiated in 2005 and the Outstanding Higher Education
                       Extension Program Award which was granted for the first time in 2008.


                       At the end of NHERA-1, a Technical Working Group was created by CHED to
                       review the  Agenda and formulate its successor, NHERA-2, taking into
                       consideration the new challenges and opportunities posed by the rapid
                       developments in ICT, emergence of new fields like nanotechnology, globalization,
                       and the knowledge-based economy.



                       NHERA-2 (2009-2018)


                       NHERA-2 restates the general policies that should guide higher education research,
                       presents strategies and initiatives to develop research capacity and enhance research
                       productivity in higher education institutions, and identifies priority areas for
                       research and research-related programs in the next ten years. It is a product of a
                       series of roundtable discussions on the changing conditions of higher education
                       in the country and the state of research in Philippine colleges and universities. It
                       incorporates the best thinking of national experts including institutional leaders,
                       senior researchers and representatives from organizations that fund research.


                       The Agenda is directed at three primary audiences, each playing a vital role in
                       shaping Philippine higher education – state policy makers, institutional leaders,
                       and researchers. It is designed to help them consider what types of research
                       would contribute most to national development and to the advancement of the
                       disciplines, and hence, should be supported.


                       NHERA is an evolving document  and will thus be periodically reviewed and
                       updated to respond to the changing times and needs of society.












                       Commission on Higher Education                                                v]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[ACRONYMS





                       ASEAN         -  Association of South East Asian Nations
                       CHED          -  Commission on Higher Education
                       CHEDRO        -  Commission on Higher Education Regional Office
                       CMO           -  CHED Memorandum Order
                       COMSTE        -  Congressional Commission on Science and Technology and
                                         Engineering
                       DBM           -  Department of Budget and Management
                       DOH           -  Department of Health
                       DOLE          -  Department of Labor and Employment
                       DOST          -  Department of Science and Technology
                       EDCOM         -  Congressional Commission on Education
                       GIA           -  Grant-in-Aid
                       HEI           -  Higher Education Institution
                       ICT           -  Information & Communication Technology
                       IRUP          -  Integrated Research Utilization Program
                       JAS           -  Journal Accreditation Service
                       MOA           -  Memorandum of Agreement
                       NEDA          -  National Economic and Development Authority
                       NIBRA         -  National Integrated Basic Research Agenda
                       NUHRA         -  National Unified Health Research Agenda
                       NSTP          -  National Service Training Program
                       OPPRI-RD -  Office of Policy, Planning, Research and Information-Research
                                        Division
                       R & D         -  Research and Development
                       S & T         -  Science and Technology
                       SUC           -  State University and College
                       UNESCO        -  United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization
                       ZRC           -  Zonal Research Center



















                       vi                                                 Commission on Higher Education]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[NATIONAL HIGHER EDUCATION RESEARCH

                                          AGENDA - 2 (2009-2018)




                       General Principles on Higher Education Research


                       Higher education research shall be guided by the following general principles:


                              1.     Research is the ultimate expression of an individual’s innovative and
                                     creative  powers.  The higher education sector shall ensure that the
                                     academic environment nurtures and supports Filipino research
                                     talents.


                              2.     Research thrives  in an environment characterized  by free  flow of
                                     information, honest  and analytical exchange of ideas, and supportive
                                     policy and administrative structures. Higher education policies shall
                                     enhance  the  institution’s  and the  individual’s capacity  to conduct
                                     independent, collaborative and productive research.


                              3.     Research is one of the main functions of the higher education sector.
                                     Universities  in  particular,  are  expected to lead in the conduct of
                                     discipline-based,     policy-oriented,     technology-directed     and
                                     innovative/creative  researches  that  are  locally  responsive  and
                                     globally competitive.

                       Goals and Objectives


                       NHERA-2 shall support the higher education sector’s goals to develop high level
                       and globally competitive  workforce, generate/transfer knowledge and technology
                       for enhancing productivity and quality of life in order to reduce poverty and ensure
                       sustainable development in the country.


                       The following objectives shall be pursued under NHERA-2:


                              1.     Improve research capability of HEIs, particularly the Philippine
                                            universities whose main  business is to generate knowledge towards
                                     international competitiveness;


                              2.     Enhance research productivity of HEIs in distinctive areas of
                                     competence;



                      Commission on Higher Education                                               1]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[National Higher Education Research Agenda 2 (2009-2018)

                              3.     Generate knowledge/technologies needed for
                                     a.     International, national and regional higher education
                                            development,
                                     b.     policy/plan formulation, particularly for higher education
                                     c.     developing innovative programs in cutting edge higher
                                            education fields  (e.g. nanotechnology, biotechnology,
                                            information and communications technology, and materials
                                            science); and
                                     d.     advancing the frontiers of knowledge in the disciplines

                              4.     Promote and facilitate dissemination and utilization of research
                                     outputs

                       Agendum 1. Improving research capability of HEIs towards
                           international competitiveness


                       NHERA-1 began a massive research capability program for HEIs in the country.
                       However, such capability building activities were focused on the more generic aspects
                       of research which cut across all disciplines e.g. research methodologies, data analysis,
                       proposal preparation and others. In order to address the peculiar requirements of
                       each higher education discipline for research, NHERA-2 shall concentrate on
                       research capability building by discipline.

                       Strategies and initiatives for Agendum 1

                              1.   Research capability building programs.  CHED  shall  provide funds
                                 to support   graduate scholarships and fellowships, including but not
                                 limited to: thesis grants, dissertation grants, and travel grants for
                                 presentation  of  research  papers in national and international
                                 conferences.   CHED   shall    likewise   strengthen    the   Visiting
                                 Research Fellows Program in order to assist promising HEI’s in their
                                 quest for research excellence.

                              2.  Strengthening   graduate  education  in  priority  disciplines.   It   is
                                 generally  recognized  that  graduate  education  plays a critical role  in
                                 producing  the  experts  needed to revitalize research in the country
                                 as  well  as  the  bulk  of  research  outputs  needed  for  development,
                                 education and policy formulation. Hence, there is a need to strengthen
                                 graduate  programs  in  priority  disciplines.  Promising HEIs with the
                                 capacity  or  reputation  to  undertake  research  on   these   disciplines
                                 shall  be  targeted  for  technical  and  financial  assistance.  The various
                                 Centers  of  Excellence  shall  also  be  tasked  to  perform  leadership
                                 roles in providing strong graduate programs in these disciplines.


                            2]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Agendum 2. Enhancing research productivity of HEIs


                       Analysis of the research productivity (in terms of the publications of higher
                       education faculty) of HEIs shows that the implementation of NHERA-1 resulted
                       in roughly 33% increase in faculty publications benchmarked from the EDCOM
                       (1993) report. However, most of the publications were concentrated in the “soft
                       sciences”. NHERA-2 will increase research productivity in every higher education
                       discipline and improve research to faculty ratio.



                       Strategies and initiatives for Agendum 2



                              1.     Funding  research in  and  on  higher  education.   CHED  shall
                                     provide funding for  the conduct of research  in  identified  priorities.
                                     Funding shall be  in  the  form of  Grants-in-Aid  or  commissioned
                                     research grant.


                                     Grants-in-Aid shall be made available to researchers in both public
                                     and  private  higher  education institutions  who  can  and want to do
                                     research on the priority areas.


                                     Commissioned research grants shall be available for specific topics
                                     or  issues/ problems  which  the Commission deems important  in
                                     the pursuit of its mandates.


                              2.     Institutionalization of a system of  rewards and  incentives  for
                                     research   undertakings   and   outputs   of   HEI   faculty   and
                                     researchers.   In  order  to  encourage  faculty  and  institutions  to
                                     conduct and invest in research, the Commission shall adopt a system
                                     of  recognizing outstanding  researchers  and outstanding research
                                     programs and outputs.  Excellence  in research shall be recognized
                                     through various  awards and  other  incentives,  including,  but  not
                                     limited  to:  REPUBLICA,   Best  HEI  Research  Program  Awards,
                                     Outstanding  HEI  Extension  Program  Awards,  and professorial
                                     chairs in public or private institutions.












                      Commission on Higher Education                                               3]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[National Higher Education Research Agenda 2 (2009-2018)


                              3.     Journal Accreditation  Service.   A  system  of  accreditation  of
                                     research journals shall be established to ensure adoption of fair and
                                     impartial   refereeing   system  for  all  research  journals  in  higher
                                     education in the country.  The JAS shall serve as a mechanism through
                                     which  a  national  standard  for peer review and journal refereeing
                                     system  can  be  implemented  uniformly  for  all  research journals
                                     published    by   the   Philippine   HEIs   and   other   professional
                                     organizations.


                       Agendum 3.   Generating  new  knowledge   needed   for   the
                           advancement of higher education as well  as for national
                           development


                       Under NHERA-1, studies were commissioned to generate knowledge needed to
                       improve policies and the implementation and administration of higher education
                       in the country.  These focused mostly on the rationalization of the higher education
                       system and on addressing the manpower demand-supply mismatch.   At the same
                       time, GIAs were provided for research in aid of national and regional thrusts,
                       particularly biodiversity and environmental management, human resource
                       development, agriculture and agri-based micro-small-medium scale enterprises,
                       tourism, ICT-related concerns, and others.


                       Under NHERA-2, the higher  educacation sector will continue to work in tandem
                       with the science and technology, industry, agriculture, energy and other sectors to
                       address the research priorities for development. Greater attention shall, however,
                       be accorded to the studies that would generate  inputs for the formulation of
                       policies, plans, programs and projects, and produce/adapt technologies for
                       enhancing quality, relevance, access and equity, and efficiency and effectiveness in
                       higher education.


                       In addition,  priority shall be given to research aimed at developing innovative
                       programs in cutting edge higher education fields  (e.g. nanotechnology,
                       biotechnology, information and communications technology, and materials science),
                       and advancing the frontiers of knowledge in the disciplines.


                       NHERA-2 aims to place Philippine higher education in the international research
                       community through awards and recognition of Filipino researchers in cutting edge
                       disciplines as well as in other priority disciplines.





                            4]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Strategies and initiatives for Agendum 3



                          1.         Dovetailing higher education research with R & D initiatives
                                     of the Department of Science and Technology  and other donor/
                                     research  agencies.  CHED  and  higher education institutions are
                                     part of the National Innovation System which comprises a number
                                     of R & D funding and implementing entities. The higher education
                                     sector’s  research   program  should  thus  complement  and  be  in
                                     harmony  with  the R & D  efforts of  the other   members   of  the
                                     national  innovation  system  --  DOST, Department of Agriculture,
                                     Department  of  Energy,   Department  of    Environment    and
                                     Natural    Resources,    Congressional Commission on Science and
                                     Technology and Engineering, and others.


                          2.         Networking. Networks or consortia shall be formed between and
                                     among  higher  education  institutions   with  research  expertise  in
                                     identified priority themes/ disciplines, to pool resources  of  the
                                     better  institutions  and  allow  sharing  of  these resources for
                                     research capability  building and conduct of research. The nodes
                                     of the networks shall be Centers of Excellence/Centers of
                                     Development, Autonomous HEIs and institutions with Level II-
                                     IV accredited programs in the priority discipline.


                          3.         Establishment of zonal research laboratories with state-of-the-
                                     art facilities and equipment for cutting edge technology research.


                          4.         Visiting scholars and fellowship program. CHED shall continue
                                     to  promote  the  Visiting Research Fellowship Program  in order to
                                     provide participating HEIs with  the   needed   high  level  expertise
                                     to establish  and  develop  the culture of research in these institutions.






















                      Commission on Higher Education                                               5]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[National Higher Education Research Agenda 2 (2009-2018)

                       Agendum 4. Promoting and facilitating dissemination and
                           utilization of research outputs



                       With CHED support, faculty researchers were able to present their research outputs
                       in international conferences/fora during the last four years of NHERA-1. National
                       and international research conferences were also organized and hosted by CHED
                       and partner institutions/organizations.

                       The Integrated Research Utilization Programs which were introduced in 2005
                       enabled SUCs to utilize  technologies that they had developed for their own Income
                       Generating Projects or transfer these to end-users for livelihood and employment
                       generation. Their technology transfer activities gave rise to livelihood projects that
                       provided employment for breadwinners in their host communities.


                       Information dissemination activities will be expanded under NHERA-2 in
                       anticipation of increased research productivity among HEIs. Support shall also be
                       provided for the publication of research papers in refereed journals. The IRUP
                       will be sustained with focus on utilization of research outputs for income generating
                       projects that will help SUCs generate more funds to be funneled back to research
                       and instruction.



                       Strategies and initiatives for Agendum 4



                              1.     Supporting dissemination of research outputs.  Cognizant of  the
                                     need to make research results known and disseminated worldwide,
                                     CHED  shall  provide  financial  support  for  the  conduct of  and
                                     participation in dissemination activities such as research fora, seminars
                                     and conferences, and for publication in/of refereed research journals
                                     in various disciplines.



                              2.     Research  utilization   and   technology   commercialization
                                     programs. CHED shall continue to support initiatives of HEIs in
                                     utilizing  the  technologies  generated by  their researchers for their
                                     own  Income  Generating  Projects or  in transferring these to end-
                                     users for commercialization and productivity enhancement.









                            6]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[PRIORITY RESEARCH AREAS /THEMES


                       Principles guiding prioritization


                       The NHERA  integrates the concerns of higher  education sector with the overall
                       development goals and objectives of the country, the National Innovation System
                       and the higher education international community.


                       In formulating the NHERA, the Commission was guided by the following principles:


                              1.     Multidisciplinarity.  Researches  that  involve   the  expertise  of
                                     researchers  in  several  disciplines  are  preferred  over  researches
                                     needing the  expertise  in  a  single  discipline.  This principle  shall,
                                     however,  not apply to the category of  “breakthrough researches”
                                     such as revolutionary scientific or mathematical discoveries.


                              2.     Policy orientation.  Policy-oriented  researches  are  preferred  over
                                     researches that  have little or no policy implication across the various
                                     higher education disciplines.


                              3.     Participation and networking.   The research should  involve the
                                     participation  of  as  many  stakeholders  as possible and should be
                                     organized preferably as network, instead of stand alone, undertaking
                                     of an HEI or individual researcher.


                              4.     Balanced attention to basic and applied research. Both basic or
                                     pure research and applied research shall be given due importance.

                              5.     Dovetailing and complementation with other R & D initiatives.
                                     In  order  to  ensure  complementation  and  avoid  duplication  of
                                     research initiatives, CHED shall coordinate closely with the DOST
                                     and other  funding  institutions in the  evaluation,  monitoring  and
                                     programming of research in HEIs.


                       Research priorities

                       Guided by the above principles there are several categories of research undertakings
                       that require and shall be given consideration:

                              1.     Basic research to generate new knowledge and advance the frontiers
                                     in the various disciplines;



                      Commission on Higher Education                                               7]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[National Higher Education Research Agenda 2 (2009-2018)

                              2.     Research  in  aid  of  policy/plan formulation and implementation
                                     particularly in education
                              3.     Research  aimed  at  producing/adapting  education  technologies
                                     and developing education  programs  in cutting edge fields such
                                     as nanotechnology, biotechnology, ICT, materials science, etc.
                              4.     R & D in aid of national/regional development


                       Priority discipline clusters

                       Consistent with the Medium term Plan for the Development of Higher Education 2005-
                       2010 and the New Higher Education Highway Toward a Knowledge-based Economy,  research
                       shall be encouraged in the following clusters of disciplines:
                              Science and Mathematics
                              Education and Teacher Training
                              Health and health profession
                              Information and Communication Technology
                              Engineering, Maritime and Architecture
                              Agriculture
                              Environmental Science
                              Humanities
                              Social Sciences
                              Other disciplines as identified by the Commission

                       The Technical Working Group on Research and the various Technical Panels of
                       CHED shall periodically review the state of the art in their respective disciplines,
                       identify knowledge gaps and recommend priority areas for research in the disciplines.
                       The recommended priority research areas shall be circulated periodically through
                       CHED Memorandum Orders.




























                            8]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Priority Research Areas in Education and Education
                              Management

                              1.     Program/curricular  studies  on  higher  education  – including
                                     assessment  of  present   programs/curricula   for   purposes   of
                                     determining how these could  be  improved/reengineered  as  well
                                     as  international  benchmarking  of   best   practices   towards  the
                                     development  of   new programs/curricula in leading edge disciplines

                              2.     Policy  oriented  studies – research  on  the  various  dimensions  of
                                     policy  formulation,  implementation,  monitoring  and e valuation
                                     focusing on but not limited to the following:
                                     a.     financing of higher education; cost sharing in higher education
                                     b.     economics of higher education,
                                     c.     governance and management of higher education,
                                     d.     accreditation and other quality assurance mechanisms,
                                     e.     rationalization of higher education,
                                     f.     internationalization of higher education
                                     g.     access and equity measures
                                     h.     student financing models

                              3.     Research on quality and standards in the context of:
                                     a.      international rankings and global benchmarking
                                     b.     quality assurance systems
                                     c.      equivalency
                                     d.      redefining classifications of HEIs


                              4.     Technology and education
                              5.     Model building studies
                              6.     Institutional development studies
                              7.     Manpower demand and supply studies
                              8.     Graduate tracer studies
                              9.     Other research topics considered by the Commission in response
                                     to emerging needs of the country

















                      Commission on Higher Education                                               9]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[National Higher Education Research Agenda 2 (2009-2018)

                       Higher education research in support of R & D initiatives of other
                            agencies/sectors


                       The higher education sector is part of the National Innovation System that generates
                       and mobilizes knowledge for enhancing productivity and addressing the goals of
                       national development. As such, CHED and the HEIs are expected not only to
                       produce research and development manpower but also to actively participate in
                       the implementation of the R & D plans for Science and Technology, Health, Energy,
                       Agriculture and other sectors that are identified as priority in the National
                       Development  Plan.


                       Hence NHERA-2 supports and complements the following:


                              1.     National Science and Technology Plan (NSTP)  2002-2020.


                                     The S &  T area thrusts of the NSTP are:
                                     a.     Agriculture, Forestry and Natural Resources
                                     b.     Health and Medical Sciences
                                     c.     Biotechnology
                                     d.     Information and Communication Technology
                                     e.     Microelectronics
                                     f.     Earth and Marine Sciences
                                     g.     Fisheries and Aquaculture
                                     h.     Environment
                                     i.     Natural Disaster Mitigation
                                     j.     Energy
                                     k.     Materials Science and Engineering
                                     l.     Manufacturing and process engineering


                              2.         National Integrated Basic Research Agenda.  NIBRA  specifies
                                     the areas of priority that will be the focus of basic research up to
                                     2010. The priorities  identified  in  NIBRA  are  consistent with the
                                     NSTP; in   addition,   these   include   areas/ topics   devoted   to
                                     policy, government, education and international affairs, social
                                     sciences and the humanities.  The main benefits of basic research
                                     results  are  “the advancement of frontiers in the discipline  itself”.

                              3.     National   Unified   Health   Research   Agenda   2008-2010.
                                     NUHRA specifies the areas and topics that need to be addressed in





                            10]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[line with the  global  and  national  initiatives  influencing  the  health
                                     sector. Priority research topics are classified into major areas, namely,
                                     health financing,  governance,  health regulations,  health  service
                                     delivery, health technology development,  health research ethics, and
                                     health information system.

                              4.     Recommendations of the Congressional Commission on Science
                                     and Technology and Engineering.  R & D priorities identified by
                                     COMSTE  are  in    six    key    areas,  namely,   agriculture   and
                                     food, electronics  and semi conductors,  energy and environment,
                                     health science, IT and IT-related industries, and science,  mathematics
                                     and engineering education.


                       Priority themes for multidisciplinary/multisectoral research


                       In light of the realities that the country is now experiencing and will face in the
                       future, research on the following themes shall be encouraged:


                              1.     Food  safety and  security.  Considering  the country’s prone-ness
                                     to    natural    hazards    and   disasters    and  with    its   booming
                                     population,   it   is  important  for  the  people  to  be  assured  of
                                     affordable and safe food on  their table.


                              2.     Enhancing indigenous renewable energy source in the domestic
                                     energy  mix.  Increasing the percentage  of  indigenous  renewable
                                     energy source into the national energy mix  will  not  only result  in
                                     dollar  saving,   and  protection  of   the   environment   but   more
                                     importantly, ensuring energy security. The search, development and
                                     exploitation  of  renewable   energy   sources   will   involve   a  multi-
                                     disciplinary approach.

                              3.     Development of vaccines and diagnostic kits using indigenous
                                     materials.   Emerging   and   reemerging   diseases   have   always
                                     threatened  the  global and regional scenes.  The country  has to be
                                     prepared  for  these by having the appropriate medication,  vaccines
                                     and diagnostic kits that are readily available and affordable.











                      Commission on Higher Education                                               11]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[National Higher Education Research Agenda 2 (2009-2018)

                              4.     Disaster   risk  management.   The   shift   from  preparedness to
                                     prevention  and mitigation  mode  in our disaster  risk  management
                                     framework  would  entail a  lot of  research  work  not only in policy
                                     formulation,  community development,  and  public awareness but
                                     also in hard science (e.g. forecasting, structural engineering aspects).


                              5.     Pollution control. Environmental issues that affect the land,  air
                                     and  water should be studied. A developing country like the
                                     Philippines  must  ensure  that   progress  is  not compromised by
                                     environmental degradation.


                              6.     Climate change specifically on the issue of global warming. The
                                     four  pillars  of  the  Bali  Action Plan  dealing  with   a) mitigation,
                                     b) adaptation, c) technology transfer, and d) financial resources are
                                     rich sources of multi disciplinary research work.  Considering that
                                     climate change issues deal with future scenarios, a wholistic approach
                                     is necessary.


                              7.     Future ASEAN. The ASEAN Charter has come into force and by
                                     AY 2015,  we  will  be  a  single community. The ASEAN will also
                                     have its own legal personality. In the process, immediate studies on
                                     how to handle this pending reality must be done.


                              8.     Peace process and conflict resolution.  This  is  a  rich  source  of
                                     research work,  the results of  which can be  applied  to governance,
                                     policies and direction setting.































                            12]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[National Higher Education Research Agenda 2 (2009-2018)

                         GUIDELINES FOR AVAILMENT OF CHED GRANTS AND
                                                        AWARDS


                       Research grants




                       In  the  implementation  of  the  National  Higher  Education  Research  Agenda-2
                       CHED shall provide five types of funding assistance:


                       1.     Grants-in-Aid (GIA) – grants  for researches that  fall within the national or
                              zonal priorities/agenda identified by CHED.  Priority is given to research
                              proposals submitted by HEIs. Proposals for GIA are processed by Zonal
                              Research Centers  identified  by the Commission,  in cooperation with the
                              OPPRI - Research Division.

                       2.     Commissioned  research  –  grants  awarded  to  institutions/individuals  with
                              proven  track  record  in  research  based  on the  topics/issues/problems
                              identified  by  the  Commission  as  important/vital   to  the  pursuit of  its
                              mandates.   Proposals  for  commissioned  research  are  processed by the
                              OPPRI-Research Division.


                       3.     Visiting  Research  Fellowships  –  grants   awarded  to   outstanding  research
                              professors   in  HEIs  across   various disciplines  in  recognition of  their
                              significant   contributions  and  outputs   in   the   academic  and  research
                              community. Proposals for Visiting Research Fellowship are processed by
                              the OPPRI-Research Division.

                       4.     Research   Professorial  Chairs.   Outstanding  research  professors  in  higher
                              education  institutions shall be given recognition through grants of  Research
                              Professorial  Chairs.  The  title  of Research  Professor remains  with  the
                              Professor  for  as  long  as  he/she  remains  actively  engaged  in CHED-
                              funded  research.  The  results  of  his  research  will  be published  in JAS
                              accredited journal. Search and selection shall be done at the OPPRI-RD.


                       5.     Thesis/Dissertation Grants –  grants awarded to deserving faculty to support
                              and  enable  them  to  do their  thesis/dissertation  and  earn  their  master/
                              PhD degree from Centers of Development/Centers of Excellence.


                              The detailed  procedures  are described  in CMO 32, s. 2008; CMO 38, s.
                              2008;  CMO 13, s. 2009;  and CMO 10, s. 2009. ( see  www.ched.gov.ph)



                            16]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Criteria for evaluating research proposals



                       The Proposal


                              a.     The proposal corresponds with one or more of the listed research
                                     priorities;


                              b.     The research proposal is relevant to the problems and needs in the
                                     local/national setting in the case of applied research;

                              c.     The methodology of the study is justified and sound;
                                     1)  Well-selected variables
                                     2)  Clarity of the objectives/problems
                                     3)  Appropriateness of methodologies
                                     4)  Comprehensiveness of  the review/scanning  of  literature  and
                                          empirical studies


                              d.     The  proposal’s  expected  outputs,   impacts  and  derivations  are
                                     clear and well-defined;


                              e.     The  work  plan includes a description of each activity in the study
                                     including date of  completion; and


                              f.     The  financial plan and budgetary  outlay are adequate and present
                                     an itemized breakdown of the total project costs and source/s of
                                     funds.

                       The Proponent



                       The  proponent  has  the  track  record/competence  to  carry  out  the proposed
                       research:
                              a)  Academic qualification
                              b)  Research experience in his field of specialization















                      Commission on Higher Education                                               17]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[National Higher Education Research Agenda 2 (2009-2018)








































































                                     2.








                            18]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Commission on Higher Education                                               19]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[National Higher Education Research Agenda 2 (2009-2018)


















































































                            20]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Commission on Higher Education                                               21]]></page></pages></Search>