<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Search><pages Count="69"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                                   AREA I – The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives


                   PARAMETER A – STATEMENT OF VISION, MISSION GOALS AND OBJECTIVES
                   I.     SYTEMS – INPUTS AND PROCESSES

                       ➢  Vision of the University/College

                       The  premier  University  in  historic  Cavite  Recognized  for  excellence  in  the
                   development of globally competitive and morally upright inidviduals.



                   •  Excerpt from the CvSU Manual of Operation Rule I General Provision, page 7. The
                       CvSU Manual of Operation was approved per BOR Resolution No. 85 series of

                       2009 dated September 3, 2009.


                       Ang  nangungunang  pamantasan  sa  makasaysayang  Kabite  na  kinikilala  sa
                       kahusayan sa paghubog ng mga inidbidwal na may paninindigang kakayahan at

                       kagandahang asal.


                       *The Filipino translation of the University Vision was approved per BOR Resolution

                       No. 89 Series of 2011 dated November 29, 2011.


                       ➢  Mission of the University/College
                       Cavite State University shall provide excellent, equitable, and relevant educational

               opportunities  in  the  arts  sciences  and  technology  through  quality  instruction  and

               responsive research and development activities.  It shall produce professional, skilled and
               morally upright individuals for global competitiveness.



                   •  Excerpt from the CvSU Manual of Operation Rule I General Provision, page 7. The
                       CvSU Manual of Operation was approved per BOR Resolution No. 85 series of

                       2009 dated September 3, 2009.









                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                       Ang  Cavite  State  University  ay  makakapagbigay  ng  mahusay,  pantay  at
                       makabuluhang edukasyon sa sining agham at teknolohiya sa pamamagitan ng

                       may kalidad na pagtuturo at tumutugon sa pangangailangang pananaliksik at mga
                       gawaing  pangka  unlaran.    Makakalikha  ito  ng  indibidwal  na  dalubhasa,  may

                       kasanayan at kagandahang asal para sa pandaigdigang kakayahan.


                   •  The  Filipino  translation  of  the  University  Mission  was  approved  per  BOR

                       Resolution No. 89 series of 2011 dated November 29, 2011.


                       ➢  Goals of the Academic Unit

               In support to the Vision and Mission of the University, CvSU Trece Martires City Campus
               shall:

                   1.  Provide high quality  instruction  in  order to produce  skilled, morally  upright  and
                       globally competitive graduates.

                   2.  Develop  and  pursue  advance  research  activities  through  arts,  sciences  and

                       technology to support instruction.
                   3.  Develop  and  conduct  extension  activities  that  will  empower  people  and

                       communities.
               Towards these ends, the Information Technology Department exerts its utmost effort to:

                   1.   Support  the  university’s  mission  and  vision  in  providing  globally  competitive
                       individuals through technological advancements;

                   2.  Equip students with knowledge in the field of information and computer technology;

                       and
                   3.  Strengthen students’ skills through research development and extension activities

                       that will endow their personal and social growth.













                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                       ➢  State the Objectives/Outcomes of the Program
                  (CMO No. 25 Series of 2015)

                       The Bachelor of Science in Information Technology program prepares students to
                  be IT Professionals, be well versed on application installation, operation, development,

                  maintenance and administration, and familiar with hardware installation, operation and

                  maintenance.


                  A graduate of Bachelor in Information Technology can be:
                  1.  Applications developer
                  2.  Database administrator
                  3.  Entrepreneur in IT Industry
                  4.  Information Security Administrator
                  5.  Information Technology Instructor
                  6.  Network Administrator
                  7.  Network Engineer
                  8.  System Analyst
                  9.  Technical Support Specialist
                  10. Test Engineer
                  11. Web Master/Web Administrator
                  12. Web Developer


                  The  Bachelor  of  Science  in  Information  Technology  program  aims  to  produce
               graduates who can:

                   1.  Apply  knowledge  of  utilization  of  both  hardware  and  software  technologies
                       involving planning, installing, customizing, operating, managing and administering,

                       and  maintaining  information  technology  infrastructure  that  provides  computing

                       solutions to address the needs of an organization;
                   2.  Conduct  relevant  researches  ad  extension  program  activities  in  the  field  of

                       information technology;
                   3.  Promote the development and transfer of appropriate information technology;

                   4.  Promote environmental preservation and protection on projects and enterprises
                       related to information technology; and

                   5.  Become morally upright IT professionals with primary or secondary job roles.






                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                       ➢  Illustrates  and  describes  the  historical  formulation,  monitoring  and
                          review of the VMGO.

                       As stated in the University’s Manual of Operations, the University Vision-Mission
               statement was framed in 2001.

                       On 2005, a Memorandum of Agreement was signed on the establishment of the

               CvSU Trece Martires City Campus and it became operationalized in June 2005 through
               BOR  Resolution  No.  41  Series  of  2005.    CvSu-Trece  Martires  City  Campus  then

               formulated its goals and objectives including the Department of Information Technology
               having the Bachelor in Information Technology, Associate in Computer Secretarial and

               Certificate in Computer Technician as programs.
                       President Hernando D. Robles included the review/revisit/revision of the University

               Vision and Mission in the Management Training and Strategic Planning Workshop held

               on  January  24,  2017  together  with  the  members  of  the  administrative  council,
               College/Campus Deans and Administrators, Directors and Unit heads. The activity was

               also participated by representatives from the students, alumni, community, industry and

               research and extension partners, and other planning stakeholders.
                       T3 Campuses (Tanza, Trece and  General Trias) goals were revised on May 9,

               2018 during the Curriculum and Instruction Committee meeting.  In which, the unified
               department objectives across T3 Campuses were also reviewed and revised .

                           DATE                                    EVENTS
                 January 22, 1998                     Republic Act No. 8468

                                                      Don  Severino  Agricultural  College  (DSAC)
                                                     was  elevated  into  University  now  known  as
                                                     Cavite State University (CvSU).

                                                      The university has an existing Development
                                                     Agenda for 1998 to 2006
                                                      Revisiting of Vision and Mission Statements

                 February 27 -29, 2001                Institutional  Planning  and  Development
                                                     Workshop

                                                      Conducted  to  harmonize  philosophies,
                                                     thrusts, and directions among campuses





                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                                                      Participants were administrators and middle
                                                     management officers.

                 June 7-8, 2001                       Performance commitment of different units for
                                                     AY 2001 – 2002
                                                      Initial  Review  of  vision  and  mission

                                                     statements of the university
                                                      Student    representatives    and     other
                                                     stakeholders took part.


                 December 19, 2001                   Multi-campus Strategic Planning Workshop

                                                     Revision  of  Existing  Agenda  for  Development
                                                     (1998 to 2006)
                                                     Thorough  analysis  of  the  internal  and  external
                                                     environments and the vision, mission and values,
                                                     for change.
                                                     Participants included community leaders, alumni,

                                                     faculty staff, students and othe stakeholders.
                 May 9, 2018                         Review  and  Revision  of  T3  Campus  Golas  and
                                                     Objectives
                                                     Revision of department Objectives
                                                     Participants  were  the  Department  Chairpersons,
                                                     Campus Coordinators and Campus Administrator.






















                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




              2. IMPLEMENTATION

                          ➢  Describe         the      stakeholders’         participation       in      the
                              formulation/monitoring/review of the Objectives of the program.



                 Stakeholders                     Nature               of  Inclusive Dates
                                                  Participation

                a.  Board     of   Regents     /  Planning/ Formulation  December 09, 2001

                    Trustees
                b.  Administration                Formulation               December 09, 2001

                                                  /Presenters
                c.  Faculty                       Participants              December 09, 2001

                d.  Non-Teaching                  Participants              December 09, 2001

                e.  Students                      Participants              December 09, 2001
                f.  Alumni                        Participants              December 09, 2001

                g.  Cooperating Agencies          Participants              December 09, 2001

                h.  Industry Sector               Participants              December 09, 2001
                i.  Concerned Groups              Participants              December 09, 2001


               T3 Campus Goals and Department Objectives

                 Campus Administrator               Presiding Officer       May 9, 2018

                 Campus Coordinators                Participants            May 9, 2018
                 Department Chairpersons            Participants            May 9, 2018
















                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



               3.OUTCOMES
                          ➢  BOR/BOT  Resolution  Approving  the  VMGO;  include  BOR/BOT

                              Resolution amendments.
                       Based on the minutes of the minutes of the 42  regular meeting of the CvSU Board
                                                                      nd
               of Regents held at CvSU, Indang, Cavite, the University Vision-Mission statement was

               duly approved on September 30, 2009 wit BOR Resolution No. 85 S 2009 and the Filipino
               translation was approved per BOR Resolution No. 89 s. 2011



















































               ➢  A study was conducted by Dr. Luzviminda Rodrin entitled Awareness, Dissemination
                   and Acceptability of the University Visio and Mission. The study concluded and

                   recommended  the following:




                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



               1.  The University stakeholders are fully aware of the vision, mission, goals and
                   objectives in general;

               2.   Stakeholders believed that the University could achieve its vision of producing
                   globally competitive graduates; and

               3.  The university could do well by having internet, local radio, providing state of the art

                   facilities, and having cooperation among and between students, faculty,
                   administrators, non-teaching staff, industry partners where most of the graduates are

                   likely to work after graduation.
               4.  BEST PRACTICES

                   1.  Don Severino Agricultural College (DSAC) was converted to Cavite State
                       University (CvSU) by virtue of RA NO. 8468

                   2.  The University conducts a review on its Vision and Mission statement.

                   3.  The VMGO are well disseminated according to the educational mandate of the
                       institution.

                   4.  The goals and objectives are being updated for approval according to the

                       competencies, values, and other attributes for the graduates in order to compete
                       for employment locally and internationally.

                   5.  VMGO was approved by the BOT/BOR.































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE











                                         PARAMETER B:




                                 DISSEMINATION AND




                                        ACCEPTABILITY

















































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE








               PARAMETER B – DISSEMINATION AND ACCEPTABILITY


               1.  SYSTEMS-INPUTS AND PROCESSES
                   ➢  Forms /Media Used in Disseminating the VMGO

                             Form/medium                       Type of Audience/Clientele

                    1.  classroom                         Students, Faculty, Staff, Visitors
                    2.  bulletin boards                   Students, Faculty, Staff, Visitors

                    3.  Student handbook                  Students, Faculty, Staff, Parents

                    4.  University website                All website viewers
                    5.  Social media pages                All social media users

                    6.  Program/Invites/leaflets          Participants, guests, others

                    7.  Posters and announcements         All students and visitors
                    8.  Office forms                      Students, faculty, staff

                    9.  Examination and Syllabi           Students and faculty

                    10. University and Campus             Students, faculty, staff, parents and
                        Newsletter                        other stakeholders























                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                              Photographs of Posted VMGO.
































                The University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives are posted in Room 107.










































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE











































                The University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives are posted in Room 108.




































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




































































                The University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives are posted in Room 106.










                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE











































                The University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives are posted in Room 201.






























                The University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives are posted in Room 202.






                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE









































                The University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives are posted in Room 203.































                The University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives are posted in Room 204.






                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE







































                The University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives are posted in Room 205.










































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE









































                            The University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives

                                         are posted in Room 105 (HRM Laboratory).






































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE










































                            The University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives

                                          are posted in Room 104 (Reading Room).































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE













































                            The University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives
                                       are posted in Room 103 (Computer Laboratory).



























                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




































































                        The BSIT students looking at the Campus Organizational Chart and discussing

                 the University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives posted in the pathway.








                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE














































                        Incoming new students looking at the Campus Offered Courses and discussing
                            the University Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives.





























                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE
































               BSIT student, requesting for a copy of grades for his private scholarship application at the Office
                   of the Campus Registrar (one of the frontline services of the campus) where the University
                   Vision and Mission and Campus Goals and Objectives are posted.


                   ➢  Documentary evidences on the participation of administrators, faculty,
                       staff, students and stakeholders in the in the formulation and review of the
                       VMGO.
                       A Multi-Campus Strategic Planning Workshop was held in December 19, 2001.

               The workshop was conducted to revise the existing Agenda for Development (1998-
               2006).  There was a thorough analysis of the internal and external environments of the

               vision, mission and values for change.
                       Participants included community leaders, alumni, faculty, staff, students, and

               other stakeholders.














                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                                                 The Planning Task Force




































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                       On  January  24,  2017,  a  University  wide  strategic  planning  was  held  at  the
               International  House  II  building  of  CvSU  main  campus.    One  of  the  highlights  of  the

               weeklong  event  is  the  review  of  the  existing  Vision,  Mission  and  objectives.    The
               participants of the event were from the administration, BOR/BOT members, Faculty, staff,

               Alumni, Cooperating Agencies, Local Government officials and other stake holders.


               2.  IMPLEMENTATION


                   ➢  VMGO  dissemination  activities,  and  provide  captions  to  all  pictures  (if

                       necessary)


                       Orientation program was always conducted for students and newly hired faculty

               members.  Part of the program is the discussion of the VMGO.
                       Dissemination of VMGO of the University was done by including it in most media

               and forms such as brochures, programs, invitations, bulletin of information, exams, office

               forms,  and  campus  newsletter.    Dissemination  of  VMGO  statements  were  also  done
               through non-printed materials such as the CvSU website and social media accounts.

               Faculty members are required to include the VMGOs of the university as part of their
               course  syllabi.    In this  manner, old  and  new  students are oriented/  re-oriented  in  the

               mission, vision, statements of the university every semester.
               The Department of Information Technology conducted meetings to discuss the programs

               educational program objectives/outcome and the target job for the graduates.  On May

               09,  2018,  the  T3  Campuses  conducted  the  review  and  revision  of  its  goals  and  the
               different department objectives.  Faculty members and students of the Department of

               Information  Technology  also  participated  in  the  study  on  awareness,  understanding,
               acceptance and perception of CvSu-Trece Martires City Campus stakeholders towards

               its Vision, Mission, Goals and Objectives.










                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE









































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



               SCREEN SHOT OF CVSU-TRECE MARTIRES CITY FACEBOOK PAGE














































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE


















































































                                                Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE


















































































  Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



               Inclusion of VMGO in the Course Syllabi

                                                                                                   VPAA-QF-10




                      CvSU Vision                   Republic of the Philippines        CvSU Mission
                     The premier university in                                      Cavite State University shall provide
                   historic Cavite recognized for   CAVITE STATE UNIVERSITY      excellent, equitable and relevant educational
                   excellence in the development   Tanza ǀ Trece Martires City ǀ Gen. Trias City Campus   opportunities in the arts, science and
                    of globally competitive and    235-7997 ǀ   410-5247 ǀ   437-0693   technology through quality instruction and
                    morally upright individuals.        www.cvsu.edu.ph          relevant research and development activities.
                                                                                   It shall produce professional, skilled and
                                                                                   morally upright individuals for global
                                                                                        competitiveness.
                                                 TRECE MARTIRES CITY CAMPUS
                                               DEPARTMENT OF ARTS AND SCIENCE
                                                      COURSE SYLLABUS
                                                   First Semester, AY 2020-2021
                                                                          Lecture  √
                Course    GNED 10    Course Title   Gender and Society   Type   Laboratory   Credit Units   3
                Code
                                                                          ___
                          This course critically examines the ways gender informs the social world in which we live. This course exposes the
                Course    "common-sense" world of gender around us; considers how we develop our gendered identities; explores the workings of
                Descriptio  the institutions that shape our gendered lives; and leads to an understanding of the relationship between gender and the
                n
                          social structure
                                                                         Lecture:
                Pre-      None                   Course Schedule         ______________________________
                requisites                                               Laboratory: ______________________________

                          Students are expected to live by and stand for the following University tenets:

                          TRUTH is demonstrated by the student’s objectivity and honesty during examinations, class activities and in the
                Core      development of projects.
                Values

                          EXCELLENCE is exhibited by the students’ self-confidence, punctuality, diligence and commitment in the assigned tasks,
                          class performance and other course requirements.



                                  Please see Course Syllabi Exhibit for more samples.
























                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                   ➢  Describe  how  members  of  the  Institution  (administrators,  faculty,  non-
                       teaching  staff  and  students)  can  articulate  procedures,  guidelines  and

                       protocols of the University/College.


                       Each member of the institution provided their own inputs to support the formulation

               and revision of the university vision and mission statements.  The administrators prepared
               the plans including workshop activities, analysis of both internal and external environment

               and synthesized the output of each workshop.  The faculty members and support staff
               performed  the  analysis  regarding  matters  in  middle  level  organization  will  serve  as

               supporting  inputs  to  enhance  the  existing  statements  presented  by  the  higher  level
               administration.    Being  the  main  clientele  of  the  institution,  the  students  can  provide

               feedback and suggestions to support the middle level organization.

                       The  members  of  the  institution  (administrators,  faculty,  non-teaching  staff,
               students)  can  also  articulate  procedures,  guidelines  and  protocols  of  the

               University/College.











































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



               3.  OUTCOMES


                   ➢  The  results  of  the  research  study  in  awareness  and  acceptability  of  the
                       VMGO by the different stakeholders



                       The study was conducted by J.A. Arbigoso, R,p/ Miranda and K. A. Paculan last
               June 2019 entitled Awareness, Acceptance and Perception of CvSU Trece Martires City

               Campus Stakeholders towards its Vision, Mission, Goals and Objectives.


                       Based on the result of the study conducted, the following conclusions were
               drawn:

                       1.  Internal stakeholders including students of different programs, faculty members

                          and staff are highly aware of the VMGO while external stakeholders such as
                          parents/guardians, alumni, cooperating agencies, snd other linkages are aware

                          of the campus VMGO.

                       2.  Internal stakeholders understand and greatly accept the VMGO while external
                          stakeholders understand and accept the VMGO.

                       3.  Both external and internal stakeholders agreed to the CvSU VMGO.
                       4.  There is a correlation between the awareness, acceptance and perception of

                          VMGO by the internal and external stakeholders.
                       5.  There is a significant difference between the internal and external

                          stakeholders level of awareness, acceptance and perception towards VMGO.





















                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE


















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE
















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                   ➢  The implementation of the VMGO and their congruence with educational
                       practices and activities.


                       Most of the universities and colleges were established by virtue of the national

               legislation.  Its mandate is to serve its service through the provision of quality and

               affordable education.  Aside from instruction, these learning institutions are mandated to
               perform research extension and production.

                       To meet the above functions every learning institution has to establish its own
               vision and mission that is in harmony with the national, regional, provincial and local

               development goals, thrusts, policies and directions.
                       Cavite State University Trece Martires City Campus has established similarly its

               goals in support with the University’s vision and mission.  With these in mind, all

               activities, plans and development directions are conducted, implemented and prepared
               toward the achievement of these guiding principles: National Economic Development

               Plan, RA 8468:  CvSU’s Legal and Educational Mandate, and Cavite State Univeristy

               (CvSU) Manual of Operations.


                       Guided by the University vision and mission and goals of the campus, the
               Program Intended learning Outcomes were also prepared.


                       To determine the congruence of all activities, plans, and development directions

               of the campus and its curricular programs with the University vision and mission, a

               continuing study on the acceptance and awareness of the vision and mission of the
               institution, goals of the campus, and objectives of the programs by its clients and other

               stake holders has been conducted.
                       The respondents of the study came from each of the target groups (students,

               administration, faculty, support staff, parents, alumni, cooperating agencies, linkages
               and  the general public) of the CvSU Trece Martires City Campus.









                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                   ➢  Instances and evidences to show that the program goals and objectives are
                       achieved


               For students, the goals and objectives are achieved through curricular activities and

               projects such as:

                   ❖  Thesis or Design Project
                   ❖  Seminars

                   ❖  Skills test (national TVET Qualification and Certification
                   ❖  Competition Winners

                   ❖  Paper and Poster Presentations
                   ❖  Recipient of Scholarship and Financial Assistance



               For faculty, the goals and objectives are achieved through:
                   ❖  Faculty profile (educational attainment of faculty members)

                   ❖  Seminars, Workshops and trainings attended

                   ❖  Research conducted
                   ❖  National TVET Qualification and Certification

                   ❖  Paper Presentation and Publication
                   ❖  Membership to Organizations


               For Staff, the goals and objectives are achieved through:

                   ❖  Successfully passed the Career Service Sub Professional and Professional

                       Examination
                   ❖  Non-academic profile (showing skills)

                   ❖  Seminars, workshops, trainings attended
                   ❖  National TVET Qualification and Certification















                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



































                                               Membership to Organizations







































                                      Attendance to Trainings, Seminar, Workshops



                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE

















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                                              National Certification (TESDA)


















































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



               4.  BEST PRACTICES


                       ➢  Cite as many best practices on Parameter B such as governance that
                          facilitate the accomplishment of the VMGO



                   1.  A system of dissemination and acceptance of VMGO
                   2.  The administrators, faculty, staff and students attend in-service trainings,

                       seminars and activities on awareness of VMGO
                   3.   The administrator discusses the relationship of the VMGO to faculty and staff

                       with their duties and responsibilities.
                   4.  The faculty and staff perform their function in consonance with the VMGO.

                   5.  Vision, Mission, goals and objectives are available in websites, bulletin boards,

                       and other forms of communication.
                   6.  The VMGO are widely disseminated to different agencies, institutions, industry

                       sector and other forms of communication.

                   7.  Inclusion of VMGO in school related documents and materials.
                   8.  Discussion of VMGO during program orientation and classroom orientation.

                       Faculty discusses to the students the importance of the implantation of VMGO.
                   9.  Inclusion of VMGO in CvSU 101 and NSTP classes.

                   10. Relevant studies were conducted regarding the VMGO of the University.




















                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                            THE QUEST FOR THE REALIZATION OF THE UNIVERSITY VISION AND MISSION




























































                   “Keeping the channel of communication wide open makes the CvSU Trece Martires City
                 Campus Department of Information Technology more significant and relevant to its students,
                                    faculty members, industry partners, and stakeholders”











                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE





























                          BSIT Department Chair meets with his faculty members (January 27, 2020)































                The BSIT 4  Year Students sharing their skills, knowledge and talent to the younger generation
                           th












                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                    Design Thinking Workshop Spearheaded by the Department of Information Technology


































                                                     November 15, 2019

































                                           th
                                     BSIT 4  Year Attended the Design Thinking Seminar






                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                                      CvSU -Trece Martires City Campus BSIT Students













































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE































               Student Orientation for SY 209-2020 with The University President Hernando D. Robles, Vice
               President for Academic Affairs Dr. Camilo A. Polinga and the Representatives from the LGUS of
               Trece Martires City, Gen. Trias City and Tanza.  Also in the picture are the Campus Administrator
               Prof. Noel A. Sedigo and Provincial Special Assistant to the Governor Vincent Bae. (August 2019)































                  Student Leaders of Trece Martires City attended the Leadership Training conducted by the
                                 Provincial Government of Cavite last December 2017, 2019









                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




































                                         th
                     Campus BLAST.. 14  Foundation Celebration of CvSU Trece last November 8, 2019
































                                            The Faculty and Staff of CvSU Trece







                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                       Research and Extension Week (September 18 – 19, 2019) CvSU, Main Campus






























































                      With some of our students who attended the activity.  JP Felizardo of BSIT won the
                                                    Photography Contest








                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE































                     BSIT Students Attended International, National and Local Seminars and Workshops













































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                Cavite State University Trece Martires City Campus through the initiative of the  Department of
                           Information Technology hosted the 2018 and 2019 Arudino Day in Cavite











































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                                          The Department’s Biggest Event to Date!!
                                                     Arduino Day 2019
                                                       April 28, 2019









































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE

















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE











































































                              Members of the Academic and Administrative Council graced the event.





                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE
















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE






































































                                                    th
                                  One of the BSIT 4  Year Students competed in the event.







                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



                                                    Some of the Exhibits










































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE


































                                                         The Winner












































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE

















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE



               5.  EXTENT OF COMPLIANCE
                   With the Recommendation for Area 1 – VMGO in the last Preliminary Survey Visit.












































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




















































































                      Area I: The Vision, Mission Goals and Objectives]]></page></pages></Search>
