<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Search><pages Count="718"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                            SYSTEM — INPUTS AND


                                           PROCESSES











               S.1.   The institution has an approved


                             and copyrighted Research


                             Journal.
























                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                            SYSTEM — INPUTS AND


                                           PROCESSES











               S.2    The institution has incentives for:


                             S.2.1 paper presentations




























                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[December 30,
               2019



               Dear Author/s,


               We are pleased to inform you that your paper has been accepted for ORAL PRESENTATION
               in INTERNATIONAL  RESEARCH  CONFERENCE  IN  COMPUTING,  ENGINEERING,  EDUCATION
               AND
               EDUCATION-TECHNOLOGY (IRCCEEE 2020)  an international conference  which will be held
               on
               January  9-10,  2020  at  LA  PIAZZA  HOTEL  AND  CONVENTION  CENTER,  Imelda  Roces
               Ave,
               Legazpi City, Philippines

               Your   paper   is   also   considered   for   publication   to   International   Journal   of   Scientific
               &  Technology  Research  (IJSTR)  (ISSN:  2277-8616,  a  Scopus-indexed  journal  since  2018)

               subject  to  the  conditions  and  standards  agreed  between  the  IRCCEEE  2020  and  the  IJSTR
               editor-in-chief.

               Please  revise  your  paper  according  to  the  suggestions  of  the  peer  reviewers  from  the
               previous  notification  you  have  received.    Your  paper  may  still  be  rejected  if  these
               instructions are not followed.



               Respectfully yours,
















               Rhowel M. Dellosa, D.Eng.


               Conference Chair, IRCCEEE

               2020]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Registration Steps:

                   1. Revise your paper according to the reviewer’s comments.
                   2. Format your paper according to the journal paper template then fill out the copyright
                      and registration form. You could get the template, copyright and registration form
                      from
                      the google docs folder named “IJTR template, copyright and registration form from
                      this link:
                      https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1QZfZfFid1LI4tJkVeUmpxbJkWjtwL4BD?usp=shari
                      ng
                   3. Use blue ink color pen to fill out the registration and copyright form.
                   4. In the registration form, just leave blank the “Paper number (IJSTR ref#)” item.
                   5. The payment for the registration and publication may be settled on or before January
                      6, 2020 or during the conference date for some exceptional cases.
                      A. Registration Fee for Presentation - P 5,000.00

                      B. Publication fee (Scopus-indexed Journal) -  P 13,
                          750.00 Bank: Legazpi Savings Bank
                          Bank Account Name: Bicol University Union of Faculty Association Incorporated
                          Bank Account Number:
                          00601111648 Or
                          Bank : BPI (Bank of the Phil Islands)
                          Acct Name: Rhowel Mercado Dellosa
                          Acct Number: 1529 - 1186 -23
                   6.   Create a folder named “paperID” (e.g. paper147) in the google link folder above. The
                      “ID” should be you’re a 2 or 3 digits number provided by the Easychair after you

                      have submitted the paper.
                   7. Copy the following files to your “paperID” folder.
                          a. Revised paper (filename: finalpaperID.doc   “e.g. finalpaper27.doc”)
                          b. Accomplished copyright form and registration form (filename:
                             copyrightpaperID.pdf  and registrationformID.pdf (e.g.
                             copyrightpaper27.pdf” and “registration formpaper27.pdf”) or you may also
                             use image file (e.g. copyrightpaper27.jpg” and “registration
                             formpaper27.jpg”)
                          c. Proof of payment (filename: proofofpaymentpaperID.pdf
                             “e.g. proofofpaymentpaper27.pdf or
                             proofofpaymentpaper27.jpg”)

                          d. Certificate of proof reading from your research department/authorized editor.
                          e. Copy of Turnitin report or any available plagiarism detection software of
                             your final paper (note: similarity index must be less than 15%).]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[PAPER ACCEPTANCE LETTER

               Paper Title        A Comparative Analysis of Image Processing Algorithms for Nutritional
                                  Deficiencies in Coffee Plants Classification
               Author/s Name      Khenilyn P. Lewis
               Presentation Type   Oral
               Cluster            Advances in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics and Allied
                                  Sciences

               CONGRATULATIONS!   We   are   happy   to   inform   you   that   your   paper   has   been   ACCEPTED   for
               presentation at  the  2 nd   National Conference  on  Science, Technology  and  Mathematics  Education.
               Your  paper  passed  the  peer-review  process  done  by  the  committee  organized  by  the  Faculty  of
               Science, Technology and Mathematics of the Philippine Normal University, Manila.

               Please  confirm  your  registration  in  our  conference  by  paying  the  registration  fee  through  the
               following details:
                             Account Name          PNU Trust and Refundable Fund
                             Account Number        1982 – 1011 – 11
                             Branch                Land Bank of the Philippines – YMCA Branch
                             Swift Code            TLBPPHMMXXX
               Early bird registration may be paid until November 6, 2019 and regular registration may be paid until
               November  29,  2019.  Please  pay  the  registration  fee  of  Php  1,500.00  (early  bird)  or  Php  1,800.00
               (regular) for PNU alumni and Php 1,800.00 (early bird) or Php 2,000.00 for non-alumni. Should you fail
               to  attend  on  the  scheduled  date,  your  registration  fee  will  not  be  refunded.  The  fee  covers  the
               following:  (2)  lunch,  am  and  pm  snacks,  conference  kit,  certificate,  entry  and  participation  to  a
               workshop.  For  other  additional  information  and  inquiries,  please  visit  the  following  websites  or
               communicate through our email address:
                   For inquiries                 pnustemconference@gmail.com
                   Official website              https://pnunationalconference.wodpress.com
                   Facebook page                 fb.me/NatConSTEM2019
               For those presenting orally, please prepare a pdf version of your presentation and submit through this
               form https://forms.gle/uMiQgy6SoPW5uTTE8. Please note that you will only be given a maximum of 15
               minutes for your presentation. Please submit the file not later than November 28, 2019 to the
               conference email address. Please use the following format as subject of your email:

                                            Format    “Surname_Initials”
                                            Example  DELACRUZ_J

               For  those  who  will  be  participating  as  poster  presenters,  here  are  the  details  and  some  reminders
               about the poster you are expected to bring during the conference:
                                Orientation         Portrait
                                Size                3 ft x 5 ft
                                Essential Content   Intro, Methods, Results, Conclusion
                                Reminders           Minimize text, use figures and illustrations

               See you at the conference! Thank you very much!

               Respectfully yours,

               Gladys C. Nivera, Ph.D.
               Conference Chair


               Paper Acceptance / 2 nd   National Conference on Science, Technology and Mathematics Education /
               November 30 - December 1, 2019 / Philippine Normal University - Manila]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[st
                                                                                 21 August 2017

               Dear Ms. Khenilyn Lewis,

               On behalf of the selection committee, I would like to congratulate you for being accepted to Tomorrow People
                              th
               Organization‘s 13 Annual Education and Development Conference and invite you to spend three days in the
                                                   th
                                               th
               beautiful city of Bangkok from March 5 – 7 2018 and present your paper entitled: ―Development of Language
               Translator From English Waray ―. This remarkable event aims to bring together academics as well as
               representatives from NGO and governmental sectors from different parts of the world who will have the unique
               opportunity to learn, interact and share ideas with the most distinguished educators and experienced professionals.

               Education and Development Conference 2018 attempts to answer multiple questions, meet the most diverse
               interests and to attract different groups of people. We will welcome scholars, corporate representatives,
               government agencies‘ representatives, NGO representatives and other individuals and organizations from   around
               the world. Being fully aware of just how the comprehensive understanding of this matter is important for
               successful and continuous development of every individual, organization and society as a whole, we have
               designed an event that will address the issues that we all have to face in transforming our ideas into workable,
               innovative and progressive projects. In order to achieve that, this 3 days event will include both exciting panel
               discussions and networking activities for educators, professionals and policy makers of all ages and from all  over
               the world.

               The cost of the Conference is 345 USD and includes: admission to all sessions, presentation of submitted paper,
               discussions, speakers, conference supplies and materials, copy of the official Conference proceedings, coffee
               breaks and lunches during the Conference, a networking night and a certificate issued by Tomorrow People
               Organization. The Conference fee does NOT include accommodation and airfare.

                                                         th
               A non refundable 120 USD deposit is due August 30 2017 and is required in order to secure your spot in the
               Conference at early bid registration rate, along with the confirmation form that can be found in the attached
                                                           th
               document. The remaining amount is due September 30 2017. Once your deposit is received and spot in the
               Conference secured, payment plans can be arranged. If you would like us to arrange hotel accommodation for
               you, we can offer you rooms in ―AETAS Lumpini‖ where the Conference will be take - at discounted rates that
               apply for our participants during the entire period of their stay. Accommodation is available at 90 USD for a
               deluxe room, per room per night, single or double, with breakfast and tax included.

               Please, find attached document with further details regarding EDC 2018 and a sponsor letter which you could
               use to aid your search for outside funding.  A number of participants have obtained funding from their home
               university or organization they work for.

               Again, congratulations for being selected to take part in this highly exciting and challenging international
               program! We are excited to have you as a participant in our Conference. Should you have any questions
               regarding the Conference, please do not hesitate to contact our EDC 2018 Organizing Team at
               contact@tomorrowpeople.org.

               Sincerely,

               Vladimir Mladjenovic
               Director


                            Tomorrow People Organization Dusana Vukasovica 73, 11 000 Belgrade, Serbia
                                        www.tomorrowpeople.org www.ed-conference.org]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[Education and Development Conference 2018
                                                th
                                                    th
                                      March 5 - 7 2018, Bangkok, Thailand

               Education and Development Conference 2018 is a three-day program, unlike most academic
               conferences. It aims to bring together scholars and students as well as experienced professionals
               willing to learn and share more about the topics related to Education and Development. It is open to
               all of those interested in gaining new knowledge as well as those who want to share their own
               research, achievements and experience.

               Education and Development Conference 2018 is intended to be a forum, discussion and networking
               place for academics, researchers, professionals, administrators, educational leaders, policy makers,
               industry representatives, advanced students, and others interested in the topics, providing resources
               and opportunities to interact with prominent leaders in the field and greatly expand on your global
               network of scholars and professionals

                      Dates
                                                                                           th
                                                                                        th
                         th
                       13 Annual Education and Development Conference will take place from 5 - 7 March 2018.
                                                                              th
                       All participants should arrive to ―AETAS Lumpini‖ on March 5 , before 2 pm, and are
                       expected to be in attendance during the entire Conference.

                      Location
                       Education and Development Conference 2018 will be held in Bangkok, Thailand. All the
                       sessions will take place in ―AETAS Lumpini‖ centrally located and easily accessible from
                       any point of the city.

                       AETAS Lumpini
                       1030/4 Rama 4 Road, Thungmahamek,
                       Satorn Bangkok 10120

                      Sessions time table
                                                                                                  th
                       Education and Development Conference 2018 will officially start on Monday, March 5 at 2
                                                          th
                       pm and will end on Wednesday, March 7 2017 at 2 pm consisting of one full day scheduled
                                 th
                                                                                  th
                                                                            th
                       activities (6 March) and two half day scheduled activities (5 and 7 March) including coffee
                       and lunch breaks in between the sessions.
                       The final Conference agenda will be available in February 2018 after the list of accepted
                       papers and confirmed presenters has been finalized.

                      Final Paper Submission- for presenters only
                       Please not that abstracts/ papers submitted with application are NOT automatically considered
                       for publication. If you want your abstract/ paper published in the official conference
                       proceedings publication (paper publication is NOT mandatory), please note that final
                                                 th
                       submission is due February 10 2018 in MS Word format, emailed to:
                       contact@tomorrowpeople.org in the following formatting:
                             A4 size paper;
                             Margins 1” on the top, bottom, left and right side;
                             Single line spacing;
                             Fonts:
                                 o   Title- Times New Roman 14 bold;
                                 o   Subtitles- Times New Roman 12 bold;
                                 o   Text- Times New Roman 12
                             Justify formatting;
                             Author/s’ name/s and affiliation under title;
                             Abstract of maximum 200 words on first page (under author/s’ name/s) or
                             Full paper starting from the second page.]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[   Presentations:
                       Oral presentations: Presenters are allocated a time slot for their presentation within an
                       appropriate panel. If the presentation include power point, video or/ and audio files, all
                       materials are to be uploaded to the conference computer in the venue, prior to the session.
                       Poster presentations: Presenters are responsible for designing and printing the posters in the
                       A1 vertical format (59.4cm x 84.1cm). Posters should be handled to the staff at registration
                       desk prior to the scheduled poster session.
                       Video presentations: Presenters are allocated time slot for their presentation that is to be
                       prepared either as a video or power point presentation slides, covered by voice

                      Accommodation
                       Price of the conference does NOT include accommodation. However, if you want us to  arrange
                       accommodation for you during your stay in Bangkok, we can offer you rooms in ―AETAS
                       Lumpini‖, at special discounted rate that applies for our participants. This is a  quality five stars
                       hotel located in one of Bangkok‘s best commercial areas, with easy access to both downtown
                       and the international airport.

                       EDC 2018 participants are entitled to special discounted rate of 90 USD for a deluxe room,  per
                       room per night, single or double, with breakfast and tax included. If you want us to book a
                       room for you, please specify the dates of your stay in the hotel in participant confirmation sheet
                       (attached as a separate document and sent along with invitation to the conference), once your
                       flight itinerary has been finalized. Discounted rate applies for the entire period of your stay in
                       the hotel, and may include dates before and after the conference as well.

                       Please, note that this rate applies only for bookings made through Tomorrow People
                       Organization and is subject to terms and conditions. Cancellations made less than 14 days
                       prior to scheduled check in the hotel may result in one night cancelation charge, as per
                       hotel’s policy. Costs of accommodation are to be settled to Tomorrow People Organization as
                       we are making final accommodation arrangements on behalf of the entire group in order to
                       secure discounted group rates.  Bookings and payments made directly with the hotel are subject
                       to regular walk in rate that is over 200 USD per night.

                       Alternatively, participants are also welcome to arrange accommodation on their own, in
                       another hotel, according to their preference.

                      Meals
                       Lunch and coffee breaks during the Conference are included in the price of the conference.

                      Costs
                       The cost of the program is 345 USD. This price includes: conference kit, admission to all the
                       sessions, presentations of submitted papers, discussions, lunch and coffee breaks during the
                       Conference, materials for following the sessions, publication of submitted paper (for
                       presenters), copy of the official conference proceedings publication and certificate issued by
                       Tomorrow People Organization. This price does not include airfare and accommodation.
                       Accommodation will be provided on request and is to be paid separately.

                                                                         th
                       A non refundable deposit of 120 USD is due August 30 2017. It is required in order to
                                                                                           th
                       secure your spot in the Conference. The 225 USD balance is due September 30 2017.
                       Payment plans can be arranged after your deposit is received and spot in the Conference
                       secured.

                       You may send your deposit either by bank wire. We are also able to accept Western Union
                       transfers. Credit card payments are accepted online directly through www.paypal.com secure
                       system. Please contact us regarding your payment plan for further information and
                       payment instructions.]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[Other Important Information

               Passport: Valid passport is required to enter the Kingdom of Thailand. If you do not have a passport, please
               apply for one immediately.
               Visa: Participants from most countries do not need a visa to enter The Kingdom of Thailand if their stay is not
               longer than 30 days. However, please double-check your visa requirements with the nearest Thai embassy,
               consulate, or representative office. If you require a visa, please let us know so that we could provide necessary
               visa assistance through our local Thai partner agent.
               Late and onsite payments: Please, note that early bid registration fee applies for the payments made until the
               deadlines stated in the acceptance letter only. For payments made after the deadline stated in the acceptance
               letter, the regular admission fee of 390 USD will apply as well as for onsite payments; Onsite registration is
               subject to availability of spots. We cannot guarantee the availability for applicants who have not secured their
               spot in advance.
               Accompanying   persons: Please,  note that  only registered delegates  are admitted to the  meeting room,  due to
               limited space available and accompanying persons will not be allowed in the meeting room, unless registered for
               the conference.
               Sightseeing  tours: There will be several  optional tours organized during the three day  program which can be
               booked  onsite.  For  the  convenience  of  the  participants,  dedicated  tour  operator  desk  will  be  provided  for  any
               additional information and tour you may want to book for yourself or accompanying persons traveling with you.
               Student observers: Full time students attending the conference as observers should submit the proof of their   full
               time student status in order to avail on student registration fee.  This can be a scanned copy of the student card, or
               a letter from their university scanned and emailed to: contact@tomorrowpeople.org.
               Insurance: Although the cost of medical care in Thailand is not expensive, we strongly recommend having an
               international recognized medical insurance that can be purchased at your local travel agent.
               Outside Funding: A number of our participants receive some sort of funding from their home university. If you
               are studying or working at the university, please check if they have funds to support attendance of international
               conferences. If you are employed, check with your organization whether they could sponsor your participation.
               You may also want to contact local service organizations, such as Rotary Club.
               Please find the letter of support in a separate document attached.]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                            SYSTEM — INPUTS AND


                                           PROCESSES











               S.2  The institution has incentives for:


                             S.2.2 journal publication




























                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="99"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="100"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="101"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="102"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="103"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="104"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="105"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="106"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="107"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="108"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="109"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="110"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="111"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="112"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="113"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="114"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="115"><![CDATA[INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF SCIENTIFIC & TECHNOLOGY RESEARCH VOLUME 9, ISSUE 04, APRIL      ISSN 2277-
          2020                                                                                     8616

               Classification And Detection Of Nutritional

               Deficiencies In Coffee Plants Using Image


                    Processing And Convolutional Neural

                                            Network (CNN)



                                           Khenilyn P. Lewis, Juancho D. Espineli

        Abstract:  Coffee  farmers  or  growers  have  difficulty  in  classifying  nutritional  deficiencies  in  coffee  plants.  Proper  detection  of  these
        nutritional  deficiencies  could  help  them  in  giving  proper  intervention  to  plants.  The  study  was  conducted  to  classify  and  detect  the  nutritional
        deficiencies in coffee plants  using  image  processing  and  Convolutional  Neural  Network  (CNN).  Once  the  nutritional  deficiency  is  identified,
        the  prototype  will  display recommended fertilizer for the plant. One thousand images with eight nutritional deficiencies were used in the study
        namely, Boron (B), Calcium (Ca), Iron (Fe), Nitrogen (N), Phosphorus (P), Potassium (K), Magnesium (Mg) and Zinc (Z). The study covered the
        four  varieties  of  coffee  named  Arabica,  Robusta,  Excelsa  and  Liberica  existing  in  the  Philippines.  The  capturing  of  images  for  testing  and
        training the dataset were  done in coffee farms and nurseries in Cavite State University, National Coffee Research, Development and Extension
        Center (NCRDEC) and Amadeo, Cavite. Experimental and development  research designs were  used.  Image  processing  techniques was  utilized
        in converting  the  images  into  grayscale  and  binary  values  for threshold  and  segmentation.  Convolutional  Neural  Network  (CNN)  provides
        the  predicted  nutritional  deficiencies  in  the  coffee  plants  through classification and detection. Results shows that CNN has a high accuracy
        in  detecting  and  classifying  the  nutritional  deficiencies  in  coffee  plants.  The  prototype  was  evaluated,  and  results  shows  that  it  is  an  effective
        alternative for classifying and detecting the nutritional deficiencies in coffee plants.

        Index Terms: classification, coffee, convolutional neural network, detection, image processing, machine learning, nutritional deficiencies
                                            ——————————      ——————————

        1 INTRODUCTION                                        Adequate    nutrients    are    essential  to    plants    for  growth.
        Coffee  is  known  as  the  most  important  crop  commodity  in   During  the  vegetation  to  pre-flowering  of  coffee  plants,
        the world  [1].  People  around  the  world  drink  two  billion    Nitrogen and Potassium  promote   the  growth   of  tissues
        cups  of coffee  every  day. A total  of  25  million  of  families    in   new  plants. Calcium is  for  leaf growth  that provides
        depend    for  coffee  for  living  specifically  for  business  or  as   high    yield    for  plants.  Magnesium  serve  as  fuel  for
        growers.  For  the  last    15    years,    43    percent    of    coffee    developing tissues and Sulfur to maximize the growth of the
        consumption  has  arisen worldwide [2]. The first coffee tree   plant  through  protein.  During  the  post    flowering    to    berry
        in  Philippines  was  planted  in    Lipa,    Batangas    and    in     formation,  Nitrogen  and  Potassium serve  as  maintenance
        1860s   coffee   are   exported   to America. Batangas reigned   for  plant  growth  and  support  berry strength.  Calcium  is
                                                              for  strong  healthy  tissues.  Magnesium and  micronutrients
        the coffee industry in the country and   was   followed   by
        Cavite   in   planting   coffee   in   1876. However, due to insect   are  for  growth  maintenance  and  berry production. These
        manifestation coffee trees in Batangas was  destroyed  and    nutrients  are  needed  by  the  plants  in  their  berry  expansion
        few of  surviving  trees  was  transferred  to Cavite.  As  of    and  berry  maturity  [9].  These  nutrients  are  in  need
        2019,  Batangas    produces    13    percent  of  the  coffee    necessary   for   the   growth    of  coffee    plants.   A    healthy
        supply    in    CALABARZON    (Region    IV-A)    and    Cavite   coffee  plants  could  maximize  the  number  of  yields  that
        produces  67  percent  [3].  The  climate  and  soil  condition  in   may  produce.    However,    identification    of    nutritional
        the Philippines  are  suitable  for  planting  coffee.  Because  of    deficiencies    is  done    manually    by        the    coffee
        this,  the  country  could  produce  the  four  varieties  of  coffee   growers    or    experts.  Characteristics  and  symptoms  of
        namely,  (Coffea  arabica),  Liberika  (Coffea  liberica),
        Arabica                                               plants  in  terms  of  nutritional  deficiencies    are    usually    like
        and  Robusta  [5].  Arabica  is  the  most  expensive  variety    other    plants.    Coffee    growers    or  farmers  should  have
        Excelsa
        of  coffee  and  usually  cultivated  in  high  elevation  areas.   enough knowledge to these symptoms so that   they   could
        Liberika (Kapeng   Barako)   is   known   for   strong   flavor     perform    the    correct    interventions    [12].  Numerous
        and    aroma.  Excelsa    has    bigger    berries    compared    to   applications of digital image processing have been recorded
        Arabica.    Robusta    is  being  used  for  expresso  and  instant   in    different    field.    Digital    image    processing    is    the
        coffee mixes. Moreover, Robusta  is  the  commonly  grown    manipulation    of    images    using    the    computer    [10].    It
        variety    coffee    in    country  which  has  a  total  production  of   converts the physical images into corresponding images and
        69 percent in 2015.  Followed by  Arabica  which  contributed    extract the information    using    algorithms.    Digital    image
        24  percent  and  Excelsa  and Liberica [6].          processing includes   image   collection,   image   processing
                                                              and   image analysis  [11].  This  study  was  conducted  to
                                                              utilize    an    image  processing    technique,    implement
                                                              Convolutional        Neural  Network  (CNN)  and  measure  the
                                                              effectiveness  for  classifying  and  detecting  nutritional
        •  Khenilyn    P.    Lewis    is    currently    pursuing    doctor    in     deficiencies in coffee plants.
           information   technology   in   AMA   University-Quezon   City,
           Philippines.  She  is  also  working    as    a    faculty    member    in    2 RELATED WORK
           Cavite    State    University,    Cavite,  Philippines.  E-mail:   This  section  discusses  the  related  works  in  image
           khenilyn@yahoo.com                                 processing and  algorithms  as  basis  for  classifying  and
        •  Juancho D. Espineli is currently the dean of the school of
           studies   in   AMA   University-   Quezon   City.   E-  detecting    the  nutritional  deficiencies  in  coffee  plants.  A
           graduate
           mail: ineli@gmail.co                               neural  network  was  trained  to  detect  the  nutritional
           jcesp
           m
                                                              deficiencies  in  coffee  plants.  As  a    result,    a    Kappa
                                                              coefficient   of   0.96   for   Nitrogen   and
                                                                                                               20]]></page><page Index="116"><![CDATA[INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF SCIENTIFIC & TECHNOLOGY RESEARCH VOLUME 9, ISSUE 04, APRIL      ISSN 2277-
          2020                                                                                     8616
        Phosphorus   deficiency   and   0.92   for   Boron.   It   was    design,  development  and  evaluation.  The  approach  is  to
        also  observed  that  the  higher  the  number  of  images  the  meet  the  consistency  and  effectiveness  of  the  system  or
        higher the result for  Kappa  [8]. Digital image  processing of  prototype  to    be    developed    [18].    It    also    answers    the
        355  images with   nutritional   deficiencies   in   coffee    questions    of    why,  how,    what    and    whom    as    it
        plants    such    as magnesium,  manganese  and  iron  was   includes    the    process    of  development  and  evaluation.
        utilized  in  the  study. Results  shows  an  accuracy of 67.5   Since  it  develops  and  evaluates,  to  is  intended  to  provide
        percent. The  image  was pre-processed   from  RGB  image.   justification in works and progress to contribute   in   different
        The    visual    features    are  extracted  to  the  image  and  then  fields   and   areas   of   knowledge.   In addition, it delivers the
        built  using  a  Random  forest  model.  The  Random  Forest  specific  and  general  processes  of  pre-  test  and  post-test
        algorithm  was  used  to  classify  the  nutritional  deficiencies  research design [17].
        present  in  the  coffee  plants  [12].  Image  processing  was
        used  in  identifying  and  classifying  disease  in  plant.        The     3.2 Research Environment
        steps     include        pre-processing,    training        and   The  coffee  leaves  used  in  the  training  and  testing  of  data
        identification.  Pixel  similarity  was  the  basis  of  the  algorithm   were  collected    at  the  National  Coffee  Research,
        for segmentation  in  identifying  the  leaf  disease  in  the    Development  and  Extension  Center  (NCRDEC),  Indang,
        plant. An algorithm  was  proposed   that does  not employ   Cavite and coffee farms in  Amadeo,  Cavite.  The  NCRDEC
        segmentation. Rather, the Principal Component Analysis was   is  the  national  leader  in coffee research and development
        directly applied to RGB colors of the leaf images. The study   in  the  country  as  designated  by    the    Department    of
        used  a  Multilayer  Perceptron  (MLP)  Neural  Network  with   Agriculture    Research    Bureau    of  Agricultural  Research
                                                              (DA-BAR).
        one  hidden  layer  and  determined    if    the    sample    has
        disease  or  not  [14].  Image  is defines   as   two   dimensional    3.3 Respondents of the Study
        array    in    forms    of    rows    and  columns  represents  as  The  respondents  of  the  study  were  the  coffee  growers
        function, F(x,y).                                     and farmers in Amadeo, Cavite since they are the end user
                                                              of the study.    To    evaluate    the    functionality    of    the
                                                              prototype,  Information  Technology  experts  were  also
                                                              included.
                                                              3.4 Data Preparation
                                                              The  study  used  1000  images  of  coffee  leaves  with
                                                              nutritional deficiencies  in  Boron,  Calcium,  Iron,  Nitrogen,
                                                              Phosphorus,  Potassium,    Magnesium    and    Zinc.    The
                                                              classified  nutritional deficiencies   were   manually   identified
                                                              and   verified   by   an agriculturist and soil expert.

                                                              3.5 Testing and Evaluation
                                                              In    evaluation,    the    study    used    a    researcher-made
                      Fig.1. Image rows and                   evaluation form   based   from   ISO/IEC   25010:2011   in
                      columns
                                                              terms    of    its  functionality,    performance    efficiency,
        Pixel  is  used  to  denote  elements  in  digital  image   usability,    reliability, maintainability and portability.
        processing.  Image    processing    has    three    steps.  First,
        importing    images  using        image    acquisition        tools.
        Second,    analysis    and manipulation  of  image.  Last,  is    3.6 Nutritional Deficiencies
        the  output  image  or  result based  from  analysis  [15].  In    Healthy  plants are  visually  shown  in leaves  which  are  alive
        terms  of  nutrients,  the  study covered the macronutrients   in green  color.  In  this  study,  eight  nutritional  deficiencies
        and  micronutrients.  Macronutrients  are    chemical    elements    were found during the data gathering [16].
        representing  the  96%  of  the  plants’ composition.    Some
        macronutrients        are    Nitrogen    (N),  Phosphorus  (P),             TABLE 1
        Potassium  (K),  Calcium  (Ca),  and  Sulfur  (S).  Some        NUTRITIONAL DEFICIENCIES IN COFFEE
        micronutrients  are  Boron  (B),  Iron  (Fe)  and  Zinc  (Z).  The          PLANTS
        images  are  used  for  training  KNN,  Naïve  Bayes  and
        Neural Network  classifiers.  The  experimental  results  show
        that  the developed  procedure  has  a  high  accuracy,  being
        the  better results  associated  to  the  identification  of  Boron
        (B)  and  Iron (Fe) deficiencies [14].

        3 PROPOSED METHOD
        This    section    discusses    the    research    design,
        nutritional  deficiencies  and  proposed  method  in  classifying
        and detecting the nutritional deficiencies in coffee plants.

        3.1 Research Design
        The      study    utilized        experimental-developmental
        research designs.  Identification of the nutritional deficiency of
        the  coffee  based  on  its  leaf’s  appearance  was  done.  The
        identification of nutritional deficiencies was collaborated with
        agriculturists and soil  expert.  Developmental  research  is  a
        study  that  includes




                                                                                                               20]]></page><page Index="117"><![CDATA[INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF SCIENTIFIC & TECHNOLOGY RESEARCH VOLUME 9, ISSUE 04, APRIL      ISSN 2277-
          2020                                                                                     8616
        3.7 Proposed Approach                                 device and output will be displayed in the 7-inched
        The    study    utilized    the    image    processing    and   LCD.
        Convolutional Neural  Network  in  classifying  and  detecting
        the  nutritional deficiencies in coffee plants.







           Fig. 2. Steps in classifying and detecting the
                       nutritional deficiencies in coffee plants

        Figure 2 shows the first step in image acquisition followed
        by  image    pre-processing.  Pattern    extraction    will    take
        place  to classify  and  detect  the  nutritional  deficiency
        present  in  the coffee leaves.
                                                                           Fig. 5. Architectural model of the study

                                                               3.8 Materials
                                                               Materials  used  in  the  study  are  Raspberry  Pi  4,  7
                                                               inched  Liquid  Crystal  Display  (LCD),  SD  card,  Logitech
                                                               cameras with maximum  resolution  of  2048  x  1536  pixels
                                                               in  .jpeg  format, Power  Supply  and  Sintra  Board.  Python
                                                               was  also  used  in coding preparation.


                                                              3.9 Classification
                                                              Convolutional    Neural    Network    (CNN)    is    the    most
                                                              commonly  wide  algorithm  for  image  processing,  object
                Fig. 3. Conceptual framework of the           detection and the like.  In  CNN  image  classification,  images
                study                                         are    captured    and  processed    or    classify    under    certain
        Figure   3   shows   the    proposed    approach   in   classifying   categories. In  this  study, the  captured  images  of  coffee
        and  identifying    the    nutritional    deficiencies    in    coffee   leaves    are    categorized    under  the  eight  nutritional
        plants.  The images  of  coffee  leave  were  taken  using  two   deficiencies.
        (2)  Logitech cameras. The leave should be place inside the
        prototype  and  should  be  seen  in  the  display.  Once  the
        images are captured it will  be  saved  in  a  SD  card  as
        storage.    During    the    image  processing,  the    images    is
        converted    from  RGB    to    grayscale.  The  resize  image  in
        grayscale is converted into vector input.
        Once  the  images  are  in  vector  format,  tensor  flow  will  be
        used in   the   Convolutional   Neural   Network   (CNN).   The
        CNN
        algorithm    will  classify  and    detect  the    input  images.  The
        LCD will be used to display the detected nutritional deficiency      Fig. 6. CNN
        in the                                                               architecture
        leaves. It will be  the  basis for  the  recommended fertilizer in  The  first  layer  of  CNN  is  extracting  the  features  of  images
        the plant.                                            in  the  convolution.  Convolution  handles  the  image  features
                                                              and pixels of the input data using image matrix or filter matrix.

                                                              3.10 Evaluation of the Proposed Algorithm
                                                              The  evaluation  of  the  prototype  in  classifying  and  detecting
                                                              the  nutritional    deficiencies    in    coffee    plants    is    done
                                                              using  the formula (1) [13].


                                                                                                (1)




                                                              Where:
                                                              D = Detection
                         Fig. 4. Block                        Accuracy t = Ground
                         diagram                              Truth
        Figure 4 shows the block diagram of the prototype. The   r = Result
        power                                                   The  Detection  Accuracy  (D)  is  the  overall  accuracy  of
         supply  and  USB  cameras  are  attached  to  the  raspberry  pi
                                                           the
                                                                                                              2078
                                                        IJSTR©2020
                                                        www.ijstr.org]]></page><page Index="118"><![CDATA[INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF SCIENTIFIC & TECHNOLOGY RESEARCH VOLUME 9, ISSUE 04, APRIL      ISSN 2277-
          2020                                                                                     8616
        image detection process. The ground truth (t) is determined
        by  the    actual    number    of    leaves    with    nutritional
        deficiencies.  In determining  the  nutritional  deficiencies,  the
        researchers  with agriculturists and soil expert manually verify
        the leaves. Lastly, result (r) is determined by the number of
        leaves with nutritional deficiencies detected by the algorithm.
        3.11 Statistical Treatment of Data
        After  data  collection,  the  raw  scores  were  tallied  and
        tabulated  in  a  columnar  sheet  using  Microsoft  Excel.  To
        determine  if  the  prototype    complies    with    the    ISO,  the
        evaluation  responses from  the  respondents  were  used  as
        basis  from  which  the weighted mean was utilized.




               Where:    =the computed mean                         Fig. 8. Inside the prototype and image
                      f=frequency of the                            acquisition
                      response                                Figure  8  shows  the  inside  view  of  the  prototype  with
                                                              Excelsa leave  variety.  The  raspberry  is  located  to  the
                           =sum of all the products of f and x
                                                              upper    part  together  with  cables  and  wires,  cameras  are
                                  =sum of all the             used to capture data  and  LED  lights  to  provide  equal  and
                                subjects/respondents
        3.12 Scaling and Quantification of Data               balance  lightning inside the device.
        The data gathered using a rating scale which ranged from 1
        to 5,  of  which  five  (5)  is  the  highest and  one  (1)  is  the
        lowest. Each  score  range  has  a  corresponding  numerical
        scale  and appropriate verbal descriptions shown in the Table
        2.
                              TABLE 2
                    SCORING AND QUANTIFICATION OF
                                DATA











                                                                        Fig. 9. Sample screen capture of
                                                                        leaves
                                                              Figure  9  shows  the  sample  screen  input  a  leave  in
        4 RESULT AND DISCUSSION                               the prototype.  Two  cameras  were  used  to  capture  the
                                                              leave depending  to  its  size  because  there  are  leaves  that
        The    researchers    used    the    experimental    and    are  too large.  The  detected  nutritional  deficiency  will  be
        developmental  method    in    this    study.    The    leaves    with    displayed together with the recommended fertilizer.
        nutritional    deficiencies  were  manually  verified  by
        agriculturists and soil expert.


















                                                                     Fig. 10. Coffee leave in different threshold
                                                                     value
                          Fig. 7. The
                                                              Figure  10  shows  the  different  images  in  threshold  value
                          prototype                           of  Robusta    with    Nitrogen    deficiency.  The    threshold    in
        Figure  7  shows  the  prototype  and  screen  loading  of    grayscale  format    will    provide    pattern    to    the    algorithm
        the software. The device is directly connected to a power   together  with  the
        source
        either in a 220 volt or a power
        bank.                                                     resize  values. These  details  were  used  for  the  convolutions.
                                                                                                             2079
                                                                                                        IJSTR©2020
                                                                                                       www.ijstr.org]]></page><page Index="119"><![CDATA[INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF SCIENTIFIC & TECHNOLOGY RESEARCH VOLUME 9, ISSUE 04, APRIL      ISSN 2277-
          2020                                                                                     8616
        The    prototype    was    tested    by  capturing    the    suspected
        leaves with  nutritional  deficiencies.  The  device  was  set  up    8
        and  the captured  images  was  verified  by  an  agriculturist
                                                               [1].  R.  Le  Pelley.  ―Pest  of  Coffee‖.  Longmans,  Green
        and  soil expert. The results of testing for classification and   REFERENCES
        detection of nutritional deficiencies were presented in table 3.   and Co. Ltd, London and Harlow. 19690307548. 2019.
                                                               [2].  J. Siddle & V. Venema. ―Saving Coffee from
                                                                   Extinction‖. BBC News Magazine. 2015.
                               TABLE 3
                                                                   globalwarming-sowhat.com
                                                               [3].  A. Papa. ―Strengths and Challenges of Philippine
                  SUMMARY OF THE DETECTION
                                                                   Produc
                                                                   Coffee tion‖.
                  ACCURACY
                                                                                                  2019.PressReade
                                                                     https://www.pressreader.com/philippines/agriculture
                                                                   r,  - 9ggr/20190301/282368336064710
                                                               [4].   Philippine  Statistics  Authority  (PSA).  ―Major  Non-
                                                                   Food
                                                                   and Industrial Crops‖. Quartely Bulletin. 2019
                                                               [5].
                                                               [6].   Philippine Coffee. Philippine Coffee Board.
                                                                   2019.
                                                                   Philippine  Coffee  Industry  Roadmap  2017-
                                                               [7].   2019. Department of Agriculture. 2017
                                                               [8].J. Sosa, J. Ramirez, L. Vives & G. Kemper. ―An
                                                                   D. Nosowitz. Is Coffee Really Going Extinct? 2019.
                                                                   for
                                                               Algorithm    Detection    of    Nutritional    Deficiencies    from
                                                                   Digital  Images    of  Coffee    Leaves    Based    on
                                                                   Descriptors    and  Neural    Networks‖.    2019    XXII
                                                                   Symposium    on    Image,  Signal  Processing  and
                                                                   Artificial Vision (STSIVA)
                                                               [9].
                                                                   Y.  Tanzania.  ―Role  of  Nutrients  by  Growth  Stage
        Table  3  shows  the  detection  and  classification  results  of    Coffe‖e.   2019.   Yara,
                                                                   in
                                                                            https://www.yara.co.tz/crop-
        the  study.  Detection  accuracy  for  Boron  (92.5%),  Calcium     nutrition/coffee/role-of-nutrients-by-growth-stage-
        (90.2%), Iron    (90.2%),    Nitrogen    (93.7%),    Phosphorus      in- coffee/
        (93.0%),                                               [10]. Eduardo  A.B. da  Silva, Gelson  V. Mendonça.
        Potassium  (90.00%),  Sulfur  (90.1%)  and  Zinc  (92.20%).   ―Digital   Processing‖.   Electrical
                                                                   Image
        The  overall    detection    accuracy    is    91.49    percent.    The    The Handbook. 2005      Engineerin
                                t
        result  of evaluation was ―Srongly Agree‖ conducted by end   [11]. L. Sun. ―Asphalt mix homogeneity‖. Structural
                                                                                             g
        users and Information  Technology  experts.  It  implies  that    Behavior
                                                                   of Asphalt Pavements, 2016
        the    used    of  image    processing    techniques    and     [12].  D.    Monsalve,    M.    Trujillo,    &    D.    Chaves.
        Convolutional   Neural Network (CNN) is an effective way of   ―utomatic Classification   of   Nutritional   Deficiencies
                                                                    A
        detecting and classifying the nutritional deficiencies in coffee   in   Coffee Plants‖.  6th  Latin-American  Conference
        plants.                                                    and    Electronic   Media     (LACNEM
                                                                   on  Networked
        5 CONCLUSIONS
                                                                     .    2015)
        The    study    proposed    a    model    for    classifying    and    [13]. S.   M.   D.   Lainez,   &   D.     Gonzales.
                                                                   doi:10.1049/ic.2015.0317
        detecting nutritional deficiencies in coffee plants using image   B.                  ―utomated
                                                                                               A
        processing and    Convolutional    Neural    Network    (CNN).      Network‖.  2019  IEEE  4th  International  Conference
                                                                   Fingerlings  Counting  Using  Convolutional
        Nutritional deficiencies  in  Boron,  Calcium,  Iron,  Nitrogen,                                    Neura
                                                                   on
        Phosphorus,  Potassium,    Magnesium    and    Zinc    were    Computer   and    Communication
                                                                                              l
        correctly  classified using   the   proposed   algorithm.   Based       (ICCCS).   Systems
                                                                   doi:10.1109/ccoms.2019.8821746 Plant  Leaf  Disease
                                                               [14].  S.  Kamlapurkar.  ―Detection  of
        on   the   result   of evaluation, CNN provide a high level of
        accuracy in terms of detecting  and  classifying  the  nutritional   Using  Image    Processing    Approach‖.    International
        deficiencies  in  coffee plants. High accuracy for classification   Journal    of  Scientific    and    Research    Publications,
        can be obtained using numerous  numbers  of  images.  The    Volume  6,  Issue 2, February 2016. ISSN 2250-3153
        level    of    detection    and  classification    could    also    be    [15]. R. Gonzales. ―Digital Image Processing Basics‖. 2019
        acquired  depending  the  size  of leaves, the higher threshold   [16]. M.   Nagao,   K.   Kobayashi   &   G.   Yasuda.
        value for smaller leaves.                              ―Mineral
                                                                   Deficiency in Coffee‖. 1986. Research Extension
                                                                   Series.
        6 FUTURE WORK                                              ISSN 0271-9916
        The  researchers  suggest  performing  deeper  researchers    [17]. K. Klaassen, &, K. Kortland. ―Developmental
        for CNN and image processing with regards to coffee. Also,   Research‖.
        this  research  can  be  improved  in  terms  of  portability  and   2015. 10.1007/978-94-007-2150-0_155.
        innovative collaboration with another platform technologies.   [18]. R.   Richey  &   N.  Wayne.   ―Developmental       S.    Al-
                                                               [19]. S.    Albawi,    T.    A.    Mohammed    &
                                                                   Zawi. (2017). ―Understanding    of    a    convolutional
                                                               research‖.
                                                                   Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.2004. pp.1099-1130  on
                                                                   neural  network‖.  2017  International  Conference
        7 ACKNOWLEDGEMENT
                                                                   Engineering
                                                                   and
        The  researchers  would  like  to  acknowledge  the  help  of
        AMA University-Quezon   City,   Cavite   State   University,       (ICET).                       Technolo
                                                                   doiBoulent,  S.  Foucher  &  J.  Théau.
                                                                   gy :10.1109/icengtechnol.2017.8308186
        National  Coffee        Research,        Development        and      [20]. J.
        Extension    Center (NCRDEC),   Office   of   the   Provincial     ―Convolutional Neural Networks for the Automatic
                                                                   Identification of Plant  Plant
        Agriculturist-    Trece  Martires  City,  Cavite,  Municipal   Diseases‖. Front        Sci.
                                                                                      2019;10:941.
        Agriculturist  of  Amadeo,  Cavite  and  Commission  on  Higher     doi:10.3389/fpls.2019.0094
        Education (CHED) K12 unit.                             [21].  1  R.A.Flores, B. M. M. N. Borges, H. J. Almeida & R.
                                                                   De Mello Prado. ―Growth and nutritional disorders of
                                                                   coffee
                                                                                                               20]]></page><page Index="120"><![CDATA[INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF SCIENTIFIC & TECHNOLOGY RESEARCH VOLUME 9, ISSUE 04, APRIL      ISSN 2277-
          2020                                                                                     8616
             cultivated    in        nutrient    solutions    with
             suppressed  macronutrients‖.    Journal    of    Plant
             Nutrition,               39(11),     1578–1588.
             doi:10.1080/01904167.2016.1161777
                                                     A
         [22].  S.  Hemlata,  S.  Shalinz  &  G.  Seema.  ―  Brief
             Overview on   Data   Mining   Survey‖.   International
             Journal   of Computer   Technology   and   Electronics
             Engineering (IJCTEE) Volume 1, Issue 3
                                                       P
         [23]. W.    Jeon    &    R.    Sang-Yong.    (2017).    ―lant
             Leaf  Recognition  Using  a  Convolution  Neural
             Network‖. The
             International    Journal    of    Fuzzy    Logic    and
             Intelligent     Systems.       17.       26-34.
             10.5391/IJFIS.2017.17.1.26.
         [24]. G.  P.  Zhang. ―Neural  Networks  For  Data  Mining‖.
             Data Mining   and   Knowledge   Discovery   Handbook,
             419–
             444. doi:10.1007/978-0-387-09823-4_21
         [25].  C.    Zhang,    P.    Zhou,    C.    Li,    &    L.    Liu.  ―
                                                          A
             Convolutional  Neural    Network    for    Leaves
             Computing   and    Communications;
             Recognition    Using    Data  Augmentation‖.  2015  IEEE
             Autonomic         Dependable, and    Secure
             International  Conference  on  Computer
             Intelligenc       Computing;               and
                                                        and
             e                 Pervasive
             Information   Technology;   Ubiquitous
             Computing. doi:10.1109/cit/iucc/dasc/picom.2015.318
         [26]. N. M. Yusoff, I. S. Abdul Halim, N. E. Abdullah & A.
         A.
             Ab.       Rahim.  ―Real-time    Hevea     Leaves
             Diseases
             Identification  using  Sobel  Edge Algorithm  on  FPGA:
             A  Preliminary  Study‖.  2018  9th  IEEE  Control  and
             System Graduate    Research
                                Colloquium        (ICSGRC).
             doi:10.1109/icsgrc.2018.8657603
         [27]. A.  P.  Marcos,  N.  L.  S.  Rodovalho  &  A.  R.
         Backes.
             ―Coffee  Leaf  Rust  Detection  Using  Convolutional
             Neural  Network‖.  2019  XV  Workshop  de  Visão
             Computacional (WVC). doi:10.1109/wvc.2019.8876931
         [28]. P.S.Kesava  &  K.P.  Peeyush.  ―Autonomous  Robot
             to  Detect    Diseased    Leaves    in    Plants    using
             Convolutional Neural Networks‖. 2019 3rd International
             Conference  on  Trends        in    Electronics        and
             Informatics    (ICOEI). doi:10.1109/icoei.2019.8862737
         [29].  S.S.Hari,  M.  Sivakumar,  P.  Renuga,  S.  karthikeyan  &
             S.  Suriya.    ―Detection    of    Plant    Disease    by    Leaf
             Image Using      Convolutional      Neural      Network‖.
             2019  International    Conference    on    Vision    Towards
             Emerging Trends  in  Communication  and  Networking
             (ViTECoN). doi:10.1109/vitecon.2019.8899748
         [30]. M.  Sardogan, A.  Tuncer, A.  &  Y.  Ozen,  Y. ―Plant
             Leaf Disease  Detection  and  Classification  Based  on
             CNN  with  LVQ  Algorithm‖.  2018  3rd  International
             Conference on        Computer        Science        and
             Engineering (UBMK). doi:10.1109/ubmk.2018.8566635























                                                                                                               20]]></page><page Index="121"><![CDATA[Khenilyn P. Lewis et al., International Journal of Advanced Trends in Computer Science and Engineering, 9(2), March - April 2020, 1101 – 1106
                                                                                                        ISSN 2278-3091
                                              Volume 9 No.2, March -April 2020
                      International Journal of Advanced Trends in Computer Science and
                                                       Engineering
                                                     Available Online at
                               http://www.warse.org/IJATCSE/static/pdf/file/ijatcse31922020.pdf
                                         https://doi.org/10.30534/ijatcse/2020/31922020

                Image Processing Techniques and Data Mining Algorithms for Coffee

                                                 Plant’s Leaves Classification
                                                                   2
                                                1
                                 Khenilyn P. Lewis , Mary Ann F. Quioc , Juancho D. Espineli 3
                                      1
                                       AMA University, Philippines, khenilyn@yahoo.com
                                   2
                                     AMA University, Philippines, maryannquioc@gmail.com
                                     3
                                       AMA University, Philippines, jcespineli@gmail.com
         ABSTRACT                                               found  in  high  elevation  areas  usually  in  low  air
                                                                 shown that Arabica coffee has 8,717 in production. It can be
                                                                temperature  [3].  Though  arabica  shows  second  largest  of
                                                                coffee production in the country. It is also noted that it is
         Arabica  coffee  is  known  for  its  unique  taste  and  aroma.
                                                                hard  to cultivate  and  grow  since  the  country  has  tropical
         This coffee variety contributed majority of coffee production
                                                                climate [4]. This coffee variety has the largest plantation in
         in  the  world.  However,  arabica  coffee  and  other  coffee
                                                                the  mountainous  areas  in  the  country,  like  in  Benguet,
         varieties  are  prone    to    extinction    because    of    several
                                                                Mountain  Province  and  Sagada  [5].  Luckily,  the
         reasons    including  climate  change,  drought,  diseases  and
                                                                researchers found some arabica coffee plants in  the area of
         issues  in  identification  of    nutritional    deficiencies.
                                                                Cavite,  Philippines.  Cavite is  part  of Region IV-A and a
         Nutritional    deficiencies    are  identified  and  classified
                                                                known  producer  of  Liberika  Coffee  locally  known  as
         manually with an expert to validate the  visual  symptoms
                                                                Kapeng Barako.
         occurred  in  the  coffee  leaves.  On  the other  hand,  the
         utilization  of  image  processing  to  analyze images  as  well
                                                                However,  despite  the  production  of  arabica  coffee  in
         as  data  mining  is  a  strong  combination  for classification.
                                                                the  Philippines  and  in  the  global  market,  a  study  was
         Therefore,  this  study  was  conducted  to  classify  the
                                                                conducted  that  60%  of  coffee  varieties  including  arabica
         nutritional  deficiencies  in  arabica  coffee  plants  including
                                                                coffee will be extinct.   The  extinction   is  due  to  climate
         Phosphorus    (P)    and    Potassium    (K)    using    image
                                                                change,  plant diseases     and     nutritional     deficiencies,
         processing  and    data    mining.    The  images    of  2045
                                                                drought   and deforestation  [6].  The  Philippines  also
         instances    with    1001  features    undergone    image
                                                                noted  a  decrease  of coffee production in the country [7].
         processing  techniques  such  as image acquisition, image
                                                                Among  the  mentioned  causes    of    extinction    of    arabica
         pre-processing  and  image  analysis.  The  70%  of  data  was
                                                                coffee    variety,    this    study  focused  in  classification  of
         for  training and 30%  was  for  testing using   Waikato
                                                                nutritional deficiencies in  coffee plants. It is important to
         Environment    of    Knowledge    Analysis (WEKA) and
                                                                identify the nutritional deficiencies in  plants  as  it  is  a
         Orange  Visual  Programming.  Random  Forest,  Support
                                                                way of  providing  correct  remedies  and measures.  It  is
         Vector  Machine  (SVM),  Neural  Network  (ANN)  and  K-
                                                                essential  to  boost  the  nutritional  content  of plants  to
         Nearest Neighbors (KNN) served as the classifiers of two
                                                                survived  and  produce  coffee  beans.  As  such,  the proper
         classes.  Results  shows  that  SVM  has  the  highest  AUC
                                                                nutritional identification  can  save money,  effort and time
         of
                                                                to   coffee   farmers   and   growers   [8].   Nevertheless,
         1.000   and  CA,  F1,  Precision   and  Recall   of   0.983.
                                                                identification    of    nutritional    deficiencies    is
         The Correctly   Classified    Instances    (CCI)    is    98.73%
                                                                manually performed  by  coffee  growers  and  sometimes
         and  Incorrectly  Classified  Instances  (ICI)  is  1.27%.
                                                                experts    and  laboratory  machine  for  these  are  expensive
         Further, the Kappa  statistics  of  0.97  shows  an  almost
                                                                and  unavailable.  The    process    of    identifying    and
         perfect  value  of agreement and implies that the classifier
                                                                classifying  the  nutritional deficiencies in coffee plants is
         is  better  in  coffee plants leave classification together with   expensive and time consuming too.
         Key  words:  coffee  plants,  data  mining,  image
         image processing.
         processing, machine learning
                                                                Further,  since  there  are  several  reasons  for  coffee
         1.                                                     extinction,  and  it  is  important  to  provide  risk
         INTRODUCTION                                           management  measure  to  save    our    coffee.    Image
                                                                processing  is  a  popular  way  of enhancing and reading
         Coffea   Arabica   is   the   most   popular   coffee   variety
                                                                images  to  get  important  information  or    features.  Thus,
         and  produces  the  75%  of  coffee  production  in  the  world
                                                                these features  are used  to processed  data and even used
         because  of  its  rich  flavor  and  aroma  [1].  Arabica  plants
                                                                for pattern recognition. In addition, machine learning and
         grows in  high altitudes area and the most expensive coffee
                                                                data mining is being utilized to predict certain forms using
         variety [2]. In the Philippines,   arabica   coffee   marked
                                                                different  classification  algorithms  which  can  be  trained
         the   second   largest production  among  four  types  named
                                                                and  further  used  for  Artificial  Intelligence  [9].  With  the
         Robusta,  Excelsa  and Liberica. The volume of production
                                                                used   of   image   processing   and   machine   learning
         in  coffee varieties  (mt)
                                                                algorithms,    a    prediction    model    can    be    developed.
                                                                Machine
                                                           1101]]></page><page Index="122"><![CDATA[Khenilyn P. Lewis et al., International Journal of Advanced Trends in Computer Science and Engineering, 9(2), March - April 2020, 1101 –
         1106
         learning could provide prediction and classification to   2.2  Image Processing
         which nutritional deficiency is present to coffee plants.   Image  processing  is  the  manipulation  of  images  to  be
                                                                process and   produced   the   desire   output   [15][16].
         2. METHODOLOGY                                         The   image processing    approach    can    be    performed
         This section discusses the classification models and image   using    image acquisition, image pre-processing and image
         processing techniques used in the conduct of the study.   analysis.
         Also, the data gathering procedures, prediction and         Image Acquisition      Image Pre-processing
         validation of the classifiers implemented was presented.   (camera, SD card,
                                                                   cloud)
         1.  Classifications
         Machine  learning  used  historical  data  to  train  algorithms
                                                                             Image Analysis
         for  prediction.    The    types    of    machine    learning    are    (Image Analytics, Image Embedding)
         supervised,  unsupervised    and    reinforcement    [10].
         Machine  learning  is also part of Artificial Intelligence that
         produces knowledge in training models and historical data        Figure 2: Image Processing Techniques
         as input [11]. The study utilized  the  most  popular  data    Figure 2 shows the proposed image processing techniques
         mining   algorithms  used   in image processing, these  are   in classification  of  coffee  plants  nutritional  deficiencies.
         Random  Forest,  Support  Vector  Machine    (SVM),    K-  The images of leaves were captured and save in a storage
         Nearest  Neighbor  (KNN)  and  Neural Network (NN).    medium  for  retrieval  and  manipulation  in  a  SD  card  or
           A. Random Forest                                     cloud.  In  image  pre-processing,    the    images    were
           Random  Forest  can    be  used  for    classification    in    converted    from    RGB    to  grayscale  values.  The  images
         machine  learning.  It  is  composed  of  several  trees  during   were  analyzed  using  the  input  array  or  grayscale  values.
         the  training  process    and    return    result    or    prediction    The image embedding from image analytics was utilized in
         values  of  the  input data.  This  algorithm  also  is  known    image analysis.
         for    high  accuracy    in  returning  results  and  has  flexible
         nodes.
           B. Support Vector Machine (SVM)
           Support    Vector    Machine    (SVM)    is    an    algorithm
         that outputs hyperplane which divides the two parts of each
         class. Technically,  SVM  separate  classes  and  best  used
         for  two classes classifications [12].
           C. K-Nearest Neighbor (KNN)
           This   algorithm   is   also   used   for   classification
         and regression. It is known as easy to implement and simple
         [13].
            D. Neural Network
           Neural  Network  patterns  the  process  of  the  brain  in
         which neurons   are   used   to   execute   programs   and
         flow.    This  algorithm  is  popularly  known  for  Artificial
         Intelligence (AI) implementation as shown in Figure 1.
                                                                    Figure 3: Image Processing Analytical Framework
                                                                The   imported   images   composed   of   coffee   leaves
                                                                will  undergone    image    embedding.    In    image
                                                                embedding,   the images  were  connected  to  the  server.
                                                                The  embedders  are SqueezeNet    (local),    Inception    v3,
                                                                CGG-16,    VGG-19, Painters, Deeploc and openface [17].
                                                                2.3 Data Preparation

                                                                Two    nutritional    deficiencies    named    Phosphorus    (P)
                                                                and Potassium (K) of Arabica coffee were found during the
                                                                farm visit   in   Cavite,   Philippines.   The   leaves   were
                                                                manually identified together with an agriculturist.
                                                                  Step   1:   The  leaves  were  manually  identified  by
                                                                          two agriculturists during the coffee farm visits.
                                                                  Step  2:  The leaves   were   captured  using  a  Nikon
                                                                          Digital SLR   Camera   D5300  with   single
                                                                          lens  reflex digital camera.
                                                                  Step 3: The images were saved in  SD  card  and  cloud
           Figure 1: Flowchart of Neural Network Algorithm                as storage.
           [14]




                                                           1102]]></page><page Index="123"><![CDATA[Khenilyn P. Lewis et al., International Journal of Advanced Trends in Computer Science and Engineering, 9(2), March - April 2020, 1101 –
         1106
                                                                4. Training of the Prediction Model

                                                                The  models were trained using the Waikato Environment
                                                                for Knowledge     Analysis     (WEKA)     and     Orange
                                                                Visual Programming.  The  training  data  set  is  composed
                                                                of  2405 instances  with  1001  features  and  the  testing
                                                                data  set  is composed of 101 instances with 1001 features
                                                                using 10-fold cross validation to avoid overfitting.
                                                                5. Prediction and Validation

                                                                Validation  is  used  to  determine  the  accuracy  of  the
                   (a)                    (b)
                                                                proposed model.  To validate a  classifier,  precision,  recall,
           Figure 4: Phosphorus deficiency (a) and Potassium deficiency   f-measure and  interrater  reliability  can  be  used  [9].  In
           (b)                                                  addition,    to  measure  the  performance  evaluation  of  a
                                     [18]                       classifier,  confusion  matrix    can    be  utilized    [21].    As
                                                                confusion    matrix    measures  classification  in  machine
         Figure  4  (a)  and  (b)  shows  the  nutrient  deficiencies
                                                                learning with two or  more classes [22].  It  is  also  a  table
         in  Phosphorus    (P)    and    Potassium    (K).    Phosphorus
                                                                that    shows    the    performance    of    the  classifiers  [23].
         deficiency  has    symptoms    in    plant  growth    and
                                                                Precision is the ratio of relevant instances in the retrieved
         produced     mottled  appearance  while  Potassium  (K)
                                                                instances that are referred to as a positive value where tp is
         deficiency has scorch tip and necrosis within the leaves.
                                                                truly positive and fp is a false-positive as shown in (1).
         2.3  Proposed Method                                                Precision = tp/(tp/fp)   (1)
         The     proposed    method    is    presented    using    the    Recall  is  defined  as  the  true  positive  rate  where  p  is
         analytical framework. The converted values of images into   true positive and fn is false-negative as shown in (2).
         vector array with  1001  features  each  were  trained  using
                                                                             Recall = tp/(tp/fn)   (2)
         the  classifiers, SVM,  Random  Forest,  KNN  and  ANN.
         The    evaluation    of  results  is  shown  using  the  confusion   The    weighted    average    of    Precision    and    Recall    is
         matrix, ROC Analysis, Scatter Plot and Distributions.   called F-Measure as shown in (3).
                                                                  F Score = 2*(Recall * Precision) / (Recall + Precision)
                                                                (3)
                                                                Cohen's    Kappa    statistic    is    one    among    the    list    of
                                                                Interrater  Reliability    within    raters.    Po    is    the
                                                                relative    observed  agreement  among  raters,  P e    is  the
                                                                hypothetical probability of chance agreement and K is the
                                                                Kappa value[24].

                                                                           K=(P o-Pe)/1-Pe          (4)

                                                                       Table 1:  Kappa Value and Level of Agreement
                                                                    Value of Kappa        Level of Agreement
                                                                       0.00-0.20                None
                                                                       0.21-0.39                Weak
                                                                       0.40-0.59              Minimal
                                                                       0.60-0.79              Moderate
                                                                       0.80-0.90               Strong
                                                                      Above 0.90            Almost Perfect

               Figure 5: Analytical Framework of the Proposed Method   Table  1  shows  the  Kappa  value  and  level  of  agreement.
                                                                The value of kappa  from  0.00-0.20  is  none,  0.21-0.39  is
         Receiver  Operating Characteristics (ROC)  is  a  plot  used
                                                                weak,  0.40-0.59    is    minimal,    0.60-0.79    is    moderate,
         to present  trade off  among classifiers  [19]. Scatter plot  is
                                                                0.80-0.90  is strong and above 0.90 is almost perfect.
         used to present data points within x and y axis to show how
         variables affect each other [20]. In addition, the testing set
         utilized the SVM  as  best  fit  classifier  to  perform  the
                                                                3. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION
         prediction  of  the classifier.
                                                                This  section  discusses  the  results  of  the  study  conducted.
                                                                Two  classes  were  analyzed  in  four  different  classification
                                                                models. Table 2  shows  the result  of evaluation  in  the
                                                                classification models.




                                                           1103]]></page><page Index="124"><![CDATA[Khenilyn P. Lewis et al., International Journal of Advanced Trends in Computer Science and Engineering, 9(2), March - April 2020, 1101 –
         1106
                 Table 2:  Evaluation Results of the            ROC  analysis  was  used  to  interpret  the  results  in
                 Algorithms                                     Phosphorus  and  Potassium  as  shown  in  figures  6  and  7
          Algorithm  AUC  CA       F1    Precisi   Reca
                                                                respectively. Five classifiers were presented to show the FP
                                            o n      l l
                                                                Rate (1-Specificity).
             KNN      0.99  0.97  0.97    0.975    0.975
                       6     5      5

             SVM      1.00  0.98  0.98    0.983    0.983
                       0     3      3

           Random     0.99  0.95  0.95    0.954    0.954
            Forest     0     4      4

             NN       0.98  0.98  0.98    0.983    0.983
                       8     3      3


         Support   Vector   Machine   (SVM)   has   the   highest
         AUC (1.000), CA (0.983), F1 (0.983), Precision (0.983) and
         Recall  (0.983).  Second  is  KNN  with  AUC  (0.996),  CA
         (0.975), F1                                                     Figure 7: ROC Analysis in Potassium
         (0.975),   Precision   (0.975)   and   Recall   (0.975).   Third    (K)
         is                                                     These    classifiers    were    SVM,    Random    Forest,
         Random  Forest  with  AUC  (0.990),  CA  (0.954),  F1   Neural  Network,  Naïve  Bayes  and  KNN.  Both  ROC
         (0.954),                                               analysis  shows  high    FP    Rate    for    SVM    since    two
         Precision    (0.954),  and  Recall  (0.954).  Neural    Network    classes  were  used  for comparison.
         also  return  high  AUC  (0.988),  CA  (0.983),  F1  (0.983),
             Class
         Precision    TP     FP    Precisi  Reca      F
         (0.983) and Recall (0.983).   o n    l l   measur
                      Rate  Rate
                    Table 3: Detailed Accuracy by Class
                                                      e
          Phosphoru  0.98  0.01     0.992   0.985   0.989
             s (P)     5     0
           Potassium  0.99  0.01    0.981   0.990   0.986
             (K)       0     5
                      0.98  0.01    0.987   0.987   0.987
                       7     2
         Table    3    shows    the    detailed    accuracy  by  class.    Two
         classes  were    determined    as    Phosphorus    (P)    and
         Potassium  (K). Phosphorus has TP Rate (0.985), FP Rate     Figure 8: Distribution of SVM for
         (0.010),  Precision  (0.992),  Recall  (0.985)  and  F-Measure   Phosphorus
         (0.989). Potassium has
                                                                Figure    8  shows    the    distribution    of    SVM    for
         TP  Rate  (0.990),  FP  Rate  (0.015),  Precision    (0.981),
                                                                Phosphorus. Phosphorus   has   larger   number   compared
         Recall
         (0.990) and F-Measure (0.986).                         to   Potassium. Likewise, the relative density also shows the
                                                                higher values.




















                                                                      Figure 9: Distribution of SVM for
                Figure 6: ROC Analysis in Phosphorus
                                                                      Potassium
                (P)


                                                           1104]]></page><page Index="125"><![CDATA[Khenilyn P. Lewis et al., International Journal of Advanced Trends in Computer Science and Engineering, 9(2), March - April 2020, 1101 –
         1106
         On the other hand, the distribution of SVM for Potassium   seen in a data table composed of several different number
         also presents higher number and relative density of    of values.  Those  values  were  saved  in  a  .csv  file  and
                                                                was processed using WEKA to determine the Kappa, CCI
         Phosphorus.
                                                                and ICI.

















                                                                Figure 11: Sample data table of images in image
                                                                embedding
                                                                Figure  11  shows  the  sample  data  table  of  images  after
                                                                image embedding. From one single image, each image has
             Figure 10: Scatter Plot of SVM for P and K         grayscale values in  each  pixel. In  here, from  one image,
             classes                                            1001 values were  found  in  the  image.  The  training  and
                                                                testing  dataset were  evaluated  using  the  four  classifiers
         The scatter plot was used to present the SVM data for P and
                                                                in  which  SVM returned the highest accuracy.
         K  classes.  In    which,  a  10-fold  cross  validation    was
         applied to avoid over fitting.
                                                                4.
                                                                CONCLUSION
                 Table 4: Kappa, CCI and ICI Values of
                 SVM                                              This    study    was    conducted    to    utilized    image
                                                                processing  techniques  and  data  mining  algorithms  in
                       Measure                Value
                                                                classifying coffee plants.   During   the   data   gathering,
                        Kappa                 0.9743
                                                                Phosphorus    (P)    and  Potassium  (K)  are  the  nutritional
            Correctly Classified Instances   98.7342%           deficiencies    occurred    and  used  in  classifications.  The
            (CCI)                                               classifiers  used  were  KNN,  SVM,  Random  Forest  and
            Incorrectly Classified Instances   1.2658%          ANN.  The  image  processing  techniques  conducted  were
         Table  4  shows  the  Kappa,  CCI  and  ICI  values  for  SVM.   image  acquisition,  image  pre-processing  and  image
            (ICI)
         The Correctly  Classified  Instances  (CCI)  is  98.7342%    analysis.  The images  were captured,  converted  from RGB
         and  the Incorrectly Classified Instances (ICI) is 1.2658%.   to   grayscale   values   and   image   embedding   was
         The Kappa value is 0.9743 which implies that the model is   performed  to  get  the  data  table  or    input  vector.  Among
         almost perfect in  predicting  the  nutritional  deficiencies    the  four    classifiers,  SVM  has  the  highest  almost  perfect
         in  arabica  coffee using two classes.                 Kappa value and implies that  it is an  appropriate model
                                                                for  coffee plants classification with two classes.
                        Table 5: Confusion
                                                                ACKNOWLEDGEMENT
                 A      Matrix  B     Classified as
                                                                The   authors   would   like   to   acknowledge   the   help
                1303        2          A-Phosphorus
                                                                and  assistance  of  the  National  Coffee  Research,
                  1        1099        B-Potassium              Development  and  Extension  Center  (NCRDEC)  in  Cavite
                                                                State  University,  the  Municipal    Agricultural    Office    of
         The  confusion  matrix  out  of  instances  was  presented  in   Amadeo,  Cavite,  AMA University-Quezon    City    and
         Table                                                  Commission    on    Higher Education (CHED).
         5.  Phosphorus  was  classified  in  1303  images  and  2
         for Potassium. Likewise, Potassium was classified 1099 and   REFERENCE
         1  for  Phosphorus.  Providing  a  high  accuracy  for  two
                                                                S  1.  Fellemedia,   Moyee   Coffee   _   Speciality
         classes using the SVM classifier.
                                                                   Ethiopian Coffee in Ireland _ FairChain, 2020. .
         On  the other hand, the image processing  techniques  used   2.  V. Aristizábal-Marulanda, Y. Chacón-Perez, and C.
         in the images were image acquisition, image pre-processing   A. Cardona   Alzate,   The   biorefinery   concept   for
         and  image  analysis.  During  the  image  acquisition,  a   the
                                                                   industrial   valorization   of   coffee
         camera  was  used  to  capture  the  images  and  saved  in  a
                                                                              processing
                                                                     by-products. Elsevier Inc., 2017.
         storage  medium.  In  the  pre-processing,  images  were
                                                                   https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-811290-8.00003-
         converted  from  RGB  values  to    grayscale    values.    In
                                                                   7
         image  analytics,  the  images  were connected to a server   3.  Department  of Agriculture  Philippines,  Code  of
         called  the  SqueezeNet  (local)  for  getting  the  grayscale   Agricultural   Practices   for   Coffee,   Philipp.
                                                                Good
                                                                   Natl.
         values. The converted grayscale values can be
                                                           1105]]></page><page Index="126"><![CDATA[Khenilyn P. Lewis et al., International Journal of Advanced Trends in Computer Science and Engineering, 9(2), March - April 2020, 1101 –
             1106

             Stand., no. 632, pp. 1–31, 2015.
         4.  R.   Leaño,   Types   of   Coffee   that   Grow   in
             the Philippines | Philippine Primer. 2017.
         5.  Arabica     Coffee    FMR     _     Philippine
             Rural Development Project. 2019
         6.  K.  Lauren,  The  world’s  most  popular  coffee
             species  are  going  extinct.  And  scientists  say  we
             are to blame, 2019.
         7.  Department  of  Trade  &  Industry  and  Department
             of  Agriculture,    2017-2022    Philippine    Coffee
             Industry Roadmap, p. 58, 2017.
         8.  Nutritional    Problems    -    Welcome    Coffee
             Growers!  . 2019
         9.  H.   D.   Gadade,   10_Machine   Learning   Approach
             towards Tomato Leaf Disease Classification, no. 1,
             pp. 3–8, 2020.
             https://doi.org/10.30534/ijatcse/2020/67912020
         10. Rajendra Akerar,  Artificial  Intelligence  for  Business,
             Am. J. Roentgenol., pp. 1–30, 2019.
         11. O.    R.    Devi,    International    Journal    of
             Advanced Trends    in    Computer    Science    and
             Engineering
             Available              Online
             at
             http://www.warse.org/ijatcse/static/pdf/file/ijatcse024
             22 015.pdf,‖ vol. 4, no. 2, pp. 15–21, 2015.
         12. A.  C.  Braun,  U.  Weidner,  and  S.  Hinz,  Vector
             Machines for   Hyperspectral   Classification   -   a
             Comparison,  2011    3rd    Work.    Hyperspectral
             Image  Signal  Process. Evol. Remote Sens., vol. 2,
             no. 3, pp. 1–4, 2011.
         13. O.   Harrison,   Machine   Learning   Basics   with
             the K-Nearest    Neighbors    Algorithm,    Towards
             Data Science2. pp. 1–16, 2018.
         14. Z. Zeng, L. Zheng, and D. Ling,  Network  Algorithm,
             vol. 0, no. 3, pp. 1716–1718, 2008.
         15. E.  A.  B.  da  Silva  and  G.  V.  Mendonca,    Digital
             Image  Processing,  Electr.  Eng.  Handb.,  pp.  891–
             910, 2005.
         16. X. Wang, Moving window-based double haar
             wavelet transform  for  image  processing,  IEEE
             Trans.  Image Process., vol. 15, no. 9, pp. 2771–
             2779, 2006.
             https://doi.org/10.1109/TIP.2006.877316
         17. Orange Data Mining - Download. 2019 .
         18. Coffee Nutritional Deficiencies — Vikaspedia. 2019.
         19. C.  S.  Specificity,  Plotting  and  Intrepretating  an
             ROC Curve. pp. 4–5, 2014.
         20. MDH, Scatter Plot  What  is  a  Scatter  Plot ? p.
             2014, 2016.
         21. J.  M.  Victoriano,  M.  Luis,  and  C.  D.  Santos,
             Predicting Pollution Level Using Random Forest:
             A  Case  Study  of    Marilao    River    in    Bulacan
             Province,    Philippines,  vol.  3,  no.  1,  pp.  151–162,
             2017.
         22. Sarang   Narkhede,   Understanding   Confusion
             Matrix  –  Towards  Data  Science,  Towards  Data
             Science. 2018.
         23. M.    Learning,    Simple    guide    to    confusion
             matrix terminology. pp. 1–9, 2014.
         24. Stephanie,  Cohen’s  Kappa  Statistic  -  Statistics
             How To. 2014.

                                                           1106]]></page><page Index="127"><![CDATA[International Journal of Computer Applications (0975 – 8887)
                                                                                     Volume 179 – No.29, March 2018

              Development of a Language Translator from English to

                                                       Waray


                                                    Khenilyn P. Lewis
                                                   Cavite State University
                                  Technological University of the Philippines-Manila, Philippines


            ABSTRACT                                            of instruction from kindergarten to Grade 3. This crucial shift,
                                                                known  as  ―Mother  Tongue-Based  Multi-Lingual  Education‖
            The Philippines is a home of different languages. Languages
            are   vital   weapons   of   communicating   with   others   and   (MTB-MLE),  is  part  of  the  K+12  basic  education  reform
            expressing   points   in   the   society   more   importantly   in   program   and   other   local   languages   will   be   added   in
            Education. Based from Department of Education, there are 12   succeeding school years.
            major languages as part  of K+12  Education System.  Among   The  Philippines  is  home  of  more  or  less  175  languages,  but
            these  is  Waray,  language  spoken  by  people  from  Samar,   some  of  them  have  just  few  speakers  left  while  others  are
            Northern    Samar,    Eastern    Samar,    Biliran,    and    Leyte.   already considered extinct because there are no more people at
            According     to     the     Department     of     Education,     the   all who use in them. According to Agence (2012), up to 50 of
            implementation  of K+12  Education System in  the country is   the country's minor languages could be lost within 20 years.
            the  used  of  mother  tongue  as  medium  of  instructions  from
            Kindergarten to Grade 3. The development of the software is   The  DepEd  also  stated  that  the  ―Local  and  international
            to translate instructional materials written in English to Waray   studies  have  shown  that  using  the  language  used  at  home
            language. The software could  accept word, sentence, phrase,   (mother  tongue)  inside  the  classroom  during  the  learners‘
            and  document file  with  .doc and  .docx extensions  written  in   early  years  of  schooling  produces  better  and  faster  learners
            English  to  be  translated  in  Waray  language.  In  addition,  the   who  can  easily  adapt  to  learn  a  second  (Filipino)  and  third
            capabilities to add new words and rules, update of dictionary,   (English)  language.‖  DepEd  national  coordinator  for  MTB-
            and  search  for  word  and  rule  are  part  of  the  translator.  The   MLE, Rosalina Villaneza stressed that studies show that using
            development of the translator used Rule-Based Algorithm that   the  child‘s  mother  tongue  as  language  of  literacy  ―bolsters
            includes parsing, searching, and matching of words inside the   comprehension  and  critical  thinking  skills  of  children  and
            database. The translator can translate document file and words   facilitates acquisition of a second language such as English or
            from   English   to   Waray   Language.   In   addition,   existing   Filipino.
            dictionary  and  rule  can  be  modified  and  added  inside  the   DepEd directive aimed at enhancing language, cognitive and
            database.   Test   and   evaluation   results   validated   that   the   academic  development  of the  child  even  as  it  also  ―seeks  to
            prototype   could    be   an    alternative    way   of    translating
                                                                create  social  and  cultural  awareness  among  the  children  by
            instructional materials written in English to Waray language.   promoting their local heritage, language and culture.‖ The use
                                                                of  mother  tongue  as  the  medium  of  instruction  will  require
            General Terms
                                                                competent  educators  especially  those  teaching  Science  and
            Natural Language Processing
                                                                Math subjects.
            Keywords                                            Furthermore,  there  are  available  software  translators  in  the
            Rule-Based Algorithm, Language Translator, Waray    Internet. One of the most popular is the Google Translate that
                                                                allow  users  to  translate  the  source/  detect  language  to  the
            1.  INTRODUCTION                                    target language. This translator comprises different languages
            Education  is  the  key  to  success.  Students  at  an  early  age   all   over   the   globe.   In   addition,   dictionary   for   Native
            should  be  able  to  understand  the  process  of  learning  that   Philippine Languages called Waray English Dictionary is also
            serves  as  their  foundation  of  knowledge.  The  early  stage  of   accessible  in  the  Web.  This  online  dictionary  accepts  either
            education  also  helps  students  to  enhance  their  emotional,   Waray or English text and translates it word  for word. Most
            physical, social and intellectual capacities. Language is one of   language   translators   though   translate   languages   does   not
            the important ingredients to  make the learning process  more   focuses  in  Native  Language  and  mostly  connected  in  the
            comprehensible. The use of books and learning materials are   Internet.   In   addition,   software   translator   from  English   to
            being   utilized   in   teaching   students.   In   the   Philippines,   Native Language nonetheless available has limited capacities.
            textbooks  are  written   in  languages   such   as  Tagalog  and
            English.   Also,   based   on   DepEd,   the   types   of   learning   The  study  is  to  developed  prototype  that  translates  English
            materials  available  are  story  books  in  big  and  small  book   language    to    Waray    and    includes    dictionary,    sentence
            formats;  flash/activity cards using letters and numbers; basic   translation, and accept document file.
            sight words or grade level words and picture dictionary; and   2.  METHODOLOGY
            picture chart for oral literacy.
                                                                2.1.1  Project Design
            According  from  the  Official  Gazette  of  the  Department  of
                                                                The  translator  offers  a  way  of  converting  English  as  source
            Education, ―The K +12 Basic Education Program‖, introduced   language to Waray dialect as target language.
            twelve  (12)  Mother  Tongue  (MT)  languages  for  SY  2012-
            2013:    Bahasa  Sug  (Tausug),  Bikol,  Cebuano,  Chabacano,
            Hiligaynon,  Iloko,  Kapampangan,  Maguindanaoan,  Meranao,
            Pangasinense,  Tagalog,  and  Waray.  These  local  languages
            spoken in different regions of the country are used as medium





                                                                                                            17]]></page><page Index="128"><![CDATA[International Journal of Computer Applications (0975 – 8887)
                                                                                     Volume 179 – No.29, March 2018

                                                                    Table 2. The Users Table of WarayDB Database
                                                                  Field Name   Data Type      Description
                                                                    UserID        int       Shows user ID and
                                                                                              cannot be null
                                                                    LoginID    varchar(20)   Accepts log in ID
                                                                   LoginPW     varchar(20)   Accepts log in password
                                                                   AcctType    varchar(50)   Account Type according
                                                                                             to level of access
                                                                   FullName    varchar(80)   Account full name
                                                                   AcctStatus   varchar(1)   Account Status
                                                                   CreateDate   datetime   Create date of account
                                                                   CreatedBy   varchar(20)   Account that created
                                                                                              other account
                                                                   LastUpdate   datetime    Last update of the
                                                                                                account
                Fig 1: Block diagram of the language translator
                                                                   UpdateBy    varchar(20)   Holds who update the
            Figure 1 shows the block diagram of the language translator.                        account
            Microsoft  SQL  Server  and  executable  file  is  installed  in  a
            computer.  The  prototype  contains  translation  for  dictionary,   Table  2  shows  the  users  table  of  the  WarayDB  database
            sentence(s), and document file. Document file to be translated   composed    of    UserID,    LoginID,    LoginPW,    AcctType,
            should have file extensions of .doc or .docx only. The source   FullName,  AcctStatus,  CreateDate,  CreatedBy,  LastUpdate
            language which is English will be parsed and matched. Inside   and UpdateBy fields. The UserID field is int in data type, auto
            the database are the fields for words, part of speech, linking   increment  and  cannot  be  null.  The  LoginID  and  LoginPW
            verb,   and   rules   that   are   ready   for   retrieval.   The   source   fields with data type varchar(20) holds the log-in information
            language will be translated to Waray as target language.   of the account. The FullName field with varchar (80) indicates
                                                                the   full   name   of   the   account   user.   For   AcctStatus   with
                                                                varchar(1) data type specifies if the account is active or not.
                                                                The fields CreateDate, LastUpdate, CreatedBy, and UpdateBy
                                                                are for update of an account.
                                                                  Table 3. The LinkingVerb table of WarayDB database
                                                                 Field Name   Data Type       Description
                                                                    LvID         int      Accepts linking verb ID`
                                                                  LvName     varchar(150)   Accepts linking verb name

                                                                Table 3 shows the LinkingVerb table of WarayDB database.
                                                                This includes LvID with data type Int and LvName with data
                                                                type  varchar  (150).  The  table  list  all  English  linking  verbs
                                                                ready for retrieval.
                                                                   Table 4. The tblWords table of WarayDB database
                                                                    Field     Data Type       Description
               Fig 2: Conceptual design of the language translator
                                                                    Name
            As  shown  in  Figure  2,  database  creation  used  to  provide   ID   int   Shows ID number and
            bilingual text corpura. Source language parsed and identified                    cannot be null
            match  after  search.  Matched  found  translated  based  on  rules   Waray   nvarchar(255)   Holds Waray words
            whereas direct translation take place if not. The bilingual text   English   nvarchar(255)   Holds English words
            corpura  composed  of  source  and  target  language,  rules  and   Part_of_S   nvarchar(255)   Holds part of speech
            linking verbs.                                          peech
                                                                  Rulevalue   nvarchar(255)   Holds Rule Value
            2.1.2  Database Design                                 Meaning   nvarchar(255)   Holds the meaning of
            Table 1. List of Tables for WarayDB Database                                    English and Waray
               Table Name           Description                                                  word
              LinkingVerbs   This table list linking English linking   Markers_   nvarchar(255)   Holds marker value
                                      verbs.                      RuleNum
                tblWords   This table composed of English and
                            Waray words with Part_of_Speech,    Table 4 shows the tblWords table from WarayDB composed
                            RuleValue, Meaning, and Marker      of ID, Waray, English, Part_of_Speech, RuleValue, Meaning,
              PartofSpeech   This table list of parts of speech   and Markers_RuleNum. ID field has data type int and cannot
                 Rules           This table list of rules       be  null.  Waray  field  holds  word  of  target  language  with
                 Users          This table list of users        nvarchar  (255)  data  type.  English  field  hold  word  as  source
                                                                language with nvarchar (255). Part_of_Speech, Rulevalue and
            Table 1 shows the list of tables inside the WarayDB database.   Markers_RuleNum  fields  hold  the  equivalent  value  of  the
            These are LinkingVerbs, tblWords, PartofSpeech, Rules, and   source and target language with data type of nvarchar (255).
            Users. Further discussions are shown in the tables below.   Moreover, meaning field with data type nvarchar (255) of the







                                                                                                            18]]></page><page Index="129"><![CDATA[International Journal of Computer Applications (0975 – 8887)
                                                                                     Volume 179 – No.29, March 2018

            table holds the description  of the English and  Waray words.
            This table serves as the dictionary of the database

            Table 5. The PartofSpeech Table of WarayDB Database

               Field Name    Data Type    Description
                   ID           int     Shows ID number
                                        and cannot be null
               PartofSpeech   varchar(50)   Holds identified part
                                            of speech
                RuleValue   varchar(50)   Holds rule value

            Table 5  shows the PartofSpeech  table of WarayDB database
            composed    of    ID,    PartofSpeech,    and    RuleValue.    The
            PartofSpeech and RuleValue with data type varchar(50) holds
            marker for translating based on rules. While ID with data type
            int serves as the control number and cannot be null.
                                                                  Fig 3: Program Flowchart of the Language Translator
            2.1.3 Link Grammar Algorithm                        Figure   3   illustrates   the   program   flowchart   of   language
            Each word with corresponding part of speech assigned a rule   translator from English to Waray. It covers the translation of
            value with the following equivalent:                document file with file extensions .doc or .docx.

                    Table 6. Part of speech and Rule value
                      Part of Speech   Rule Value
                          Noun            N
                        Pronoun          PRO
                        Adjective        ADJ
                          Verb            V
                       Preposition       PREP
                         Adverb          ADV
                       Conjunction      CONJ
                         Article          A
                       Contraction      CONT
                       Interjection      INTJ
                        Markers           M


            After assigning the rule value:
               1.  Provide noun markers that include an, it, ha, hi, hin,
                   han, and hit.
               2.  The program randomly selects from noun markers.
               3.  Words  with  more  than  one  equivalent  get  the  first
                   value found in the database.                        Fig 4: Translate File Program Flowchart

            4.   Re-writing Document File as Output             Figure  4  shows  the  program  flow  chart  for  translating  file
            The program includes:                               document. The opened file is read and converted to Rich Text
                                                                Format (.rtf). Rich Text format allows text be read and figure/
               1.  Saving word and rule matched in a data table in the
                   memory.                                      images retained. The parsed sentence will be saved inside the
               2.  Automatically save the translated file in an output   database   table.    Since,    Waray   grammars    do    not   have
                   folder (C:\WarayProj\WarayDoc\Output\) without   equivalent  linking  verb/s  then  it  is  removed  in  the  parsed
                   deleting the original file. File will have the same   sentence.   Parsed   sentence   will   be   divided   according   to
                   name as the original file.                   English rules counterpart. If there are matched rules inside the
                                                                database,  it  will  be  re-written  and  replace  document  file
                                                                uploaded  in  the  translator.  If  there  are  no  matched  found
            Project Development
                                                                inside  the  database,  word  for  word  translation  takes  place.
            The conceptual and database design  guided the development
            process and program flow chart of the language translator as   Replacing the document file after translation do not delete or
            shown in the Figures 3 to 5.                        re-  write  original  file.  Furthermore,  translated  file  is  saved
                                                                inside the output folder of the computer‘s drive.















                                                                                                            19]]></page><page Index="130"><![CDATA[International Journal of Computer Applications (0975 – 8887)
                                                                                     Volume 179 – No.29, March 2018

                                                                                    ID,  password,  account  type  and
                                                                                    full name.
                                                                                2.  Clicked the Save button.
                                                                                3.  Clicked   New   Word   button   to
                                                                                    dictionary menu tab.
                                                                                4.  Verified user name and password.
                                                                                5.  Supplied  fields  for  Waray  word,
                                                                                    English  word,  part  of  speech  and
                                                                                    meaning.
                                                                                6.  Clicked the Save button and Clear
                                                                                    button to reset.
                                                                                7.  Clicked  find  rules  under  Manage
                                                                                    Rules menu tab.
                                                                                8.  Entered  English rule, Waray  Rule
                                                                                    and Rule Description.
                                                                                9.  Clicked the Save button and Clear
                                                                                    button to reset fields.
               Fig 5. Program flowchart for sentence translation
                                                                2.1.5.2. Evaluation Procedure
            Sentence translation in Figure 5 follows the same rule as the   To determine the performance of the language translator, ISO
            document  file.  However,  there  is  no  uploading  of  file  and   9126   evaluation   criteria   used   to   evaluate   functionality,
            input and output display will be found in text fields. Finally,   usability,   reliability,   efficiency,   portability,   and
            when  word  entered  found  matched,  Waray  word  equivalent,   maintainability.
            meaning and part of speech will be displayed in the screen.
                                                                The following were undertaken during the evaluation:
            For the dictionary, entering English word that matched inside   1. The   translator   presented   to   the   evaluator-respondents
            the  database  will  provide  the  corresponding  Waray  word,   consisting     of     ten     (10)     information     technology
            meaning and part of speech.                            professionals and twenty (20) Waray speakers.
            5.    Operation and Testing Procedure               2. The  evaluator-respondents  explored,  navigated  and  used
            1.     Testing Procedure                               the translator for evaluation;
            The   main   purpose   of   this   stage   is   to   test   software‘s   3. Requested   them   to   rate   the   translator   using    Likert
            functionality   and   accuracy.   It   was   tested   by   five   (5)   Scale  shown  in  Table  7  and  the  prepared  evaluation
            information  technology  professionals  and  five  (5)  teachers   instrument;
            from   the   Department   of   Education   who   speak   Waray
            language.                                           4. Collected and tabulated the data and computed the  mean
                                                                   for each criterion and the overall mean of all the criteria;
            The following were undertaken during the testing:      and
                                                                5. Results  were  interpreted  for  the  equivalent  descriptive
                        Table 6: Testing procedures                rating using Table 8.
               Module/              Test Conducted                     Numerical Scale   Interpretation
              Component                                                        Table 7. Likert Scale
                                                                             5              Excellent
               Translate    1.  Opened the translator .exe file.             4             Very Good
               Document     2.  Clicked Open button under the file
                                menu tab.                                    3               Good
                            3.  Selected    file   to    open   in   any
                                                                             2                Fair
                                location in the computer. Learning
                                materials  from  DepEd   was   first         1               Poor
                                uploaded to the system.
                            4.  Clicked Translate button under the
                                file menu tab.                   Table 8. Range of Mean Values Scale and Interpretation
                            5.  Clicked View button under the file     Numerical Scale    Interpretation
                                menu tab.
                            6.  Opened  another  document  file  to      4.51 – 5.00        Excellent
                                translate.                               3.51 – 4.50       Very Good
               Dictionary   1.  Clicked Dictionary menu tab.
                            2.  Clicked Search button.                   2.51 – 3.50         Good
                            3.  Entered  English word  and  clicked      1.51 – 2.50          Fair
                                Search button.
               Sentence     1.  Entered  sentence  in  the  first  text   1.00 – 1.50         Poor
              Translation       field.
                            2.  Clicked Translate button.
                            3.  Clicked    Clear    button    to    reset
                                fields.
               Account      1.  Created account by entering log-in




                                                                                                            20]]></page><page Index="131"><![CDATA[International Journal of Computer Applications (0975 – 8887)
                                                                                     Volume 179 – No.29, March 2018


            3. RESULTS AND DISCUSSIONS                            Ultimate 32 bit          seconds   24 seconds
                                                                 AMD E-450 APU
            1.  Project Description                                @ 1.65 GHz
            The  prototype  is  capable  of  translating  word  for  dictionary,   2.00GB RAM
            sentence, and document file with file extensions .doc or .docx   Windows  7  Home   842   10.12   3 minutes
            from English to Waray. Document file translation uploads file   Edition 64 bit Intel   seconds   05 seconds
            inside the system. The uploaded file will be converted to .rtf   Core  ™  i5-3210M
            format  to  segregate  image  and  text.  Text  is  parsed,  and   CPU @ 2.50 GHz
            terminators served as the indicator. Matched words and rules   4.00 GB
            will be used  for translation. On the other hand, no rules and
            word   matched   will   create   word   for   word   translation.   Table 9 shows the test conducted and result of translation time
            Translated  file  saved  in  the  output  folder.  Words  inside  the   of the prototype. Three different computer specifications were
            dictionary matched and displayed part of speech, Waray word
                                                                used.  The  result  of  the  table  shows  that  translation  time
            equivalent, and meaning. Moreover, parsing and matching be   defends   on   the   number   of   words   in   file   and   computer
            applied  for  sentence  translation.  Additional  feature  of  the   specifications. Furthermore, table 8 implies that the higher the
            translator is the capability of admin to add and manage word   computer specifications, the faster translation time is.
            and rules inside the database. The translator was created using
            C#    programming    language,    Microsoft    SQL    Server    as   3.2.2. Evaluation Results
            database, and Telerik for interface design.
                                                                The   software   was   evaluated   according   to   functionality,
            3.1.1. Project Capabilities and Limitations         usability,   reliability,   efficiency,   portability,   and
                                                                maintainability.  It  was  evaluated  by  30  respondents  with  10
            The  software  could  translate  word,  sentence,  and  documents
                                                                information technology professionals and 20 Waray speakers.
            file from English to Waray. It is capable of adding and editing
            word and rules inside the database. Further, the user account   Table below shows the evaluation  result of each  criteria and
            is used  to  manage update inside the  database. The translator   overall result.
            converts document file to Rich Text Format. Converted .doc   The result of evaluation shows the overall mean rating for the
            to  .rtf  will  be  parsed  and  matched  using  the  database.  The   language translator. It was rated 4.47 by the respondents and
            prototype  could  re-  write  document  file  content  to  Waray   found very good. Furthermore, functionality is 4.22, reliability
            language without deleting original file. Output is saved in an   is 4.29, efficiency is 4.45, and portability is 4.33 and all found
            output folder in the computer‘s drive.              as very good in performance. On the other hand, usability is
                                                                4.66  and  maintainability is  4.60  and  both  found  excellent  in
            As  limitations,  the  words  and  rules  used  in  translator  came   performance. The result of evaluation discusses that usability
            from Komisyon sa Wikang Filipino- Manila and Panrehiyong   got  the  highest  mean  and  functionality  got  the  lowest  mean
            Sentro  ng  Wikang  Filipino  (Region  8).  Hence,  output  of the
                                                                but  still  very  good  as  construed.  The  result  implies  that  the
            translator is limited and varies only to those cited sources. It is   prototype  could  be  an  alternative  way of  converting  English
            not connected  in the Internet or any dictionary except to  the   text in Waray language.
            sources mentioned above. Document file that can be uploaded
            is with .doc and .docx file extensions only. The software is not   4. SUMMARY, CONCLUSION AND
            capable of identifying wrong entries of the user.
                                                                RECOMMENDATIONS
            2.  Project Evaluation                              4.1 Summary of Findings
            1.    Test Results                                  Based on tests and evaluation conducted on the performance
            The results during the test procedure show that:    capability  of  the  language  translator,  the  following  were  the
                                                                findings  of  the  study.  The  software  is  capable  of  translating
            There  are  English  rule  that  does  not  have  match  in  the
            database  and  produced  word  for  word  translation.  There  are   English   words   as   source   language   to   Waray   as   target
            words not translated because it does not exist in the database.   language.   It   can   provide   dictionary   that   displayed   the
                                                                meaning,  English  and  Waray  words,  and  part  of  speech.  It
            Special  characters  and  text  cases  were  not  read.  Also,  the
            respondent did not able to translate more than one sentence in   could  translate  sentence  and  document  file  with  .doc  and
            the field. In addition, to be able to add and edit word and rule,   .docx  extensions.  It  was  created  using  C#  as  programming
            the  respondent  must  have  a  valid  account.  The  test  result   language,  Microsoft  SQL Server  as  database,  and  Telerik  as
            shows that because of limited sources, there were words and   interface   design.   Rule   based   algorithm   was   used   to   get
                                                                matches in the database. The software was tested by five (5)
            rules that were not translated. Since word for word translation   Department of Education teachers that speak Waray and five
            occurred the context of the sentence also changed. The testing   (5) information technology professionals for improvements. It
            result  was  the  reference  for  the  software‘s‘  improvement.  In   was  evaluated  to  be  ―Very  Good‖  with  an  overall  mean  of
            addition, translation time was considered during the testing as   4.47 signifying that the prototype could be alternative way of
            shown in the table below.
                                                                translating English to Waray language.
                 Table 9. Test conducted for Translation Time
               Computer      Number   Uploading  Translation
             Specifications   of words   Time in   Time         4.2 Conclusions
                            in the file   the                   In consideration of the objectives of the study and the results
                              (from   translator                of    testing    and    evaluation    carried    out,    the    following
                             DepED)                             conclusions   were   derived.   The   language   translator   was
            Windows 7 Starter   842   1 minute   12 minutes     developed  such  that  it  provided  dictionary  for  English  to
             32 bit Intel Atom        12 seconds   24 seconds   Waray, could translate sentence and word document with .doc
            CPU @ 1.66 GHz                                      and .docx file extensions. The software was created using C#
              2.00GB RAM                                        programming  language,  Microsoft  SQL  Server  as  database
               Windows 7      842       24.57    7 minutes      and Telerik to interface design. Test results validated that the





                                                                                                            21]]></page><page Index="132"><![CDATA[International Journal of Computer Applications (0975 – 8887)
                                                                                     Volume 179 – No.29, March 2018

            software  could  translate  words,  sentence  and  document  file   [11] The Provincial Government Website of Leyte. Retrieved
            from English to Waray language. It could execute to Windows   last   August   8,    2012      from
            7  platforms  and  the  higher  the  computer  specification,  the   http://www.leyte.org.ph/about_leyte-gen_info.htm.
            faster  the  translation  time.  The  performance  of  the  software
            was rated ―Very Good‖ by the respondents which proved that   [12] Rouse,  Margaret.  2005.  Expert  System.  Retrieved  last
            it can  be an  alternative  way of converting English to  Waray   August   3,   2012   from   http://searchcio-
                                                                    midmarket.techtarget.com/definition/expert-system
            language.
                                                                [13] Nueva,    Frederico    G.    Development    of    Translation
            4.3. Recommendations                                    Software  of  Four  Philippine  Major  Dialects.  Master‘s
            Implementing the prototype highly recommended since it can   thesis.   Technological   University   of   the   Philippines,
            be an alternative in translating English to Waray language.   Manila. May 2004.
            However, several recommendations to further enhancement of
                                                                [14] Prasad, Rajkishore and Sinha, A.K. 2003. Using ESTA to
            the project are hereby endorsed including the Upgrade of the   Develop   Expert   System   for   the   Natural   Resource
            translation  algorithm,  providing  markers  when  adding  rules   Management.  6 th    Annual  International  Conference  and
            and could be an online translator.
                                                                    Exhibition, New Delhi, India.
            5. ACKNOWLEDGEMENT                                  [15] Basnette,    Susan.    2002.    Translation    Studies-    Third
                                                                    Edition.  Routledge  Taylor  and  Francis  Group  London
            Thank  you  to  Technological  University  of  the  Philippines-
            Manila, Komisyon  sa Wikang Filipino- Manila, Mr. Voltaire   and New York.
            Q.   Oyzon   and   Panrehiyong   Sentro   ng   Wikang   Filipino   [16] Bosco,    Gabriela.    2012.    ―Translation    Techniques‖.
            (Region 8) for providing the necessary documents during the   Interpro  translation  Solutions.  Retrieved  last  August  2,
            conduct of the study.                                   2012                                  from
                                                                    http://www.interproinc.com/articles.asp?id=0303
            6.  REFERENCES
            [1]   Guidelines on the Implementation of the Mother Tongue-   [17] Herther,  Nancy  K.  2012.  Language  Translation  in  the
                                                                    Internet Age ‗My Hovercraft Is Full of Eels‘. Information
               Based-   Multilingual   Education.   2012.   Department   of   Today, Inc. Vol. 20, No. 1.
               Education.    Retrieved    last    August    5,    2012    from
               www.deped.gov.ph.                                [18] Top  Ten  Reviews.  Retrieved  last  August  8,  2012  from
                                                                    http://translation-software-review.toptenreviews.com.
            [2]   Agence, France- Presse. 2012. Along fight begins to save
               Philippine languages. Retrieved last August 5, 2012 from   [19] Zogheib,   Ali.   2007.   Genetic   Algorithm-based   Multi-
               http://www.rappler.com/nation/4537-a-long-fight-begins-   Word Automatic Language Translation. IT-Universitetet
               to-save-philippine-languages                         i   Goteborg   -   Department   of   Applied   Information
                                                                    Technology. ISBN 978-83-60434-59-8, pages 751–760.
            [3]   Discussion    Paper    on    the    Enhanced    K+12    Basic
               Education Program. 2010. DepEd Discussion Paper.   [20] PhP:  Hypertext  Preprocessor.  Retrieved  last  August  3,
                                                                    2012                                  from
            [4]   Clarke,  Derek.  1996.  Software  Evaluation  Criteria-  The
                                                                    http://www.webopedia.com/TERM/P/PHP.html
               Users.     Retrieved     last     August     2,     2012  from
               http://content.alterra.wur.nl/Internet/webdocs/ilri-   [21] Rouse, Margaret. 2007. Visual Basic .NET (VB.NET or
               publicaties/special reports/Srep2-h5.pdf             VB   .NET).   Retrieved   last   August   3,   2012   from
                                                                    http://searchwindevelopment.techtarget.com/definition/V
            [5]   Schneidewind,  Norman  F.  2003.  Software  Reliability   isual-Basic-NET
               Measurement,     or     Life     Cycle     Core     Knowledge
               Requirements   for   Software   Reliability   Measurement.   [22] Gaurav, Khanna. 2010. Benefits of VB .NET. Retrieved
               Volume23   Number   2,   June   2003.   Reprinted   from   last   August   3,    2012      from
               Reliability Review, The R & M Engineering Journal.   http://social.msdn.microsoft.com/Forums/en/netfxnetcom
                                                                    /thread/a5c456c8-e432-4b46-b963-3b4559e0a81d
            [6]   Mathew,  Tom  V.  2005.  Genetic  Algorithm.  Retrieved
               last     August      3,      2012     from       [23] Hanumesh, V. J. and Seema Acharya. (2005). Relational
               http://www.civil.iitb.ac.in/tvm/2701_dga/dga/dga.html   Database Management System.  Education  and  Research
                                                                    Department Inforsys Technologies Ltd. No. 350, Hebbal
            [7]   Parikh,    Prashant.    2001.    The    Use    of    Language.   Electronics City Hootagalli, Mysore.
               Distributed  for  Center  for  the  Study  of  Language  and
               Information. CSLI Publications.                  [24] The  Tech  Terms  Computer  Dictionary.  Retrieved  last
                                                                    August 5, 2012 from http://www.techterms.com
            [8]   Sugbo, Victor N. 2003. Language Policy and  Literature
                                                                [25] Rouse, Margaret. (2006). MySQL. Retrieved last August
               in  the  Philippines.  University  of  the  Philippines  in  the
               Visayas.                                             3,                2012                from
                                                                    http://searchenterpriselinux.techtarget.com/definition/My
            [9]   Rubrico,  Jessie  Grace  U.  2006.  The  Languages  of  the   SQL
               Philippines. Language Links. Org. Retrieved last August
               4,                2012                from       [26] Hubpages. How Google Translate Works. Retrieved last
               http://www.languagelinks.org/onlinepapers/fillang.html   February   1,        2013         from
                                                                    http://animshare.hubpages.com/hub/How-Google-
            [10] The  Official  Website  of Samar  Province.  Retrieved  last   Translate-Works
               August 8, 2012 form http://www.samar.lgu-ph.com.








                                                                                                            22]]></page><page Index="133"><![CDATA[International Journal of Computer Applications (0975 – 8887)
                                                                                     Volume 179 – No.29, March 2018

            [27] Microsoft  Website.  Retrieved  last  August  5,  2012  from   [30] Education.   US   Library   of   Congress.   Retrieved   last
               http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/products           August        3,         2012         from
                                                                    http://countrystudies.us/philippines/53.htm.
            [28] ISO  9126  Software  Quality  Characteristics.  Retrieved
               last     August      3,      2012     from       [31] The K to 12 Basic Education Program. Official Gazette
               http://www.sqa.net/iso9126.html                      of the Republic of the Philippines. Retrieved last August
                                                                    2, 2012 from http://www.gov.ph/k-12.
            [29] Uebersax,  John  S.  (2006).  Likert  Scales:  Dispelling  the
               Confusion.    Retrieved    last    August    8,    2012    from
               http://www.john-uebersax.com/stat/likert.htm.













































































           IJCA TM  : www.ijcaonline.org

                                                                                                            23]]></page><page Index="134"><![CDATA[Circulation in Computer Science
                                               Vol.3, No.3, pp: (1-5), May 2018
                                           https://doi.org/10.22632/ccs-2018-252-80

                     Social Commerce Acceptance of Students in a

                  State University in the Philippines: A Unified View




                 Khenilyn P. Lewis              Paquito G. Fernando Jr.            Dennis B. Gonzales, PhD
                Cavite State University              John Paul College                   AMA University
              Trece Martires City, Cavite         Roxas, Oriental Mindoro           School of Graduate Studies
                   Philippines 4109                                                  Quezon City, Philippines

                                                 Manuel Luis C. Delos
                                                         Santos
                                                 Asian Institute of Computer
                                                         Studies
                                               AICS Building, Commonwealth
                                                Avenue, Don Antonio Heights,
                                                  Holy Spirit, Quezon City,
                                                        Philippines

            ABSTRACT                                            connected in the network. Also, that users do not need to pay
                                                                for  advertisement  or  create  their  own  website  to  promote
            One  of  the  increasing  concept  nowadays  in  ecommerce  is
            social commerce. Social commerce is the buying and selling   which  in  other  way  expensive.  The  idea  is  to  use  portable
            of  goods  and  services  through  the  use  of  social  networking   devices such as mobile phones, tablets and the like. The most
            sites.   In   addition,   social   commerce   primarily   affects   the   common device that being used are the mobile phones. In the
            millennials composed  mostly of college students. This study   Philippines  with  more  than  millions  of  users,  this  kind  of
            was conducted to determine the characteristics of students in   technology  is  very  efficient.  Another  advantage  is  location
            terms  of  age  and  sex  and  their  relationship  to  the  factors   wise,  users  do  not  need  to  travel  or  spend  time.  They  can
            affecting the acceptance of social commerce. The factors were   advertise, promote, buy and sell even if they are just at home.
            based   on   the   User   Acceptance   of   Technology:   Towards   In   terms  of  payment,   most  people  consider   the  used   of
            Unified  View.  Facebook  was  considered  as  the  platform  of   Internet.
            social   commerce   in   this   study.   The   questionnaire   was   Further, as Internet users, students have the most numbers in
            answered   by   100   respondents   composed   of   Bachelor   of   terms  of  social  media  usage.  In  this  era,  they  are  called  the
            Science in  Information  Technology and  Bachelor of Science   Millennials.  They are individuals who  are born  between  late
            in Business Management. Descriptive statistics was used such   1980 to early 2000. They have the most hours of surfing the
            as  frequency  count,  percentage  and  mean  to  determine  the   Internet and viewing website pages. They have the network of
            characteristics of the participants and  factors affecting social   extending   their   reviews   and   feedbacks   in   any   issues,
            commerce  acceptance.  Pearson  correlation  was  used  to  find   specifically in promotions and advertisement.
            the   relationship   between   the   characteristics   and   factors
            affecting  social  commerce  acceptance  of  students  in  a  State   On the other hand, it is imperative that social commerce and
            University.                                         user‘s acceptance be  measured  through  the unified  theory of
                                                                acceptance   and   use   of   technology (UTAUT).   It   is   an
            Keywords                                            acceptance technology model that explains the user‘s behavior
            Social Commerce, State University, Unified View     and intentions in information technology.  In this case, social
                                                                commerce  acceptance could  be determined  using the unified
                                                                view    with    four    key    constructs    namely    performance
            1.  INTRODUCTION
                                                                expectancy, effort expectancy, social influence and facilitating
            The increase numbers of internet users nowadays created new   conditions.
            avenue   for   e-commerce.   E-commerce   is   the   buying   and
            selling  of goods  and  services  over  the  net.  One  new way  of   The  study  was  conducted  to  determine  the  factors  affecting
            extending e-commerce to the users is the used of social media,   social   commerce   acceptance   of   the   students   in   a   state
            most  popular  is  the  Facebook.  The  used  of  social  media   university   in    the   Philippines   using   the   unified    view.
            platforms provides the most sales in the net.  Sales that takes   Specifically,    this    study    aimed    to:    (1)    identify    the
            place   and   established   in   social   media   belongs   to   social   characteristics of students in a state university; (2) determine
            network-driven sales.                               the  factors  affecting  social  commerce  acceptance;  and  (3)
                                                                determine   the   relationship   between   the   characteristics   of
            Social  commerce  became  widespread  because  the  platform
                                                                students to the factors affecting social commerce acceptance.
            that  being  utilized  is  just  near  in  fingertips.  Most  common
            activities  that   being  done  on  these  are   watching  videos,
            viewing contents, research, messaging and e-commerce.   It is
            accessible  in  the  sense  that,  anytime,  anyone  could  provide
            and  gather  data  through  social  media  platforms  as  long  as


            Copyright  ©  2018  Khenilyn  P.  Lewis  et  al.  This  is  an  open-access  article
            distributed  under  the  terms  of  the  Creative  Commons  Attribution  License  4.0,
            which  permits  unrestricted  use,  distribution,  and  reproduction  in  any  medium,
            provided the original author and source are credited.]]></page><page Index="135"><![CDATA[Circulation in Computer Science, Vol.3, No.3, pp: (1-5), May 2018
            www.ccsarchive.org

            2. RELATED LITERATURE                                Table 1. Companies and brands most liked by millennials
                                                                                  on Facebook
            1.  Social Commerce
                                                                  2013             2014              2016
            Social  commerce  is  the  used  of  social  media  to  extend  e-   Nike   Bike         Nike
            commerce. The used of online media to buy and sell products
                                                                  Apple           Apple             Sephora
            and   services   in   the   Internet.   It   encapsulates   different   Target   Amazon   Disney
            technologies  and  aspects.  Further,  the  principle  of  social   Starbucks   Target   Apple
            commerce   involved   return   of   investment,   reputation   and
                                                                Forever 21   Dunkin‘ Donuts/Forever 21   Buzzfeed/
            reach. The categories to social commerce includes the social                         Victoria‘s Secret
            network  driven  sales,  peer  to  peer  sales,  group  buying,  peer
            recommendations,     user-curated     shopping,     participatory
            commerce  and  social  shopping.  Return  of  investment,  reach   Student in a University revealed  that they feel the closeness,
            and reputation is part of its advantage (Anderson, Sims, Price   and  familiarity among the social  network  friends.  They trust
                                                                social  network  friends  and  they  enjoy  in  involving  social
            and Brusa, 2011).
                                                                commerce   activities.   They   are   committed   to   the   social
            Learning   from  forums,   communities,   ratings  and   reviews   network  community  and  they  feel  the  social  presence  on
                                                                social network. They have the high level of purchase intention
            create  a  vital  importance  in  social  commerce.  These  aspects
            could be the focus for more social commerce  exposures and   and of course they have already purchased products based on
            techniques  to  have  a  larger  volume  of  return  of investments   the  information  and  recommendations  available  on  social
            (Che,  Lu  and  Wang,  2017).  In  addition,  elements  of  social   network (Razi, Tamrin and Hussin, 2017).
            commerce are reciprocity, community, social proof, authority,   2.3  Unified  Theory  of  Acceptance  and  Use
            liking, and scarcity.
                                                                of Technology (UTAUT)
            2.2 Millennials on Social Commerce                  Research  on  individual  acceptance  and  use  of  information
                                                                technology  (IT)  is  one  of  the  most  established  and  mature
            Millennials are people born in late 1980 to early 2000. They   streams  of  information  systems  (IS)  research  (Venkatesh,
            are now the driving force of social commerce. The 35 percent
            of  millennials  used  the  ―buy‖  button  on  Facebook  and  24   Davis, & Morris, 2007). There is also research on technology
                                                                adoption   by   groups   and   organizations   (e.g.,   Sarker   &
            percent on other social media platforms. It is Facebook as the
            most popular of those platforms. Also, that 48 percent of them   Valacich,  2010;  Sarker,  Valacich,  &  Sarker,  2005;  Sia,  Lee,
            use  smart  phones  and  21  percent  use  tablets  to  purchase   Teo, & Wei, 2001; Sia, Teo, Tan, & Wei, 2004) that holds the
                                                                premise  that  one  must  first  use a  technology before  one  can
            online.  The  most  purchased  online  are  products  in  hair,  and
            beauty and apparel (Barnes and Lescault, 2018).     achieve desired outcomes, such as improvement in employee
                                                                productivity and task/job performance in organizations.



















                                                                             Fig 2: The UTAUT model
                                                                Considering  the  historical  development  of  this  theories  and
                                                                various researchers observation the most elaborated theory is
                                                                Unified Theory of Acceptance and Use of Technology which
                                                                outlines 4 key constructs (Venkatesh, Morris, Davis & Davis,
                                                                2003):
                                                                • Performance expectancy – the degree to which an individual
                                                                 believes that using the system will help him or her to attain
                                                                 gains in job performance
                                                                • Effort  expectancy –  the degree  of ease  associated  with  the
                                                                 use of the system • Social influence – the degree to which an
                                                                 individual perceives that important others believe he or she
                                                                 should  use  the  new  system  •  Facilitating  conditions  –  the
                                                                 degree to which an individual believes that an organizational
                 Fig 1: Motivation for social media engagement
                                                                 and  technical  infrastructure  exists  to  support  use  of  the
                                                                 system.



                                                                                                             1
                                                                                                             3
                                                                                                             0]]></page><page Index="136"><![CDATA[Circulation in Computer Science, Vol.3, No.3, pp: (1-5), May 2018
            www.ccsarchive.org

            3. METHODOLOGY                                      Table 2 shows that majority of the respondents is 20 years old
                                                                and  below  with  74  percentage.  Twenty  three  percent  of  the
            1. Research Design
                                                                respondents is in 21 to 30 years old and three percent is 31 to
            The  descriptive  research  design  was  used  in  this  study  to   40 years old. However, since respondents are college students,
            gather  the  information  regarding  the  factors  affecting  social   ages 41-50, 51-60 and 61 above has no percentages.
            commerce acceptance in a state university in the Philippines.
            The  study  used  survey  type  questionnaire  and  adapted  the
                                                                4.1.2 Characteristics of Participants in terms of
            factors   from   User   Acceptance   of   Technology:   Towards
            Unified View (2013).                                      sex
            2. Hypothesis                                          Table 3. Characteristics of students in terms of sex
            Null  hypothesis  state  that  there  is  no  significant  difference   Sex   Frequency   Percentage
            between  the  characteristics  and  the  factors  affecting  social   Female   47        53
            commerce acceptance of students in a State University in the   Male      53              47
            Philippines.                                            Total           100              100
            3.4 Sources of Data
                                                                In terms of sex, Table 3 shows that most of the respondents
            The primary data was obtained through survey questionnaire   are female with 53 percent while male respondents with 47
            adopted  from  the  User  Acceptance  of  Technology:  Towards
                                                                percent.
            Unified   View   (2013).   The   questionnaire   was   used   to
            determine the demographic profile of the respondents in terms   4.2 Factors Affecting Social Commerce
            of   age   and   sex   and   factors   affecting   social   commerce   Acceptance
            acceptance of students in a State University.
                                                                The  four key constructs used  in the study were  performance
            3.Participants  and  Sampling  Techniques of        expectancy, effort expectancy, social influence and facilitation
                                                                conditions.
            the Study
            The  participants  of  the  study  were  the  100  students  from
                                                                4.2.1 Performance Expectancy
            Cavite State University-Trece Martires City Campus, Cavite,
            Philippines.  The  students  are  composed  of  BS  Information
            Technology and BS Business Management students and quota   Table 4. Mean score of students’ performance expectancy
            sampling was used in selecting the participants.
                                                                   Performance Expectancy   Mean     Verbal
            4. Data to be gathered                                                                Interpretation
            The purpose of the study is to determine the characteristics of   1.  I would find the system   3.59   Agree
            the students in a State University in the Philippines in terms of   useful in my task
            age  and  sex  and  determine  the  relationship  to  the  factors
            affecting social commerce acceptance.               2.   Using the system enables me   3.64   Agree
                                                                    to accomplish tasks more
            5. Data Analysis                                        quickly.
            Descriptive   statistics   was   used   such   as   frequency   count,
            percentage  and  mean  to  determine  the  characteristics  of  the   3.  Using the system increases   3.64   Agree
            participants and factors affecting social commerce acceptance.   my productivity.
            Pearson correlation was used to find the relationship between
            the   characteristics   and   factors   affecting   social   commerce   4.  If I use the system, I will   3.60   Agree
            acceptance of students in a State University.           increase my chances of
                                                                    getting a raise.
            4.  RESULTS AND DISCUSSION
            4.1 Characteristics of Participants                            Mean             3.62     Agree
            The characteristics of the participants are determined through
            age and sex. Tables 2 and 3 shows the result of the study in
            terms of sex and age.                               Table   4   shows   the   mean   score   of   students  in   terms   of
                                                                performance expectancy of 3.62 which interpreted as ―Agree‖.
            4.1.1 Characteristics of Participants in terms of   The  result  implies  that  ―Using  the  system  enables  me  to
                 age                                            accomplish   task‖   and   ―Using   the   system   increases   my
                                                                productivity‖  has  the  highest  mean  of  3.64.  However,  ―I
               Table 2. Characteristics of students in term of age   would find the system useful in my task‖ has the lowest mean
                                                                of 3.59 but still with verbal interpretation as ―Agree‖.
                Age          Frequency       Percentage         4.2.2 Effort Expectancy
             20 & below         74               74
                21-30           23               23                Table 5. Mean score of students’ effort expectancy
                31-40           3                3
                41-50           0                0
                                                                      Effort Expectancy    Mean      Verbal
                51-60           0                0                                                Interpretation
             61 & above         0                0
                                                                1.  My interaction with the   4.19   Agree
                Total           100             100                 system would be clear and
                                                                    understandable.
                                                                2.   It would be easy for me to   4.15   Agree


                                                                                                             1
                                                                                                             3
                                                                                                             1]]></page><page Index="137"><![CDATA[Circulation in Computer Science, Vol.3, No.3, pp: (1-5), May 2018
            www.ccsarchive.org


               become skillful at using the                     4.2.5 Overall mean of factors affecting social
               system.
            3.    I would find the system easy   4.18   Agree   commerce
               to use.                                            Table 8. Overall mean score of factors affecting social
            4.   Learning to operate the   4.32   Agree                   commerce acceptance of students
               system is easy for me.
                                                                       Factors         Mean        Verbal
                      Mean              4.21     Agree
                                                                                                 Interpretation
                                                                Performance Expectancy   3.62       Agree
            Table 5  shows the  mean  score of students in  terms  of effort   Effort Expectancy   4.21   Agree
            expectancy  of  4.21  with  verbal  interpretation  as  ―Agree‖.
                                                                Social Influence        3.76        Agree
            ―Learning  to  operate  the  system  is  easy  for  me‖  has  the   Facilitating Conditions   3.56   Agree
            highest mean of 4.32 and ―It would be easy for me to become
            skillful   at   using   the   system‖   has   lowest   mean   but   both   Mean   3.79   Agree
            interpreted as ―Agree‖.
                                                                Table  8  shows  the  overall  mean  score  of  factors  affecting
            4.2.3 Social Influence                              social commerce acceptance of students in a State University.
                                                                Performance  expectancy  is  3.62,  effort  expectancy  is  4.21,
                Table 6. Mean score of students’ social influence   social influence is 3.76 and facilitating conditions is 3.56, all
                  Social Influence     Mean      Verbal         factors has verbal interpretation as ―Agree‖.
                                              Interpretation
            1.   People who influence my   3.69   Agree         4.3.Relationship between sex and factors
               behavior think that I should                         affecting social commerce acceptance
               use the system.
            2.   People who are important to   3.69   Agree       Table 9. Relationship between sex and factors affecting
               me think that I should use the                               social commerce acceptance
               system.
                                                                               PEARSON         SIGNIFICANCE
            3.   The senior management of   3.78   Agree                    CORRELATION
               this business has been helpful
               in the use of the system.                        Female          0.411184          Moderate
                                                                Male            0.215309            Low
            4.     In general, the organization   3.90   Agree
               has supported the use of the
               system.                                          Table   9   shows  the  relationship   between   sex  and   factors
                                                                affecting social commerce acceptance. Male respondents have
                      Mean              3.76     Agree
                                                                low   significance   and   female   respondents   with   moderate
                                                                significance.   Result   implies   that   female   respondents   has
            Table 6 shows the mean score of students in terms of social   significant    relationship    to    the    factors    affecting    social
            influence  has  a  mean  of  3.76  with  verbal  interpretation  as   commerce acceptance of students in a State University.
            ―Agree‖. ―In  general,  the organization  has supported the use
            of the system‖ has the highest mean of 3.90 and interpreted as   4.4.Relationship between sex and factors
            ―Agree‖. However, ―People who influence my behavior think   affecting social commerce acceptance
            that I should use the system‖ and ―People who are important
            to me think that I should use the system‖ has lowest mean of
            3.69 but still ―Agree‖ as construed.                 Table 10. Relationship between age and factors affecting
                                                                            social commerce acceptance
            4.2.4 Facilitating Conditions
                                                                               PEARSON         SIGNIFICANCE
             Table 7. Mean score of students’ facilitating conditions       CORRELATION
                                                                20 & below      0.215664            Low
                Facilitating Conditions   Mean   Verbal         21-30           0.014173         Negligible
                                              Interpretation
                                                                31-40           0.188982         Negligible
            1.   I have the resources necessary   3.86   Agree
               to use the system.
                                                                Table 10 shows the relationship between age and the factors
                                                                affecting  social  commerce  acceptance  of  students.  Ages  20
            2.   I have the knowledge   3.65     Agree
               necessary to use the system.                     and below has low signification correlation. However, 21-30
                                                                and  41  above  years  of age  has  no  correlation  to  the  factors.
            3.   The system is not compatible   3.23   Agree    Result   implies   that   respondents   aged   20   and   below   has
               with other systems I use.
                                                                significant relationship to the factors.
            4.   A specific person (or group)   3.50   Agree
               is available for assistance                      5.  CONCLUSION
               with the system difficulties.                    The  study  determined  that  there  is  significant  relationship
                      Mean              3.56     Agree          between sex and age to the factors affecting social commerce
                                                                acceptance of students in a State University in the Philippines.
            Table   7   shows   the   mean   score   of   students  in   terms   of   Fifty  three  percent  of  the  respondents  are  female,  and  forty
            facilitating  condition  of  3.76  with  verbal  interpretation  as   seven percent are male. In terms of age, 20 years and below
            ―Agree‖. ―I have the resources necessary to  use the system‖   has  seventy  four  percent  of  the  respondents  and  aged  21-30
            has  the  highest  mean  of  3.86  and  interpreted  as  ―Agree‖.   has 23 percent. The used of User Acceptance of Technology:
            However, ―The system is not compatible with other systems I   Towards  Unified  View,  determine  the  factors  of  the  social
            use‖ has lowest mean of 3.23 but still interpreted as ―Agree‖.
                                                                commerce  acceptance  of  students  in  a  State  University.  The


                                                                                                             1
                                                                                                             3
                                                                                                             2]]></page><page Index="138"><![CDATA[Circulation in Computer Science, Vol.3, No.3, pp: (1-5), May 2018
            www.ccsarchive.org

            overall  mean  of  3.79  shows  that  the  respondents  agree  in   [4]  Chahal,  M.  .(2016).  Social  commerce:  How  willing  are
            social commerce and Pearson correlation denotes that there is   consumers to buy through social media? Retrieved from
            relationship  to  the  factors  in  terms  of  in  age  and  sex.  In   https://www.marketingweek.com/2016/03/23/social-
            addition, result shows that female respondents have moderate   commerce-how-willing-are-consumers-to-buy-through-
            correlation  to  the  factors  and  aged  20  and  below  has  low   social-media/
            correlation.  The  result  of  the  study  could  be  the  basis  for
            future researches related to social commerce and students in a   [5] Cummings,   C.   (2015).   Infographic:   How   Your   Age
            State University.                                       Affects What You Share on Social Media Retrieved from
                                                                    http://www.adweek.com/brand-marketing/infographic-
            6. ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS                                     how-your-age-affects-what-you-share-social-media-
            Our  thanks  to  Cavite  State  University-Trece  Martires  City   166878/
            Campus,  Trece  Martires  City,  Cavite,  Philippines  and  AMA   [6]  Channeladvisor.  (2017).  Selling  in  the  Age  of  Social
            University,  Quezon  City,  Philippines  for  providing  us  the   Commerce. Channeladvisor Corporation.
            necessary documents and data.
                                                                [7] Bowman, M., Debray,  S. K., and Peterson, L. L.  (1993).
            7. REFERENCES                                           Reasoning about naming systems
            [1]   Mohamed   Jalaldeen   Mohamed   Razi,   Mohd   Izzuddin
               Mohd   Tamrin,   &   Husnayati   Hussin.   (2017).   Social   [8] Venkatesh, V., Morris, M. G., Davis, G. B. and Davis, F.
               commerce    behavior    among    university    students    in   (2003).  User  Acceptance  of  Information  Technology:
               Malaysia   in   Zulikha,   J.   &   N.   H.   Zakaria   (Eds.),   Toward a Unified View. MIS Quarterly, (27: 3)
               Proceedings   of   the   6th   International   Conference   of   [9]  Anderson;  Matt;  Sims,  Joe;  Price,  Jerell;  Brusa,  Jennifer
               Computing & Informatics  (pp  350-355).  Sintok: School   (2011). "Turning "Like" to  "Buy" social  media emerges
               of Computing.                                        as  a  commerce  channel"(PDF). Booz  &  Company  Inc.
                                                                    Retrieved 2014-12-04.
            [2]  Social Commerce:  Which  Social  Media Platforms  Drive  the
               Most    Sales?.   (2017).   Retrieved   from     [10]  Chen,  A.,  Lu,  Y.  and  Wang,  B.  (2017).  Customers‘
               https://www.shopify.com.ph/infographics/social-      purchase decision-making process in social commerce: A
               commerce                                             social   learning   perspective.   International   Journal   of
                                                                    Information  Management  Volume  37,  Issue  6.  Pages
            [3] Number of Facebook users in the Philippines from 2015 to
                                                                    627-638
               2022   (in   millions).   (2018).   Retrieved   from
               https://www.statista.com/statistics/490455/number-of-   [11]  Razi,  M.,  Tamrin,  M,  and  Hussin,  H.  (2017).  Social
               philippines-facebook-users/                          Commerce   Behavior   Among   University   Students   In
                                                                    Malaysia.  6  th  International  Conference  on  Computing
                                                                    and  Informatics,  ICOCI  2017  25-27April,  2017  Kuala
                                                                    Lumpur. Universiti Utara Malaysia.












































            CCS | 2018 | ISSN 2456-3692                                                                     5
            Published by: CSL Press, USA]]></page><page Index="139"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                            SYSTEM — INPUTS AND


                                           PROCESSES











               S.2  The institution has incentives for:


                             S.2.3 outstanding research,


                             related performance and
























                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="140"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="141"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="142"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="143"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="144"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="145"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="146"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="147"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="148"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="149"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="150"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="151"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="152"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="153"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="154"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                            SYSTEM — INPUTS AND


                                           PROCESSES











               S.2  The institution has incentives for:


                             S.2.4 outstanding research,


                             related performance and
























                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="155"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="156"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="157"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="158"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="159"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="160"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="161"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="162"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="163"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="164"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="165"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="166"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="167"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="168"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="169"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="170"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="171"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="172"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="173"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="174"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="175"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="176"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="177"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="178"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="179"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="180"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                            SYSTEM — INPUTS AND


                                           PROCESSES











               S.2  The institution has incentives for:


                             S.2.4 patented outputs.




























                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="181"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.1.          The institution provides


                             opportunities for the


                             dissemination of research results

                             in fora, conferences, seminars,


                             and other related means
















                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="182"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="183"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="184"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="185"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="186"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="187"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="188"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="189"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="190"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="191"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="192"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="193"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="194"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="195"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="196"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="197"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="198"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="199"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="200"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="201"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="202"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="203"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="204"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="205"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="206"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="207"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="208"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="209"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="210"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="211"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="212"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="213"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="214"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="215"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="216"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="217"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="218"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="219"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="220"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="221"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="222"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="223"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="224"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="225"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="226"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="227"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="228"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="229"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="230"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="231"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="232"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="233"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="234"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="235"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="236"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="237"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="238"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="239"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="240"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="241"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.2 The institution regularly publishes a


               research journal.




























                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="242"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="243"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="244"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="245"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="246"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="247"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="248"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="249"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="250"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="251"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="252"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="253"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="254"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="255"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="256"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="257"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="258"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="259"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="260"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="261"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="262"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="263"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="264"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="265"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="266"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="267"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="268"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="269"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.3           Library exchange of research


                             publications with other HEI's and


                             agencies is maintained.























                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="270"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="271"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="272"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="273"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="274"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="275"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="276"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="277"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="278"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="279"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="280"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="281"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="282"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="283"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="284"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="285"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="286"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="287"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="288"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="289"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="290"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="291"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="292"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="293"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="294"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="295"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="296"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="297"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="298"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="299"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="300"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="301"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="302"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="303"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.4           Research manuscript/technical


                             reports are well-written and


                             edited following the institutional

                             format.





















                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="304"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="305"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="306"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="307"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="308"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="309"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="310"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="311"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="312"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="313"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="314"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="315"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="316"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="317"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="318"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="319"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.5.          The institution supports the


                             researchers in all of the following


                             activities:


                                            I.5.1 Instructional Materials


                                            Development;
















                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="320"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="321"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="322"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="323"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="324"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="325"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="326"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="327"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="328"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="329"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="330"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="331"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="332"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="333"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="334"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="335"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="336"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="337"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="338"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="339"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="340"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="341"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="342"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="343"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="344"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="345"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="346"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="347"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="348"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="349"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="350"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="351"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="352"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.5.          The institution supports the


                             researchers in all of the following


                             activities:


                                            I.5.2. paper presentations,


                                            journal publication,


                                            classroom lectures, and


                                            other similar activities;








                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="353"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="354"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="355"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="356"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="357"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="358"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="359"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="360"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="361"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="362"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="363"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="364"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="365"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="366"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="367"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="368"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="369"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="370"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="371"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="372"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="373"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="374"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="375"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="376"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="377"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="378"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="379"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="380"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="381"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="382"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="383"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="384"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="385"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="386"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="387"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="388"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="389"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="390"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="391"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="392"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="393"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="394"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="395"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="396"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="397"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="398"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="399"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="400"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.5.          The institution supports the


                             researchers in all of the following


                             activities:


                                            I.5.3. editorship/writing in


                                            academic, scientific and


                                            professional journals;












                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="401"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="402"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="403"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="404"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="405"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="406"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="407"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="408"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="409"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="410"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="411"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="412"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="413"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="414"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="415"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="416"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="417"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="418"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.5.          The institution supports the


                             researchers in all of the following


                             activities:


                                            I.5.4. thesis/dissertation


                                            advising; and
















                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="419"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="420"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="421"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="422"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="423"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="424"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="425"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="426"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.5.          The institution supports the


                             researchers in all of the following


                             activities:


                                            I.5.5. patenting of research


                                            outputs.
















                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="427"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="428"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="429"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="430"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="431"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="432"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="433"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="434"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="435"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="436"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="437"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="438"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="439"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="440"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="441"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="442"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="443"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="444"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.6.          Research results are published


                             preferably in refereed journals.




























                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="445"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="446"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="447"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="448"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="449"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="450"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="451"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="452"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="453"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="454"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="455"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="456"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="457"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="458"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="459"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="460"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="461"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="462"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="463"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="464"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="465"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="466"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="467"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="468"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="469"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="470"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="471"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="472"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.7.          Research results are


                             disseminated to the target


                             clientele.
























                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="473"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="474"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="475"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="476"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="477"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="478"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="479"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="480"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="481"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="482"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="483"/><page Index="484"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="485"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="486"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="487"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="488"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="489"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="490"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="491"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="492"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="493"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="494"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="495"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="496"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="497"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="498"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="499"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="500"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="501"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="502"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="503"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="504"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="505"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="506"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="507"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="508"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="509"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="510"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="511"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="512"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="513"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="514"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="515"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="516"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="517"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="518"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="519"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="520"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="521"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="522"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="523"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="524"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="525"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="526"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="527"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="528"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="529"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="530"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="531"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="532"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="533"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="534"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="535"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="536"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="537"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="538"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="539"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="540"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="541"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="542"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="543"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="544"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="545"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="546"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="547"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="548"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="549"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="550"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="551"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="552"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="553"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="554"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="555"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="556"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="557"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="558"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="559"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="560"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="561"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="562"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="563"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="564"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="565"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="566"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="567"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="568"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="569"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="570"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="571"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="572"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="573"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                    IMPLEMENTATION















               I.8.          The College/Academic Unit


                             generates income from patents,


                             licenses, copyrights, and other

                             research outputs.





















                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="574"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="575"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="576"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="577"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="578"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="579"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="580"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="581"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="582"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="583"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="584"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="585"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="586"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="587"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="588"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="589"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="590"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="591"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="592"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="593"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="594"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="595"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                            OUTCOME/S















               O.1   Research outputs are published


                             in refereed journals.




























                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="596"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY

                                      AREA V: RESEARCH













                                       PARAMETER D:



                                  PUBLICATION AND



                                      DISSEMINATION










                                           OUTCOME/S











                   O.1   Research outputs are utilized





































                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="597"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="598"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="599"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="600"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="601"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="602"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="603"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="604"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="605"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="606"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="607"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="608"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="609"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="610"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="611"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="612"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="613"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="614"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="615"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="616"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="617"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="618"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="619"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="620"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="621"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="622"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="623"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="624"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="625"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="626"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="627"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="628"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="629"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="630"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="631"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="632"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="633"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="634"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="635"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="636"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="637"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="638"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="639"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                                        AREA V: RESEARCH











                                       PARAMETER D:




                                   PUBLICATION AND


                                       DISSEMINATION













                                            OUTCOME/S















               O.2   Research outputs are utilized.
































                       Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="640"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="641"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="642"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="643"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="644"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="645"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="646"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="647"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="648"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="649"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="650"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="651"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="652"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="653"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="654"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="655"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="656"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="657"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="658"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="659"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="660"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="661"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="662"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="663"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="664"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="665"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="666"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="667"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="668"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="669"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="670"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="671"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="672"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="673"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="674"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="675"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="676"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="677"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="678"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="679"><![CDATA[PARAMETER D:



                                  PUBLICATION AND



                                      DISSEMINATION










                                           OUTCOME/S











                   O.3   Research outputs are utilized]]></page><page Index="680"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="681"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="682"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="683"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="684"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="685"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="686"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="687"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="688"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="689"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="690"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="691"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="692"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="693"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="694"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="695"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="696"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="697"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="698"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="699"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="700"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="701"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="702"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="703"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="704"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="705"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="706"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="707"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="708"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="709"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="710"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="711"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="712"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="713"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="714"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="715"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="716"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="717"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="718"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>
