<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="24"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[IN THE YEAR 2015, LEADERS FROM 193 COUNTRIES OF THE WORLD
       CAME TOGETHER TO FACE THE FUTURE.


       And what they saw was daunting. Famines. Drought. Wars. Plagues. Poverty.
       Not just in some faraway place, but in their own cities and towns and villages.


       They knew things didn’t have to be this way. They knew we had enough
       food to feed the world, but that it wasn’t getting shared. They knew there
       were medicines for HIV and other diseases, but they cost a lot. They knew
       that earthquakes and floods were inevitable, but that the high death
       tolls were not.


       They also knew that billions of people worldwide shared their hope for a
       better future.

       So leaders from these countries created a plan called the Sustainable
       Development Goals (SDGs). This set of 17 goals imagines a future just 15 years

       off that would be rid of poverty and hunger, and safe from the worst effects of
       climate change. It’s an ambitious plan.

       But there’s ample evidence that we can succeed. In the past 15 years, the
       international community cut extreme poverty in half.


       Now we can finish the job.

       The United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) is one of the leading
       organizations working to fulfil the SDGs by the year 2030. Present in nearly

       170 countries and territories, we help nations make the Goals a reality.
       We also champion the Goals so that people everywhere know how to
       do their part.

       UNDP is proud to continue as a leader in this global movement.


       Learn about the Sustainable Development Goals.  What’s your Goal?]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[END EXTREME POVERTY IN ALL FORMS

          BY 2030.


          Yes, it’s an ambitious goal—but we believe it can be done. In 2000, the
          world committed to halving the number of people living in extreme
          poverty by the year 2015 and we met this goal. However, more than
          800 million people around the world still live on less than $1.25 a day—
          that’s about the equivalent of the entire population of Europe living in

          extreme poverty. Now it’s time to build on what we learned and end
          poverty altogether.]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[END HUNGER, ACHIEVE FOOD SECURITY

          AND IMPROVED NUTRITION AND PROMOTE
          SUSTAINABLE AGRICULTURE



          In the past 20 years, hunger has dropped by almost half. Many
          countries that used to suffer from famine and hunger can now
          meet the nutritional needs of their most vulnerable people. It’s an
          incredible accomplishment. Now we can go further and end hunger
          and malnutrition once and for all. That means doing things such as
          promoting sustainable agriculture and supporting small farmers. It’s a tall
          order. But for the sake of the nearly 1 out of every 9 people on earth who

          go to bed hungry every night, we’ve got to try. Imagine a world where
          everyone has access to sufficient and nutritious food all year round.
          Together, we can make that a reality by 2030.]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[ENSURE HEALTHY LIVES AND PROMOTE
          WELL-BEING FOR ALL AT ALL AGES


          We all know how important it is to be in good health. Our health affects
          everything from how much we enjoy life to what work we can perform.
          That’s why there’s a Goal to make sure everyone has health coverage
          and access to safe and effective medicines and vaccines. In the 25

          years before the SDGs, we made big strides—preventable child deaths
          dropped by more than half, and maternal mortality went down by
          almost as much. And yet some other numbers remain tragically high, like
          the fact that 6 million children die every year before their fifth birthday,
          or that AIDS is the leading cause of death for adolescents in sub-Saharan
          Africa. We have the means to turn that around and make good health
          more than just a wish.]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[ENSURE INCLUSIVE AND EQUITABLE QUALITY
          EDUCATION AND PROMOTE LIFELONG

          LEARNING OPPORTUNITIES FOR ALL


          First, the bad news on education. Poverty, armed conflict and other
          emergencies keep many, many kids around the world out of school. In
          fact, kids from the poorest households are four times more likely to be
          out of school than those of the richest households. Now for some good
          news. Since 2000, there has been enormous progress on the goal to

          provide primary education to all children worldwide: the total enrolment
          rate in developing regions has reached 91%. By measures in any school,
          that’s a good grade. Now, let’s get an even better grade for all kids,
          and achieve the goal of universal primary and secondary education,
          affordable vocational training, access to higher education and more.]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[ACHIEVE GENDER EQUALITY AND
          EMPOWER ALL WOMEN AND GIRLS



          We can celebrate the great progress the world has made in becoming
          more prosperous and fair. But there’s a shadow to the celebration. In
          just about every way, women and girls lag behind. There are still gross
          inequalities in work and wages, lots of unpaid “women’s work” such as
          child care and domestic work, and discrimination in public decision-
          making. But there are grounds for hope. More girls are in school now
          compared to in 2000. Most regions have reached gender parity in
          primary education. The percentage of women getting paid for their work

          is on the rise. The Sustainable Development Goals aim to build on these
          achievements to ensure that there is an end to discrimination against
          women and girls everywhere.]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[ENSURE AVAILABILITY AND SUSTAINABLE
          MANAGEMENT OF WATER AND SANITATION
          FOR ALL



          Everyone on earth should have access to safe and affordable drinking
          water. That’s the goal for 2030. While many people take clean drinking
          water and sanitation for granted, many others don’t. Water scarcity
          affects more than 40 percent of people around the world, and that

          number is projected to go even higher as a result of climate change.
          If we continue the path we’re on, by 2050 at least one in four people
          are likely to be affected by recurring water shortages. But we can take
          a new path—more international cooperation, protecting wetlands
          and rivers, sharing water-treatment technologies—that leads to
          accomplishing this Goal.]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[ENSURE ACCESS TO AFFORDABLE, RELIABLE,
          SUSTAINABLE AND MODERN ENERGY FOR
          ALL



          Between 1990 and 2010, the number of people with access to electricity
          increased by 1.7 billion. That’s progress to be proud of. And yet as the
          world’s population continues to rise, still more people will need cheap
          energy to light their homes and streets, use phones and computers,
          and do their everyday business. How we get that energy is at issue; fossil
          fuels and greenhouse gas emissions are making drastic changes in the
          climate, leading to big problems on every continent. Instead, we can
          become more energy-efficient and invest in clean energy sources such
          as solar and wind. That way we’ll meet electricity needs and protect the

          environment. How’s that for a balancing act?]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[PROMOTE SUSTAINED, INCLUSIVE AND
          SUSTAINABLE ECONOMIC GROWTH, FULL
          AND PRODUCTIVE EMPLOYMENT AND

          DECENT WORK FOR ALL


          An important part of economic growth is that people have jobs that
          pay enough to support themselves and their families. The good news
          is that the middle class is growing worldwide—almost tripling in size

          in developing countries in the last 25 years, to more than a third of the
          population. But today, job growth is not keeping pace with the growing
          labour force. Things don’t have to be that way. We can promote policies
          that encourage entrepreneurship and job creation. We can eradicate
          forced labour, slavery and human trafficking. And in the end we can
          achieve the goal of decent work for all women and men by 2030.]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[BUILD RESILIENT INFRASTRUCTURE,
          PROMOTE INCLUSIVE AND SUSTAINABLE
          INDUSTRIALIZATION AND FOSTER

          INNOVATION


          Technological progress helps us address big global challenges such as
          creating jobs and becoming more energy efficient. For example, the
          world is becoming ever more interconnected and prosperous thanks to

          the internet. The more connected we are, the more we can all benefit
          from the wisdom and contributions of people everywhere on earth.  And
          yet four billion people have no way of getting online, the vast majority
          of them in developing countries. The more we invest in innovation
          and infrastructure, the better off we’ll all be. Bridging the digital divide,
          promoting sustainable industries, and investing in scientific research and
          innovation are all important ways to facilitate sustainable development.]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[REDUCE INEQUALITY WITHIN AND AMONG

          COUNTRIES



          It’s an old story: the rich get richer, and the poor get poorer. The divide
          has never been starker. We can and must adopt policies that create
          opportunity for everyone, regardless of who they are or where they
          come from. Income inequality is a global problem that requires global
          solutions. That means improving the regulation of financial markets
          and institutions, sending development aid where it is most needed
          and helping people migrate safely so they can pursue opportunities.
          Together, we can now change the direction of the old story of inequality.]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[MAKE CITIES AND HUMAN SETTLEMENTS
          INCLUSIVE, SAFE, RESILIENT AND
          SUSTAINABLE



          If you’re like most people, you live in a city. More than half the world’s
          population now lives in cities, and that figure will go to about two-thirds
          of humanity by the year 2050. Cities are getting bigger. In 1990 there
          were ten “mega-cities” with 10 million inhabitants or more. In 2014, there
          were 28 mega-cities, home to 453 million people. Incredible, huh? A lot

          of people love cities; they’re centers of culture and business and life. The
          thing is, they’re also often centers of extreme poverty. To make cities
          sustainable for all, we can create good, affordable public housing. We
          can upgrade slum settlements. We can invest in public transport, create
          green spaces, and get a broader range of people involved in urban
          planning decisions. That way, we can keep the things we love about
          cities, and change the things we don’t.]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[ENSURE SUSTAINABLE CONSUMPTION AND
         PRODUCTION PATTERNS


         Some people use a lot of stuff, and some people use very little—in fact,
         a big share of the world population is consuming too little to meet even

         their basic needs. Instead, we can have a world where everybody gets
         what they need to survive and thrive. And we can consume in a way
         that preserves our natural resources so that our children can enjoy them,
         and their children and their children after that. The hard part is how to
         achieve that goal. We can manage our natural resources more efficiently
         and dispose of toxic waste better. Cut per capita food waste in half
         globally. Get businesses and consumers to reduce and recycle waste.
         And help countries that have typically not consumed a lot to move
         towards more responsible consumption patterns.]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[TAKE URGENT ACTION TO COMBAT CLIMATE
          CHANGE AND ITS IMPACTS



          Every country in the world is seeing the drastic effects of climate
          change, some more than others. On average, the annual losses just
          from earthquakes, tsunamis, tropical cyclones and flooding count in the
          hundreds of billions of dollars. We can reduce the loss of life and property
          by helping more vulnerable regions—such as land-locked countries
          and island states—become more resilient. It is still possible, with the
          political will and technological measures, to limit the increase in global

          mean temperature to two degrees Celsius above pre-industrial levels—
          and thus avoid the worst effects of climate change. The Sustainable
          Development Goals lay out a way for countries to work together to meet
          this urgent challenge.]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[CONSERVE AND SUSTAINABLY USE THE
          OCEANS, SEAS AND MARINE RESOURCES
          FOR SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT



          The oceans make human life possible. Their temperature, their chemistry,
          their currents, their life forms. For one thing, more than 3 billion people
          depend on marine and coastal diversity for their livelihoods. But today
          we are seeing nearly a third of the world’s fish stocks overexploited.
          That’s not a sustainable way of life. Even people who live nowhere near
          the ocean can’t live without it. Oceans absorb about 30 percent of the
          carbon dioxide that humans produce; but we’re producing more carbon

          dioxide than ever before and that makes the oceans more acidic—26%
          more, since the start of the industrial revolution. Our trash doesn’t help
          either—13,000 pieces of plastic litter on every square kilometer of ocean.
          Sounds bad, right? Don’t despair! The Sustainable Development Goals
          indicate targets for managing and protecting life below water.]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[PROTECT, RESTORE AND PROMOTE
          SUSTAINABLE USE OF TERRESTRIAL
          ECOSYSTEMS, SUSTAINABLY MANAGE

          FORESTS, COMBAT DESERTIFICATION, AND
          HALT AND REVERSE LAND DEGRADATION
          AND HALT BIODIVERSITY LOSS



          Humans and other animals rely on other forms of life on land for food,
          clean air, clean water, and as a means of combatting climate change.
          Plant life makes up 80% of the human diet. Forests, which cover 30%
          of the Earth’s surface, help keep the air and water clean and the Earth’s
          climate in balance. That’s not to mention they’re home to millions of

          animal species. But the land and life on it are in trouble. Arable land
          is disappearing 30 to 35 times faster than it has historically. Deserts
          are spreading. Animal breeds are going extinct. We can turn these
          trends around. Fortunately, the Sustainable Development Goals aim to
          conserve and restore the use of terrestrial ecosystems such as forests,
          wetlands, drylands and mountains by 2030.]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[PROMOTE PEACEFUL AND INCLUSIVE
          SOCIETIES FOR SUSTAINABLE
          DEVELOPMENT, PROVIDE ACCESS TO

          JUSTICE FOR ALL AND BUILD EFFECTIVE,
          ACCOUNTABLE AND INCLUSIVE
          INSTITUTIONS AT ALL LEVELS



          How can a country develop—how can people eat and teach and learn
          and work and raise families—without peace? And how can a country
          have peace without justice, without human rights, without government
          based on the rule of law? Some parts of the world enjoy relative peace
          and justice, and may come to take it for granted. Other parts seem to

          be plagued by armed conflict, crime, torture and exploitation, all of
          which hinders their development. The goal of peace and justice is one
          for all countries to strive towards. The Sustainable Development Goals
          aim to reduce all forms of violence and propose that governments
          and communities find lasting solutions to conflict and insecurity. That
          means strengthening the rule of law, reducing the flow of illicit arms,
          and bringing developing countries more into the center of institutions
          of global governance.]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[STRENGTHEN THE MEANS OF
          IMPLEMENTATION AND REVITALIZE THE
          GLOBAL PARTNERSHIP FOR SUSTAINABLE

          DEVELOPMENT


          The Sustainable Development Goals are pretty big to-do list, don’t you
          think? In fact, it’s so big, you may just want to throw your hands up in the
          air. “Forget it! Can’t be done! Why even try!” But we’ve got a lot going for
          us. The world is more interconnected today than ever before, thanks to
          the internet, travel and global institutions. There’s a growing consensus
          about the need to work together to stop climate change. And the

          Sustainable Development Goals are no small matter either. 193 countries
          agreed on these goals. Pretty incredible, isn’t it? 193 countries agreeing
          on anything? The final goal lays out a way for nations to work together to
          achieve all the other Goals.]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[?       WHAT CAN



                 I DO TO HELP








          There are many ways to show your support and help us reach
          the Sustainable Development Goals by 2030. Here are a few :






          Make a donation

          Money doesn’t just make the world go around; it’s also the most direct
          way to reduce and eradicate all forms of poverty.

          Start a fundraiser

          Fundraising is a great way to raise money, create awareness, and inspire
          others. Plus, it’s fun!
          Go shopping

          Visit shop.undp.org for SDG merchandise, and show off the goals you’re
          most passionate about.

          Spread the word

          Search for @UNDP on Twitter, Facebook and Instagram, and share the
          content you love.


          To donate or learn more about fundraising, visit undp.org/takeaction]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[NOTES]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[NOTES]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>