<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="99"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE





                                            AREA IV- SUPPORT TO STUDENTS


               PARAMETER A – STUDENT SERVICES PROGRAM (SSP)


               1. SYSTEM-INPUTS AND PROCESSES

                            ➢  Present the BOR/BOT approved Student Services Program.

                                     The Student Services Program of the University is under the Office of the


                              Student  Affairs  and  Services  (OSAS).  Through  the  years,  the  office  had

                              undergone a series of renaming. It has changed to Student Services Project in

                              1986.  Student  Services  in  1989,  Student  Services  in  1991  and  was  again

                              renamed as Office of Student Affairs (OSA) in 1998 when DSAC (Don Severino

                              delas  Alas  Campus)  was  elevated  into  university,  currently  known  as  Cavite


                              State  University.  The  different  services  offered  by  OSA  and  its  guidelines  are

                              stated  in  the  student  handbook  and  were  based  from  the  CvSU  Manual  of

                              Operations  2009  which  was  approved  by  the  Board  of  Regents  (BOR)  on

                              September  3,  2009  per  Res.  No.  85,s.2009.  To  include  relevant  information

                              about the university, the handbook was updated and approved by the BOR per

                              Res. No. 84, s. 2006.

                                     When the Commission on Higher Education promulgated the “Enhanced

                              Policies and Guidelines on Student Affairs and Services” on April 19, 2013 (CMO


                              no.  19,  s.  2013),  the  Office  of  Student  Affairs  conducted  a  workshop  on

                              September 22, 2014 to review and revise its existing policies and guidelines with

                              reference to the enhanced policies and guideline from CHED. As an output, a

                              proposal to rename the OSA to OSAS was made as well as the revision of the


                              composition and organization structure of the unit.








                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     In  December  19,  2014,  the  OSA  was  officially  renamed  as  Office  of

                              Student  Affairs  and  Services  (OSAS)  by  virtue  of  BOR  Resolution  no.  77,  s.


                              2014. The office provides different student services to its client such as guidance

                              and counselling, admission and testing, and student development services like

                              the  student  organization  and  socio-cultural  affairs,  student  publication  and

                              placement of students and graduates. The mandated National Service Training

                              Program (NSTP) subject was also offered by the office since 2002. As a sign of

                              commitment to serve its client efficiently, the OSAS conducted another Workshop

                              on  Review  and  Revision  of  Student  Welfare  Services  of  the  CvSU  Manual  of


                              Operation last June 14-16, 2016 with reference to CMO no. 19, s. 2013. While

                              waiting  for  the  approval  of  the  revised  Student  Welfare  Services  the  office

                              continued  and  remain  committed  to  provide  student  welfare  and  development

                              activities to the CvSU Academic community and the public.


               2. IMPLEMENTATION

                            ➢  A.1. Describe the Institution’s Student Services Program and its components.

                                     The  Student  Services  and  Program  prepared  by  the  Office  of  Student

                              Affairs was designed to wholly develop the students of the University viz-a-viz the

                              vision-mission  of  the  University.  The  basic  services  provided  by  the  Student


                              Services Program are divided into four:

                                   a.        Student Welfare Services (SWS) shall deliver student services

                                             and programs needed to ensure and promote the well-being of

                                             student.  These  include  Information  and  Orientation  Services,

                                             Guidance and Counselling Services; Career and Job Placement


                                             Services,  Student  Handbook  Development  and  the  Economic

                                             Enterprise Development.





                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                   b.        Student  Development  Services  shall  provide  services  and

                                             programs  designed  from  exploration,  enhancement  and

                                             development for students’ full potential for personal development,


                                             leadership  and  social  responsibility  through  various  institutional

                                             student activities. The services include Student Organization and

                                             Activities,  Leadership  Training,  Student  Council/Government,

                                             Student Discipline and Student Publication.

                                   c.        Institutional  Student  Program  and  Services  shall  provide

                                             programs  to  serve  the  need  of  the  students,  develop  their


                                             individuality  and  spiritual  identity  and  also,  respond  to  basic

                                             health,  food,  shelterand  safety  concerns  of  all  students.  This

                                             include Admission Service Scholarship and financial Assistance

                                             (SFA), Food Service, Health and Wellness, Safety and Security

                                             Services  and student  Housing  and  Residential  Services.  In  the


                                             revised  Student  Affairs  and  Services,  Multi-faith  and  Inter-faith

                                             Services,  Foreign  and  International  Student  Services,  Services

                                             for Student with Special Needs, Culture and Arts Programs are

                                             now specified.

                                   d.        Research,  Monitoring  and  Evaluation  of  Student  Services

                                             Unit  shall  conduct  researches  related  to  student  welfare  and

                                             development,  and  shall  be  in-charge  of  evaluating  results  in


                                             institutional development.


                            ➢  A.2. State the Objectives of the Student Services Program

                                     The Office of Student Affairs and Services shall able to:








                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     1.     regularly implement comprehensive guidance programs with a full

                                            range  of    activities  suas  assessment,  information,  consultation,


                                            counselling, referral, placement, follow-up and follow-through;

                                     2.     implement  effective  information  and  orientation  strategies  in

                                            promoting awareness on student rights and obligations;

                                     3.     provide  financial  assistance  grants,  service  and  job  experience

                                            programs,  student  loans  and  mutual  aid  funds,  giving  priority  to

                                            those belonging  to the vulnerable and marginalized sector;

                                     4.     provide  leadership  trainings  to  enhance  leadership  effectiveness


                                            of students, both at personal and organization levels;

                                     5.     strictly  implement  institutional  rules  and  regulations  governing

                                            student  behavior  to  be  able  to  produce  morally  upright

                                            professionals;

                                     6.     provide avenues to hone students’ talents and interests to ensure


                                            social and cultural growth;

                                     7.     implement  relevant  sports  development  programs  to  provide  the

                                            opportunities  for  athletic  competition,  physical  fitness  and  well-

                                            being of students;

                                     8.     develop skills and potential of student writers;

                                     9.     promote  student  involvement  in  community  development

                                            programs;


                                     10.    provide  an  environment  conducive  to  free  expression  of  one’s

                                            religious orientation in accordance with institutional principles.


                            ➢  A.3.  Present  the  Organizational  Structure  of  the  Student  Services
                                Program/Units






                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE












































                            ➢  A.4. Describe the Profile of the Student Services Program Officials


                 Student Services     Unit Head/Designated          Educational             Length of
                  Program/Units              Position              Qualification       Experience in SSP

               1.  Coordinator of     LILIAN O. SIDAMON        Master  in  Business  3 years
               Office of Student                               Administration
               Affairs and Services
                                                               Licensed  Professional
                                                               Teacher

               2.  Guidance           GIDEON LUKE P. TY        Units in Master of Arts  3 years
               Services                                        in Psychology

                                                               Licensed
                                                               Psychometrician

               3.  Job Placement      LILIAN O. SIDAMON        Master  in  Business  3 years
               Services/ Student                               Administration
               Welfare Services
                                                               Licensed  Professional
                                                               Teacher






                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




               4.  Scholarship and    LILIAN O. SIDAMON        Master  in  Business  3 years
               Financial Assistance                            Administration
               Services
                                                               Licensed  Professional
                                                               Teacher

               5. Student             LILIAN O. SIDAMON        Master  in  Business  3 years
               Organization                                    Administration

                                                               Licensed  Professional
                                                               Teacher

               6. Student             GIDEON LUKE P. TY        Units in Master of Arts  3 years
               Publication Services                            in Psychology

                                                               Licensed
                                                               Psychometrician

               7. Socio-Cultural      PAMELA        DAPHNE  Master  in  Information  3 years
               Development            BUSOG                    Technology
               Services


               8. Sports              MARC        VHERSON  Bachelor  in  Sports  3 years
               Development            MOJICA                   and       Recreational
               Services                                        Management

               9. Research,           JESSIE      ANN      T.  PHD     in   Business  3 years
               Monitoring and         DEMETILLO                Management
               Evaluation of

               Student Services

               10.  National          VIENNA       MI      A.  Units,    Doctor    of  3 years
               Service Training       FERANIL                  Education            in
               Program                                         Educational
                                                               Management

                                                               Licensed  Professional
                                                               Teacher



               3. OUTCOMES

                            ➢  Cite instances or manifestations that students are knowledgeable and satisfied
                                with the operations/services of the Student Services Program.









                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                       The following are examples of situations showing that the students of

                                the  University  are  knowledgeable  with  operations/services  of  the  Student


                                Services Program:

                                 a.  Orientation  programs  are  conducted  regularly  during  the  start  of  the

                                     academic year. This is done to create welcoming environment that could

                                     build  a  sense  of  community  among  new  students,  transferees,  old

                                     students,  faculty  and  staff.  The  overview  of  the  University  Student

                                     Services as well  as  the  students’  rights and privileges,  student  code  of

                                     conduct,  prohibited  acts  and  institutionalized  policies  are  discussed    to


                                     help the students understand and be familiarized with the environment of

                                     the University, the educational opportunities that they can avail of like the

                                     different  scholarship  and  financial  assistance  offered  by  the  University.

                                     Furthermore,  matters  relating  to  student  registration,  housing,  campus

                                     activities  and  other  aspects  of  University  life  are  also  mentioned  in  the


                                     programs.

                                 b.  Student  Handbooks  were  distributed  to  students  so  they  can  read,

                                     understand and engage in all facets of being a student.

                                 c.  The different Student Services Programs of the OSAS as well as other

                                     information related to the University are now accessible to the University

                                     website through www.cvsu.edu.ph.

                                 d.  Students  are  represented  by  the  different  student  leaders  who  were


                                     involved in the revision, evaluation and planning of the student services

                                     program. This was manifested during the recently held workshop on the

                                     revision of the Student Welfare Services where student leaders are part

                                     of  the  committees  involved  in  the  workshop.  This  gave  opportunities  to

                                     the students to be more aware on the procedures done in the formulation




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     of  policies  and  guideline  in  the  University.  This  may  also  increase

                                     students’ sense of engagement or attachment to the University.


                                 e.  As part of the Student Enhancement Activities, students were allowed to

                                     conduct different activities that do not fall into the realm of their normal

                                     curriculum of school. It gave them more opportunities to learn the values

                                     of  teamwork  and  responsibility.    The  OSAS  as  well  as  other  University

                                     officials provided prompt, courteous and efficient services and support to

                                     them since the activities are still part of what is mandated in the student

                                     handbook or in the University Operation Manual and gave benefits for the


                                     welfare of the students.


               4. BEST PRACTICES

                            ➢  Cite  as  many  best  practices  as  you  can  on  Parameter  A  (Student  Services
                                Program).

                                 a.  Student  Services  Program  is  composed  of  Student  Welfare  Services,


                                     Student  Development  Services  and  Institutionalized  Student  Programs

                                     and Services which caters the basic needs of the students by providing

                                     technical  assistance  for  policy  and  programs  that  support  student

                                     admission, equity and success.

                                 b.  Revision of the Student Welfare Services was done in compliance to the

                                     new CMO no. 9, series of 2013 also known as “Enhanced Policies and

                                     Guidelines  on  Student  Affairs  and  Services”  that  would  provide


                                     supplemental services for special population such as foreign students and

                                     persons who are differently abled.

                                 c.  Students  are  involved  in  the  planning  revision  and  evaluation  of  the

                                     student services. They are now part of the newly revised organizational

                                     chart of the Office of Student Affairs and Services.




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 d.  The Office of Student Affairs and Services is composed of well-competent

                                     Dean and qualified staff.


                                 e.  Student  Services  Program  of  the  University  is  readily  available  both  in

                                     print and online access.

                                 f.   The Office of Student Affairs and Services is collaborating to other units

                                     of  the  University  in  providing  food,  health,  shelter,  security  services  as

                                     well  as  establishing  programs  on  sports,  culture,  arts  and  social

                                     community involvement.

                                 g.  Orientation programs are done both university-wide and per program and


                                     are conducted regularly every start of the academic year.

                                 h.  Reading  materials  on  Anti-sexual  harassment,  anti-violence  against

                                     women, anti-bullying act, etc. are readily accessible both print and non-

                                     print  fliers.  Furthermore,  the  University  established  a  Gender  and

                                     Development (GAD) office that is responsible on conducting activities that


                                     would increase awareness on anti-violence against women and children

                                     and anti-sexual harassment act of 1995.

                                 i.   The  University  have  an  allotted  budget  for  the  Student  Affairs  and

                                     Services.

                                 j.   Regular monitoring and evaluation of the different student services and

                                     facilities are conducted.
















                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE





               PARAMETER B – STUDENT WELFARE


               1. SYSTEM-INPUTS AND PROCESSES

                            ➢  Present institutional guidelines on Information & Orientation of Students

                                       The Information and Orientation Services of the Office of the Student

                                Affairs  and  Services  is  designed  to  facilitate  student  adjustment  to  the

                                University  life.  It  aims  to  orient  the  incoming  students  in  the  new  level  of

                                learning: to assist them in coping with the new surrounding adjust to college life

                                and also, to provide students with information in three major areas of concern:


                                educational, occupational, and personal – social.

                                     These services have the following guidelines:

                                 a.  The  Information  and  Orientation  Services  shall  provide  and  prepare

                                     information  materials  on  the  institutional  mission,  vision  and  goals,

                                     academic rules and regulations, student conduct and discipline, student


                                     programs, services and facilities which should be made accessible and

                                     available to all students.

                                 b.  A regular and comprehensive orientation program for new and continuing

                                     students shall be conducted.

                                 c.  An  organized,  updated  and  readily  educational,  career  and

                                     personal/social materials in different accessible formats shall be prepared

                                     and made available to the students.


                                 d.  The  information  materials  on  educational,  career,  personal/social

                                     concerns  shall  be  available  such  as  RA  9262  or  Anti  Violence  Against

                                     Women  and  Children  Act;  Anti  Bullying  Act;  Guidance  on  Drug  Abuse

                                     Prevention  and  Control;  RA7877  or  the  Anti-Sexual  Harassment  Act  of

                                     1995; HIV AIDS awareness; Self-care and healthy lifestyle; and RA 9442,




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     particularly  on  the  provision  on  public  ridicule  and  vilification  against

                                     person with disability. Present the duly approved StudentHandbook. The


                                     approved Student Handbook is based on the CvSU Manual of Operation

                                     2009 that was approved by the Board of Regents (BOR) on September 3,

                                     2009  per Res. No. 85, s. 2009.


                            ➢  Present the duly approved Student Handbook.

                                 (see exhibit for a copy of Student Handbook)


                            ➢  Present the approved Guidance and Counselling Program.

                                            The  Guidance  Program  complements  the  Academic  Program  of

                                     the  University  by  providing  services  to  all  facilitating  program  for  the

                                     students.  It  represents  the  University’s  expression  of  concern  to  assist

                                     students in understanding the diversity, intensity and extent of personal

                                     experiences as well as the opportunities available and the many choices


                                     open  to  them.  Moreover,  students  are  assisted  to  recognized,  interpret

                                     and act upon their personal strengths and resources thereby developing

                                     individuals  who  can  plan  their  work  sensibly  and  solved  their  problems

                                     with grace and high sense of moral values.

                                            The  program  generally  aims  to  assists  in  the  development  of

                                     students who are well informed, self-directed and adjusted.

                                          Specifically, the oriented guidance services are designed to assist


                                   students to:

                                     a.  Evaluate their needs, abilities, achievements, aptitudes, interests, etc.

                                     b.  Make the best adjustments in school

                                     c.  Make decision about their program of studies and work

                                     d.  Think through their problems




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     e.  Appreciate themselves and others.

                                   Program Highlights


                                         The thrust of the program is preventive and developmental rather that

                                     redemptive  and  disciplinary.  It  focuses  on  the  strength  of  individuals,

                                     which can be utilized by them in decision making and problem solving.

                                   Program Components

                                   1.  Basic Guidance Services

                                       1.1 Orientation Services

                                                This  is  designed  to  orient  the  incoming  students  in  the  new


                                          level of learning; to assist them in coping with the new surroundings

                                          and to aid them to adjust in college life.

                                       1.2 Appraisal Services

                                                This service is designed to collect, analyze and use a variety

                                          of objective and subjective tests and non-test data about students to


                                          understand them and assist them to understand themselves.

                                       1.3 Information Services

                                                This service intends to provide students with information in the

                                          three  major  areas  of  concern:  educational,  occupational  and

                                          personal-social.

                                       1.4 Counseling Services

                                                It  is  expected  that  through  this  service,  student’s


                                          selfunderstanding and self-development through dyadic and group

                                          relationship will be facilitated.

                                       1.5 Planning, Placement and Follow-Up










                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                                It  is  designed  to  enhance  the  development  of  students  by

                                          helping them select and utilize opportunities within the school and


                                          labor market.

                                       1.6 Consultation Services

                                                It  is  designed  to  give  technical  assistance  to  teachers,

                                          administrators,  parents  and  alumni  as  regard  to  student

                                          development and how they can be effective in dealing with students.

                                   2.  Special Services

                                       2.1 Career Placement Development


                                              This  consists  of  sessions  and  activities  to  assist  students  to

                                       students to study themselves and the world of work to prepare them for

                                       a career choice. This program will also help students find a job fitted to

                                       them.

                                       2.2 Peer Counselling Program


                                              This is designed to train students to be equipped with knowledge

                                       and  skills  in  helping  their  fellow  students.  The  peer  counsellors  will

                                       assist the professional staff of the College Guidance Office in reaching

                                       to as many college students as possible, thereby checking the lack of

                                       manpower in the Guidance Center.

                                   3.  Physical Resource Development

                                            This  focuses  on  the  improvement  of  the  physical  facilities  of


                                       guidance unit, e.g. guidance/counseling and testing rooms, purchase of

                                       equipment and test materials.

                                   4.  Monitoring/Evaluation

                                            Evaluation is both formative and summative. Formative evaluation

                                     of the program shall be made periodically to determine the progress of




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     the development plan. Likewise, summative evaluation will be conducted

                                     to determine program effectiveness and efficiency.


                                   5.  Research

                                            Research  is  focused  on  student  abilities;  performance,  behavior

                                     and  development  to  determine  how  school  and  guidance  center  in

                                     particular could be of service to the students.

                              IMPLEMENTING GUIDELINES ON BASIC GUIDANCE SERVICES

                              1.  ORIENTATION SERVICES

                                         The initial challenge that confronts the Guidance Services Unit is how


                                     to  inform  students  their  right,  privileges  and  responsibilities  as  soon  as

                                     they become a bona fide student of the Cavite State University. Hence,

                                     orientation  service  is  necessary  for  the  students  to  cope  with  the  new

                                     surroundings  and  how  to  adhere  with  the  set  of  academic  rules  and

                                     regulation as well as the university’s norm of conduct.


                              2. APPRAISAL SERVICES

                                     A.  Individual Inventory Service

                                            All incoming freshmen/transferees are required to fill out individual

                                     inventory Record form a week after the commencement of classes, the

                                     form will become part of the official document of each student.

                                     B.  Testing Services

                                            This process of collecting information about a student includes the


                                     proper  use  of  standard  test  and  inventories.  These  are  tests  of  mental

                                     ability, aptitude and achievement, which could help predict how well an

                                     individual may be expected to profit from future training. While inventories

                                     include  occupational  interests,  study  habits  and  skills,  values,  attitudes

                                     which provide qualitative data needed about the individual.




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                            Through  the  abovementioned  services,  faculty  counselors,

                                     instructors and other school officials may advise/request the students to


                                     visit the Guidance Office as need arises as deemed necessary.

                              3.     INFORMATION SERVICES

                                            This service intends to provide students with information in three

                                     major areas of concern: educational, occupational and personal-social.

                                     1.     Educational Aspect

                                                   The  Guidance/Faculty  Counselor  should  prepare  an

                                            orientation program for all freshmen, transferees, and returnees.


                                            This  will  help  students  gain  insights  regarding  the  policies,

                                            guidelines,  services  provided/offered,  and  all  information  that  as

                                            student should know about the University.

                                                   Guidance/Faculty Counselor should provide orientation for

                                            parents.  Guidance/Faculty  Counselor  is  the  responsible  in


                                            updating  the  Bulletin  of  Information.  The  Bulletin  should  contain

                                            the following information:

                                                   a.      Provision on scholarships

                                                   b.      Newsletters/updates of the University

                                                   c.      Examination Results

                                                   d.      Schedule of activities (seminar, convocation, etc.)

                                                   e.      Training etc.


                                                   f.      Other student-related programs

                                                   All  incoming  freshmen/transferees  are  required  to  attend

                                            the  university-wide  orientation  program  before  the  opening  of

                                            classes.  Parents/guardians  are  also  requested  to  attend  so  that







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                            they are also well-informed of the guidelines that the university is

                                            implementing.


                                     2.     Occupational Aspect

                                                   In  every  guidance  office,  there  should  be  newspapers,

                                            magazines, books that will help students and graduates in finding

                                            job  opportunities  and  gain  information  related  to  job  placement.

                                            There  should  be  bulletin  of  information  specific  for  job  opening

                                            that will updated regularly.

                                                   Guidance/Faculty     Counselor     should    create   and


                                            disseminate  information  through  leaflets,  brochures,  etc.

                                            containing the services that is provided by the guidance office.

                              4.     COUNSELING SERVICES

                                            The counseling service in the academic setting faces contradicting

                                            definitions between and among students and service providers as


                                            well. Majority of teachers and students sees counseling service as

                                            disciplinary  in  nature  when  in  fact  it  is  a  responsive  service  to

                                            issues  that  trends  immediate  or  continuous  action  such  as  the

                                            following:

                                                   a.      School failure

                                                   b.      Family crises

                                                   c.      Peer conflicts/violence


                                                   d.      Interpersonal difficulties

                                                   e.      Depression

                                                   Through the university’s counseling program, the guidance

                                            counselors  and  the  peer  facilitators  assumes  a  critical  role  in

                                            helping  students  these  non-developmental  issues  by  conducting




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                            individual and group counseling. Focus Group Discussion or FGD

                                            will also be helpful to students with common or similar concerns.


                                            Guidelines in accomplishing the Counseling/Anecdotal Records:

                                                   Counseling/Anecdotal Records form shall be accomplished

                                            by the counselor based on the following:

                                            a.     Problems reported/shared by the student

                                            b.     Referral made by school officials

                                            c.     Incident/offence report

                                                   The  accomplished  Counseling/Anecdotal  Records  form


                                            shall  be  filed  in  the  individual  folder  of  student  and  be  treated

                                            confidentially.

                              5.     CONSULTATION SERVICES

                                     Guidelines in Accomplishing the Student Referral Form (SRF)

                                            a.     Secure referral form from the Guidance Unit of OSA and fill


                                                   out the necessary information.

                                            b.     Student  referral  form  shall  be  accomplished  by  the

                                                   teacher/guidance  counselor  before  a  student  could  be

                                                   endorsed at the Guidance Office or vice versa.

                                            c.     Submit  the  referral  form  ahead  of  time  to  agree  on  the

                                                   consultation date and time that is both convenient for the

                                                   counselor and the consulting party.


                                            d.     The  guidance  counselor  takes  down  notes  of  the

                                                   discussion that transpired in the consultation.

                                            e.     Student referral form shall be kept in the office where the

                                                   student  is  endorsed.  It  must  bear  the  action  taken  and

                                                   remarks made by the counselor in-charge.




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                            f.     The accomplished SRF shall be attached to the Individual

                                                   Inventory  Records  of  the  student  filed  at  the  Guidance


                                                   Office.

                                            g.     File the documents (referral form, record of consultation) in

                                                   separate folders.

                                            h.     Conduct follow-up if necessary

                                                   The  teachers,  administrators,  parents  and  alumni  can  be

                                                   requested to visit OSA  and they could also request for a

                                                   visit to the office as the need arises.


                                     Guidelines in Accomplishing the Student Referral Form (SRF)

                                            a.     Student  Referral  Form  shall  be  accomplished  by  the

                                                   teacher/guidance  counselor  before  a  student  could  be

                                                   endorsed to Guidance Office or vice versa.

                                            b.     Student referral form shall be kept in the office where the


                                                   student  is  endorsed.  It  must  bear  the  action  taken  and

                                                   remarks made by the counselor in-charge.

                                            c.     The accomplished SRF shall be attached to the counseling

                                                   records of the student concerned for evaluation and record

                                                   purposes.

                                     PLANNING, PLACEMENT AND FOLLOW-UP SERVICES

                                            The  need  for  career  guidance  and  counseling  programs  is


                                     apparently  increasing  amidst  actual  problem  of  dissatisfaction  among

                                     those  who  are  employed  as  well  as  the  harsh  reality  of  unemployment

                                     amongst  thousands  of  graduates  every  year.  For  these  reasons,

                                     planning,  placements  and  follow-up  services  are  designed  to  serve  as

                                     catalyst to assist individual acquire the knowledge, skills and experience




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     necessary  to  identify  the  options,  explore  alternatives  and  eventually

                                     succeed in society.


                                     PLANNING

                                            In  counseling  clients  for  their  career  development  and  eventual

                                     placement, counselors may employ a variety of facilitative techniques to

                                     assist  person  in  self-awareness,  education  career  awareness,  career

                                     exploration, planning and decision-making such as follows:

                                     a.  Conduct of career orientation.

                                     b.  Administer standardized test to find out the client’s aptitude, interest,


                                         values  and  personality  traits  that  will  reveal  strength  as  well  as

                                         weaknesses of an individual that are important in the development of

                                         concepts related to self that are helpful in career exploration.

                                     c.  Individual  or  group  counseling  should  follow  if  circumstances

                                         necessitate such action.


                                     d.  Orient students/clients about the different career options available at

                                         present and see if they are consistent with their interests in life thus

                                         giving them the fulfillment they want to achieve.

                                     e.  Orient  clients  about  the  relationship  between  self-educational

                                         opportunities,  and  the  world  of  work  through  the  use  of  films  and

                                         printed materials.

                              PLACEMENT AND FOLLOW-UP


                                 a.  Conduct  pre-employment  counseling  or  seminar  to  assist  students,

                                     school  drop-outs  and  graduates  in  obtaining  a  more  realistic

                                     understanding of the world of work.










                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 b.  Established  linkage  with  local,  national  and  even  international

                                     employment  personnel  to  provide  the  best  possible  assistance  for  job


                                     seekers.

                                 c.  Conduct job fair.

                                 d.  Expand  information  service  through  distribution  of  flyers  that  contains

                                     helpful  tips  and  guideline  in  applying  for  work,  staying  focused  and

                                     surviving the work place.

                                 e.  Regular follow-up on graduates through annual tracer study.

                                     Conduct research on shiftees and drop-outs.

                            ➢  Present legal documents such as RA 9262 (Anti Violence Against Women &
                                Children); Anti-Bullying Act; Guidelines on Drug Abuse Prevention and Control;
                                RA  7877  (Anti  Sexual  Harassment  Act);  RA  9442  (Provisions  on  Public
                                Ridicule and Vilification against persons with disability).

                                     ✓  Republic Act No. 9262 – An Act Defining Violence Against Women &

                                         Their  Children,  Providing  For  Protective  Measures  For  Victims,

                                         Prescribing Penalties Therefore, and For Other Purposes

                                     ✓  Republic  Act  No.  9165  –  An  Act  Instituting  The  Comprehensive

                                         Dangerous Drugs Act of 2002, Repealing The Republic Act 0.6425,

                                         Otherwise  Known  as  the  Dangerous  Act  of  1972,  As  Amended,


                                         Providing Funds Therefore, And For Other Purposes.

                                     ✓  Republic  Act  No.  7877  –  An  Act  Declaring  Sexual  Harassment

                                         Unlawful  In  The  Employment,  Education  Or  Training  Environment,

                                         And For Other Purposes.

                                     ✓  Republic Act No. 7277 – An Act Providing The Rehabilitation, Self-

                                         Development  and  Self-Reliance  of  Disabled  Person  and  Their


                                         Integration Into The Mainstream Of Society And For Other Purposes.








                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     ✓  Republic  Act  No.  9442  –  ProvisionsOn  Public  Ridicule  and

                                         Vilification Against Person With Disability (An Act Amending Republic

                                         Act No. 0.07277, Otherwise Known As the “Magna Carta For Disabled


                                         Persons, And For Other Purposes).


               2. IMPLEMENTATION

                            ➢  Describe the Institution’s Information & Orientation Services

                                       The  Institution’s  Information  and  Orientation  Services  is  under  the

                                Student  Welfare  of  Services  of  the  Office  of  Student  Affairs  and  Services

                                (OSAS).  It  facilitates  the  transition  of  new  students  (freshmen,  transferees,

                                shiftees,  returnees)  into  the  institution  by  preparing  them  for  educational

                                opportunities  and  student  responsibilities.  A  comprehensive  orientation


                                program is regularly conducted both university-wide and per college or unit to

                                familiarize with the new surrounding and to aid them to adjust in college life.

                                The  following  are  the  topics  discussed  during  the  University-wide  orientation

                                program:

                                          a.  Overview of Student Services

                                          b.  Academic Policies

                                          c.  Library Policies


                                          d.  Scholarship and Financial Assistance

                                          e.  Student Membership and Organization Membership

                                          f.  University Policies on Student Norm of Conduct

                                            Meanwhile, College orientation usually discussed the University’s

                                     and  College’s  Vision,  Mission,  Objectives  and  College  Policies  and


                                     Regulations,  and  Guidance  Counseling.  Presentation  of  student








                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     organizations  and  their  accomplishment  is  also  done  during  the

                                     orientation program.


                                            Information  materials  in  the  form of  print  (brochures,  pamphlets,

                                     fliers)  and  non-print  (power  point  presentation  and  audio-visual

                                     presentation) are also made available during the program. Furthermore,

                                     information  materials  on  educational,  career,  personal  and  social

                                     concerns  shall  be  available  such  as:  RA  9262  or  anti-violence  against

                                     Women  and  Children  Act;  Anti-Bullying  Act;  Guidelines  on  Drug  Abuse

                                     Prevention and Control; RA 7877 or the Anti-Sexual Harassment Act of


                                     1995,  HIV  AIDS  Awareness;  Self-care  and  Healthy  Lifestyles;  and  RA

                                     9442,  particularly  on  the  provision  on  public  ridicule  and  vilification

                                     against persons with disability are also available in the different units of

                                     the  university  such  as  the  OSAS,  office  of  the  different  student

                                     organizations, colleges and in Gender and Development (GAD) Office.



                            ➢  Describe the Guidance Program and its Services;


                                       The  Guidance  Services  Unit  represents  the  expression  of  concern  to

                                students. It exists to assist students in understanding the variety, depth, and

                                breadth  of  personal  experiences,  the  opportunities  available,  and  the  many

                                choices open to them. Moreover, students are assisted to recognize, interpret

                                and  act  upon  their  personal  strengths  and  resources  thereby  developing


                                individuals  who  can  plan  their  work  sensibly  and  solve  their  problems  with

                                moral values.

                                       The program generally aims to assist in the development of individuals

                                who are well informed, self-directed and adjusted.







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                  Guidelines Services           Projects/Activities             System of          Status of
                                                   Implemented               Monitoring and        Implement
                                                                               Evaluation            ation


                   I.  Basic     Guidance
                   Services
                   a.  Orientation Service
                                                •  Annual     University
                                                   Orientation Program

                                                •  Upgrades          the
                   b.  Information Service
                       (Educational,               Bulletin           of
                                                   Information            Formative – determine  On-going
                       Occupational,            •  Coordinates with the  the  progress  of  the
                       Personal-Social             Placement        Unit  development       plan
                                                   regarding  the  Pre-   (Accomplishment
                                                   Employment             Reports)
                                                   Seminar
                                                                          Summative            –
                                                                          determine the program
                                                                          effectiveness      and

                                                                          efficiency
                   c.  Counseling Service       •  Provides     reading
                                                   material          on
                                                   Personality            Conduct  research  on
                                                   Development,
                                                   Relationship,  Health   student      abilities,
                                                   and Leisure            performance,
                                                •  Use of Student         behavior,          and
                   d.  Consultation                Referral Form (SRF)  development
                       Service                  •  Use the Referral
                                                   Form for scheduling
                                                   of counseling
                                                •  Compilation of
                                                   consultation files for
                   e.  Appraisal Services          safekeeping
                                                •  Use of individual
                                                   Inventory Record
                                                   Need Assessment
                                                   Checklist and other    Formative/Summative
                                                   required forms

                   II.    Special
                          Services

                   a.  Peer    Counseling       •  Assist the college
                       Program                     faculty Guidance
                                                   Coordinator in
                                                   reaching out the                               On-going
                                                   college students




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                   III.   Human                 •  Attend     seminars,  Formative/Summative      On-going
                          Resources                convention       and
                          Development              workshop
                          Program               •  Provide  in  service
                                                   training         and
                                                   graduation training
                   I.     Physical              •  Improve the physical  Formative/Summative      On-going
                          Resource                 facilities of Guidance
                          Development              Unit
                                                •  Purchase equipment
                                                   and test materials


                                     A counselling room is provided to all students including those with special

                              needs  to  ensure  the  privacy  and  confidentiality  of  the  different  counselling


                              sessions. The counseling session is done either individual or group to facilitate

                              positive change in student behavior, feelings and attitude. Gender sensitivity and

                              cultural differences are also considered during counselling.

                                     Updated  student’s  cumulative  records  containing  their  relevant

                              information are kept and stored in the Guidance Office.

                                     A  well  planned  assessment  program  for  students  with  appropriate


                              standardized psychological tests is implemented, where the results of which are

                              interpreted to students, teachers and concerned individuals. The test results are

                              utilized in designing activities to meet student needs.


                            ➢  Describe the Career and Job Placement Services;

                                       Career and Job Placement Services is one of the major services

                                provided by the Office of Student Affairs. Its main function is to help the student

                                to choose appropriate major/field of specialization and to mentor and open

                                opportunities for students to achieve success in their chosen career. The

                                proper decision-making as to what course to take in college, and what career to


                                pursue after graduation.






                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                       The Career and Job Placement Services provides the following:

                                       a.  Career  Education  or  Pre-Employment  Seminars  –  It  helps  the


                                          graduating  students  to  be  prepared  and  knowledgeable  for  their

                                          entry in the world of employment. Topics discussed relate to areas

                                          as  Personality  Development  and  Tips  for  Interview,  Resume

                                          Preparation,  Job  Hunting  Strategies  and  Survival  Strategies  and

                                          Local and International Employment Status.

                                       b.  Annual Job Fair – Companies representing various industries and

                                          schools  are  invited  as  part  of  the  school’s  on-campus  recruitment


                                          program. Information materials on career and job opportunities are

                                          also  accessible  to  the  graduates.  It  also  serves  as  an  avenue  in

                                          identifying the competencies of graduates required by the industries.

                                          The  identified  required  competencies  of  graduated  also  provide  a

                                          basis for possible curricular development.


                                       c.  Tracer Studies – Conducted to follow-up the employment status of

                                          graduates thru survey, text messaging and e-mail. The results of the
                                          tracers’  study  may  be  utilized  by  the  University  to  determine  the


                                          effectiveness  of  its  curricular  offering  in  meeting  the  global  labor

                                          market demands.

                                       d.  Creation  of  Directory  of  Graduates  –  Regular  updating  of  the

                                          directory of graduates is an important activity necessary in following-


                                          up the status of the graduates. Again, this is done in coordination to

                                          the designated College Job Placement Coordinators


                            ➢  Describe the Economic Enterprise development; and








                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                       The Economic  Enterprise  is  now  included  in  the  proposed  revision  of

                                the  Student  Welfare  of  the  OSAS.  It  states  that  the  institution  encourages


                                student economic ventures such as but not limited to:

                                a.  Student laboratory cooperatives

                                b.  Entrepreneurial activities/projects

                                c.  Savings

                                     The guidelines of this services are as follows:

                                     a.  There  shall  be  an  Economic  Enterprise  Development  Center  (EED)

                                         which would be benefit all the students according to their needs. This


                                         EED Center is open to all of enterprising within the University.

                                     b.  EED  Center  shall  be  supervised  by  the  OSAS-SWS  in  coordination

                                         with  EBA  Office  where  applicable  (in  compliance  with  the  existing

                                         rules of implementation of enterprising within the University).

                                     c.  Products to be offered and/or marketed may be an innovation which


                                         would  be  of  essential  help  to  the  students  in  their  academic

                                         endeavors.  Students  may  also  offer  services  (example:  tutorials)

                                         depending on the expertise of the course they are enrolled in or the

                                         objective/nature of their organization.

                                     d.  Each student organization shall abide with the rules and regulations *

                                         of OSAS in the implementation and operation of EED Center (*to be

                                         proposed)


                                       Although  the  guidelines  on  the  establishment  of  the  Economic

                                Enterprise  Development  Center  is  yet  to  be  approved  by  the  BOR,  student

                                organizations are already encouraged to be engaged in the different income-

                                generating activities  that can  be  done during  the  College/University  Day  and

                                Intramurals or even at regular school days as long as it would not affect their




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                studies. Each Student Organization shall abide with the rules and regulations of

                                OSAS  in  the  implementation  of  the  different  student  activities.  Meanwhile,


                                students  offering  services  such  as  tutorials  is  usually  done  as  part  of  their

                                community services as extension activities.


                            ➢  Describe the student Handbook Development.

                                       The  Central  Student  Government,  assisted  by  designated  faculty


                                members  and  OSAS  staff,  shall  be  responsible  in  the  preparation,  revision,

                                updating  and  distribution  of  student  handbook  which  student  and  university

                                stakeholders.

                                       Formats  for  the  dissemination,  information  anti  guidance  of

                                Representative  from  the  different  Student  Councils  of  the  University  are


                                included in the development and revision of student handbook.


               3. OUTCOMES


                            ➢  Present evidences that qualify student welfare services are made available for
                                all students.

                                       The  following  are  evidences  that  quality  student  welfare  services  are

                                made available for all students:

                                     a.  Student handbooks are available in print and are distributed to every

                                         student of the University.

                                     b.  Comprehensive  Orientation  Program  is  conducted  annually.  Both


                                         university-wide  and  college-based  orientations  are  conducted  to

                                         inform student their rights, privileges and responsibilities as soon as

                                         they become a bona fide student of the Cavite State University.

                                     c.  Reading materials on RA 9262, Anti-Bullying Act, Guidelines on Drug

                                         Abuse Prevention and Control, RA 7877, HIV AIDS Awareness, Self-




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                         Care and Healthy Lifestyles and RA 9224 are available in print and

                                         are  posted  in  bulletin  boards  and  student  organization  offices  for


                                         information dissemination.

                                     d.  There is an existing Guidance and Counseling program that provide

                                         services  such  as  appraisal  service,  information  service,  counseling

                                         service, planning, placement and follow-up and consultation services.

                                     e.  Pre-employment  seminar  and  Job  Fairs  are  regularly  conducted  to

                                         help  the  graduating  students  to  be  more  ready  in  the  employment

                                         world.


                                     f.  College Placement Coordinator is designated to facilitate tracer study

                                         and  monitoring  of  the  performances  of  the  graduates  in  their

                                         respective works.

                                     g.  Information  materials  on  career  and  job  opportunities  are  made

                                         accessible to the graduates by posting it in the bulletin boards and in


                                         the University-website.

                                     h.  Students  are  involved  in  the  development  and  revision  of  student

                                         handbook.

                                     Revision of the Student Welfare Services was done to further improve the

                              services offered to the students.

               4. BEST PRACTICES

                            ➢  Cite as many best practices as you can on Parameter B (Student Welfare).

                              a.     Student handbooks are distributed to students of the University.

                              b.     University-wide  and  College  orientation  programs  are  regularly

                                     conducted.










                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                              c.     Reading  materials  on  RA  9262,  Anti  Bullying  Act,  Guidelines  on  Drug

                                     Abuse Prevention and Control, RA 7877, HIV AIDS Awareness, Self-care


                                     and Healthy

                              d.     Lifestyles and RA 9224 are available in print and are posted to the bulletin

                                     boards  and  student  organization  offices  for  information  dissemination.

                                     Gender and Development (GAD) Office is established and is responsible

                                     for information dissemination about RA 9262 and RA 7877.

                              e.     Counseling  room  is  provided  to  ensure confidentiality  of  the counseling

                                     sessions.


                              f.     Gender  sensitivity  and  cultural  differences  are  now  considered  during

                                     counseling.

                              g.     The  Guidance  Program  is  headed  by  a  licensed  Guidance  Counselor.

                                     There is also a designated Guidance Counselor to every college.

                              h.     Pre-employment seminars and Job Fairs are conducted regularly.


                              i.     Student leaders are involved in the development and revision of student

                                     hand  book  manifested  in  the  attendees  of  the  recently  held  seminar-

                                     workshop  on  Review  and  Revision  on  Rule  VII  of  the  CvSu  Manual  of

                                     Operation




















                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE





               PARAMETER C – STUDENT DEVELOPMENT


               1. SYSTEM-INPUTS AND PROCESSES

                            ➢  Present  institutional  policies  and  guidelines  on  recognition,  accreditation,
                                monitoring and evaluation of student organizations/projects and activities.

                            Student Organization
                                   Student organization shall refer to association club, or any other organized


                            group  of  cultural  and/or  civic  organization  whose  members  are  students  of  the

                            University.  Those  of  provincial,  sectional,  or  regional  in  character  or  orientation

                            (e.g. Ilocano, Bicolano, Batangueno) are discouraged. Greek letter organizations

                            such as fraternities and sororities are not allowed.

                                   A  University-wide  student  organization  shall  be  one  whose  members


                            belong  to  two  or  more  units.  A  unit  organization  shall  be  one  whose  members

                            belong exclusively to only one unit of the University and a class organization shall

                            be  composed  of  members  of  any  class  of  the  University.  All  University

                            organizations  shall  be  directly  under  the  supervision  of  the  Socio-Cultural

                            Organizations Unit of the Office of Student Affairs.

                                   Every  student  organization  shall  have  one  or  more  faculty  adviser/s

                            recommended by such organizations and approved by the Dean of Student Affairs.


                            No student organization may hold any meeting or undertake any activity for any

                            activity for any purpose whatsoever, except that of adopting a constitution, before

                            its adviser or advisers are appointed and have assumed office as such.

                                   No student organization shall be allowed to operate without a constitution

                            and by-laws approved by the Dean of Student Affairs.


                                   No  student  organization  that  advocated  physical  contact  as  a  form  of

                            initiation  or  trial  for  membership  shall  be  recognized  by  the  University  and  is,





                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                            therefore,  not  allowed  to  operate  on  campus  or  any  other  campuses  of  the

                            University.


                            Classification of Student Organization

                              a)  College/High School Organizations

                              ❖  Central  Student  Government  and  Student  Body  Organization  shall  be

                                 composed  of  students  enrolled  in  the  collegiate  and  high  school  levels,

                                 respectively

                              ❖  Unit Organization shall be one whose members belong exclusive to one unit

                                 of the College and High School.


                              b)  Class Organization shall be composed of any class or section in the college

                                 and high school. Non-Class Organizations shall be made up on students who

                                 may  want  to  join  SUCH  organizations  without  compulsion  provided  said

                                 students are not included in the delinquency organizations are social, cultural,

                                 arts and others of special concerns in nature.


                          Formation of Student Organizations

                              a)  Only  bona  fide  students  of  CvSU  may  organize.  Any  direct  or  indirect

                                 involvement of an individual not connected with the University in organizing or

                                 running the student organization is  absolutely prohibited. However, DepEd-

                                 endorsed organization like YCSC and BSP are exempted.

                              b)  A  letter  of  request  to  organize  must  be  submitted  to  the  Dean  of  Student

                                 Affairs , with the following requirements:


                                 •  Objectives of the organization;

                                 •  List of prospective members with their signatures, course and year, home

                                     and campus address and name of parents/guardian;

                                 •  Name of at least two (2) prospective advisers who are regularly faculty

                                     members of CvSU with their signatures and letters of acceptance; and




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 •  Program/Calendar of activities

                          Recognition


                              a)  For  Newly  Formed  Organizations.  A  newly  formed  organization  shall  be

                                 recognized on probation basis for at least (1) semester.

                              A duly accomplished application for recognition must be submitted along with the

                          following requirements:

                              •  Proposed organization’s Constitution and By-Laws signed by its officers;


                              •  List of members and their signatures;

                              •  List of officers with their signatures, complete home and campus address,

                                 year and section and the college where they belong;

                              •  Bio-data and two (2) passport size picture (2x2) of the head of the

                                 organization;


                              •  Work Plan/Calendar of Activities for the school year with their corresponding

                                 dates. This should include:

                                         o  Proposed date of activity

                                         o  Title of activity

                                         o  Objectives of the activity


                                         o  Type of activity

                                         o  Strategies

                                         o  Target clientele

                                         o  Resource/Budgetary Requirement

                                         o  Expected Output

                              b)  For Existing Organization. Existing organizations and those which were on

                                 probation in the previous semester/year that wish to continue must submit the


                                 following:






                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                              •  Constitution and By-laws

                              •  Updated list of members and their signatures


                              •  Bio-data and (2) passport size photos of the head of the organization;

                              •  Work plan/calendar of activities for the year;

                              •  Letter of acceptance by at least two regular faculty and staff members of

                                 CvSU with their signatures’


                              •  Must take responsibility for any violations committed by the organization;

                              •  Are expected to refer to the Head of SOSCA and Dean of Student Affairs or

                                 any problem; and

                              •  Shall perform other tasks as may be required by the Dan of Student Affairs


                                 and President of the University.

                              c)  Duties/Functions

                              •  Assist/supervise organizational unit in the programming of calendar of

                                 activities;

                              •  Coordinate    and    monitor   activities   of   the   organization   in   the


                                 execution/implementation;

                              •  Monitor/evaluate program of activities;

                              •  Conduct/act as chaperon in seminars, symposia, convocation, contest, field

                                 trips and the like;

                              •  Act as guide in the policy revisions of the Constitutions and By-Laws;


                              •  Act as the member of the board of canvassers during election;

                              •  Coordinate  with  the  Board  of  Student  Discipline  in  cases  of  student

                                 misconduct in consonance with the student norm of conduct;

                              •  Review and/or edit reports of the organizations;









                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                              •  Submit  to  the  SOSCA,  semestral  and  annual  accomplishments  of  the

                                 organization;


                              •  Encourage moral support to students to participate in campus activities;

                              •  Coordinate with SOSCA from time to time.

                          Conduct of Activities

                              a)  Activities of all student organization shall require prior approval from the Dean

                                 of  the  Student  Affairs.  However,  activities  to  be  conducted  outside  the


                                 University and those that will last beyond 5pm in the afternoon would need

                                 the approval of the Office of the Vice Presidents (OVPAA) and OP. Approval

                                 of  said  activities  shall  be  based  on  the  submitted  list  and  schedule  of

                                 activities of organizations. Only in very exceptional cases where an activity is

                                 not listed that an activity could be approved.

                              b)  Except for the Central Student Government-sponsored convocations, social

                                 activities that would tend to disrupt the normal schedule of classes shall no


                                 longer  be  allowed.  University  sponsored  programs  are  exempted  from  this

                                 provision.  Any  activity  shall  be  approve  at  least  a  week  before  its

                                 implementation.

                              c)  Off-campus activities shall be discouraged with the exception provided in the

                                 University Code (Section II f).


                              d)  Fund raising activities such as raffle, bingo socials and other games which

                                 will incur contribution or solicitation shall no longer be allowed. Sale of tickets

                                 and promotions from students, faculty members and staff shall be minimized.

                              e)  Activities including education field trips that would require contribution from

                                 members shall be allowed. The OSA shall set the limit for such contribution.

                                 Exceptions  to  this  are  HRM  and  other  skilled-oriented  courses.  However,

                                 departments concerned shall be required to submit to OVPAA the schedule




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 of  student  activities  and  the  corresponding  estimates  of  expenditures.

                                 Provided however, that the proposed education field trip has been specified


                                 in  the  course  analysis  of  the  teacher  concerned.  Education  field  trips  of

                                 students in the HRM and other skills-oriented courses shall require approval

                                 from  OVPAA  and  OP  and  at  the  same  time,  parents  permit  form  shall  be

                                 used.  In  the  case  of  the  branch  campuses,  their  respective  deans  shall

                                 approve the HRM activities.

                                         Any student activity shall be held with an approved activity proposal

                                 and activity permit.


                                         These include the following:

                                         •  Fund raising

                                         •  Socials

                                         •  Services


                                         •  Field trips

                                         •  Initiation/Induction Rites

                                         •  Recruitment, recognition and orientation of new members

                                         •  Convocation, seminar, workshop and symposium


                              f)  No student activity shall be allowed:

                                 •  During class hours (7am-12noon; 1pm-5pm)

                                 •  A week before the midterm and final examinations

                              Information Bulletins and Announcements

                                     All campus bulletins and announcement must be:


                                 a)  Written in Filipino/English with no indecent vulgar word(s).












                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 b)  Noted  by  the  SOSCA  Head  before  posting,  otherwise  they  shall  be

                                     removed  by  authorized  person  without  prior  notice  to  the  organization


                                     concerned.

                                 c)  Posted on campus bulletin board.

                                 d)  Removed right after the activity to allow other groups to post their bills.

                              Recognition and Suspension of Organization Activities

                                     a)  Grounds for non-recognition or suspension:

                                         •  Non-compliance of requirements;


                                         •  Lack of worthwhile projects based on point system;

                                         •  Failure so submit required reports (Financial/Accomplishments);

                                         •  Violations of any policies of organization or other college rules and

                                            regulations;


                                         •  Preventive suspension may be imposed pending decision of the

                                            investigating body.

                                     b)  In case of any violation of any policies on organization of other college

                                         rules, the following procedures shall be effected:

                                         •  Upon receipt of the violation report, the Dean of OSA shall call the


                                            officers and other concerned members of the said organization for

                                            a fact finding meeting.

                                         •  If  the  case  warrants  punishments  beyond  admonition  or

                                            reprimand,  the  Dean  of  OSA  shall  forward  his  finding  to  the

                                            Preliminary Investigating Committee.


                              Privileges
                                     a)  Only fully recognized organization may:










                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     1.  Use  the  facilities  of  the  University  such  as  classrooms,  grounds,

                                         lights, etc. with approval from proper authority;


                                                Charges.  Certain  charges  are  imposed  on  the  use  of  some

                                         college facilities and equipment.

                                                Proper Responsibility. The officers of the student organization

                                         concerned shall be jointly and severally responsible for any damage

                                         to property.

                                     2.  Participate in inter-organizational activities/competitions;

                                     3.  Compete for awards;


                                     4.  Officially  bear  the  name  of  the  University  when  in  engaging  in  off-

                                         campus activities;

                                     5.  Have their organizational activities publicized in any credited student

                                         publication.

                                     b)  Organizations on Probation


                                         Organization on probation are two categories:

                                         •  Newly formed organizations applying for full pledge status.

                                         •  Those  on  probation  because  of  violations  of  the  guidelines  on

                                            student organizations and activities.

                                         Organizations  on  probation  can  only  avail  of  certain  privileges  as


                                     specified below:

                                         •  Shall avail for privileges 1 and 2

                                         •  Shall avail only privileges 1, 2 and 5

                                     c)  Incentives/Awards

                                         1.  Five  (5)  best  organization  shall  be  selected  at  the  end  of  the


                                            school  year.  The  Accreditation  criteria  shall  be  used  in  the

                                            selection. Trophies shall be awarded to the winners.



                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                         2.  An  outstanding  student  leader  shall  likewise  be  chosen.  A

                                            committee  for  this  purpose shall  be  formed  by  the  OSA  to  draft


                                            selection criteria and select the recipient. The winner shall receive

                                            a plaque of recognition.

                                     Prohibited Activities

                                            Any  student  activity  that  is  subversive  in  nature  and  one  which

                                     incited  insurgency  including  those  against  the  existing  University  rules

                                     and regulations is strictly prohibited and disallowed. Hazing and inflicting

                                     any form of physical injury are strictly prohibited.


                                            The violator/s  as  well  as  the  officers  of  the  student  organization

                                     including  the  faculty  coordinator  if  warranted  by  the  circumstances  of

                                     each case shall be held administratively liable for the illegal activity of the

                                     organization without prejudices to criminal prosecution.

                                     Penalty for Violation


                                            In  addition  to  the  revocation  of  the  authority  to  operate,  the

                                     student  organization  may  be  reprimanded,  suspended  or  dropped  from

                                     the  roll  of  the  school  or  expelled  from  the  University  depending  on  the

                                     seriousness of the offense committed.

                            ➢  Present institutional guidelines on Student Grievance.

                                       As guidance services represents the University’s expression of concern

                                for  the  students,    it  is  likewise  expected  that  personal  experiences  of  each


                                student shall be treated as the stage that they need to pass through  even if

                                sometimes those experiences signify negative quality. This is the stage where

                                Student  Formation  program  will  play  a  very  important  role.  As  students  are

                                helped to face the consequences of their actions, they will also undergo series







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                of activities that will them to re-gain self-confidence and self-trust as their self-

                                esteem.


                                     Within the Student Formation section is the Student discipline unit, with

                              the following functions:

                                 •  Conduct preliminary investigation on cases involving student discipline;

                                 •  Conduct hearing of student cases;

                                 •  File  formal  charges  upon  respondents  in  cases  where  complaints  or


                                     report is found supported evidences; and

                                 •  Submit  to  higher  authorities  the  complete  report  of  the  student  cases

                                     containing findings on fact conclusion and recommendation.

                              Disciplining Authorities

                              a)  Committee  on  Student  Misdemeanor.  The  Committee  on  Student


                                 Misdemeanor  shall  be  composed  of  the  Dean  of  Student  Affairs  as

                                 Chairperson,  and  two  (2)  other  members  of  the  Faculty  designated  by  the

                                 President for the term of one (1) School Year, as Member.

                              b)  Board  of  Student  Discipline.The  Board  of  Student  Discipline  shall  be

                                 composed of the Vice President for Administrative and Support Services as

                                 Chair, the Dean of College where the offender is enrolled as a Member, and

                                 one (1) member of the Faculty designated by the President for a term of one


                                 (1) School Year, as Member.

                              c)  Upon request, at any stage of the proceedings, the Committee on Student

                                 Misdemeanor or the Board of Student Discipline, may allow the heads of not

                                 more  than  two  (2)  student  organizations  accredited  by  the  University  to  sit

                                 during  its  deliberations  as  observers  and  with  the  right  to  vote  for  the


                                 Committee  on  Student  Misdemeanor  and  without  the  right  to  vote  on  the

                                 Board of Student Discipline.



                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                              d)  Meetings of either of the Disciplining Authorities shall be convened at the call

                                 of the Chairperson or any two (2) Members thereof.


                              e)  The  presences  of  at  least  two  (2)  Members  shall  continue  a  quorum  of  at

                                 either of the Disciplining Authorities. The vote of at least two (2) Member shall

                                 be required for a decision of either of the Disciplining Authorities.

                              f)  All deliberations of the Disciplining Authorities shall be recorded in writing.

                              g)  The office of Student Affairs shall serve as the Secretariat of the Disciplining

                                 Authorities and shall be the custodian of all records.

                              Jurisdiction


                              a)  The  Committee  on  Student  Misdemeanor  shall  have  original  and exclusive

                                 jurisdiction over all offenses where the penalty prescribed under this Code is

                                 EXCLUSION for not more than one (1) semester.

                              b)  The Board of Student Discipline shall have original and exclusive jurisdiction

                                 over all offenses where the penalty prescribed under this Code is EXCLISION


                                 for not less than one (1) semester, and appellate jurisdiction over all appeals

                                 taken from decision of the Committee on Student Misdemeanor, where the

                                 penalty imposed is EXLUSION for more than two (2) months.

                              Procedure

                              a)  Complaints

                                 1.  Complaints against pupils/students for any violation/s of this code shall be

                                     filed by any person in Authority and/or any party who is alleged victim of


                                     the offense/s charged with the office Student Affairs.

                                 2.  The  complaint  must  be  in  writing  and  shall  state  the  name/s  of  the

                                     student/s charged, the offence/s committed citing the pertinent provisions

                                     of  this  Code,  the  date,  time  and  place  where  the  offence/s  was







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     committed, the name/s of witnesses, and other proof that the offence was

                                     committed.


                                 3.  The office of Student Affairs shall stamp the Complaint with the date and

                                     time  it  was  filed  and  shall  assign  number  the  order  that  complaint  are

                                     received as “ADMINISTRATIVE CASE NO. _____” followed by the last

                                     two (2) digits of the current year).

                                 4.  An  immediate  determination  shall  be  made  as  to  whether  the  offense

                                     charged  and  the  penalty  prescribed  fall  within  the  jurisdiction  of  the

                                     Committee on Student Misdemeanor or the Board of Student Discipline.


                                 5.  The  office  of  Student  Affairs  shall  then  endorse  the  complaint  to  the

                                     proper Disciplining Authority.

                              b)  Answer:

                                         The Disciplining Authority shall furnish each student charged with the

                                 copy of the compliant together with a notice to file an Answer within seventy


                                 two (72) hours from receipt thereof.

                              c)  Preliminary Inquiry:

                                 1.  Upon the receipt of the answer or expiration of the period given for filing

                                     the  same,  the  Disciplining  Authority  concerned  shall  convene  for  the

                                     purpose of making a Preliminary Inquiry to determine if on the basis of the

                                     Compliant and answer filed, if any, there is sufficient basis to warrant a

                                     hearing.  For  this  purpose,  the  Disciplining  Authority  may  invite  the


                                     complaint and/or the student/s charged, to provide more information, or

                                     further proof, to assist in its determination.

                                 2.  The Disciplining Authority may likewise call the parties for the purpose of

                                     exploring  the  possibility  of  an  “Amicable  Settlement”,  or  executing  an

                                     “Agreed  Stipulation  of  Facts  and  Simplification  of  the  Issues”.  An




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     “Amicable Settlement” agreed by the parties shall be reduced to writing,

                                     shall state the terms and conditions thereof, the period/s for


                                 3.  Compliance therewith, and shall be signed by the parties and attested by

                                     the Chair of the Disciplining Authority.

                                 4.  An  “Agreed  Statement  of  Facts  and  Simplification  of  the  Issues”  shall

                                     likewise be reduced to writing , shall state the facts and simplified issues

                                     agreed to by the parties, and shall likewise be signed by the parties and

                                     attested by the Chair of the Disciplining Authority.

                                 5.  No further proof shall be required and no other issues shall be considered


                                     in  the  hearing  of  the  case,  other  than  those  agreed  upon  in  the

                                     “Agreement Statement of Facts and the Simplification of Issues”.

                              d)  Notice of Hearing:

                                 1.  A written “Notice of Hearing” shall be served on all the parties, stating the

                                     date, time and place where the initial hearing of the case will be held.


                                 2.  The date set for the initial hearing shall not be less than five (5) days, nor
                                     more than ten (10) days from receipt of the “Notice of the Hearing” by the


                                     parties.

                                 3.  Continuance  or  subsequent  hearing  shall  be  set  by  the  Disciplining

                                     Authority  upon  the  termination  of  each  hearing,  which  shall  be

                                     acknowledged  by  the  signature  of  the  parties  and/or  their  respective

                                     counsel or representatives.

                                 4.  A “Notice of Hearing”, and other pleadings served on a counsel or other


                                     representative or record in the case shall be sufficient notice to the parties

                                     concerned.

                              Hearing







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 a)  The initial hearing shall commence the date, time and place stated in the

                                     “Notice  of  Hearing”.  Only  one  “Motion  for  Postponement”  shall  be


                                     entertained in any hearing if it is for good and sufficient cause.

                                 b)  Failure of any party to attend two (2)  consecutive hearing where notice

                                     was properly received shall be constructed as a waiver of the right of said

                                     party  to  attend  said  hearing  and  shall  not  prevent  the  Disciplining

                                     Authority from continuing with the hearing of the case.

                                 c)  Conduct of Hearing:

                                     1.  At  the  start  of  the  hearing,  the  entire  complaint  will  be  read  to  the


                                         student/s charged. Each one of them will be asked if they wish to be

                                         represented by counsel or representative, who need not be a lawyer

                                         or  a  member  of  the  Philippine  Bar,  or  they  may  elect  to  personally

                                         undertake  their  defense  by  themselves.  The  choice  made  by  the

                                         student/s  charged  shall  be  recorded,  together  with  the  name/s  and


                                         address/es of counsel or representative named.

                                     2.  Where  the  student/s  charged  do  not  admit  the  allegations  in  the

                                         complaint, the Disciplining Authority shall set the case for hearing for

                                         three (3) consecutive school days which shall not be earlier than five

                                         (5)  days  from  the  date  of  the  initial  hearing  nor  more  than  ten  (10)

                                         days thereafter.

                                     3.  The Disciplining Authority shall be endeavor to complete the hearing


                                         within a period of three (3) consecutive school days.

                              Order of Hearing

                                     a)  The complainant shall first present documentary evidence and/or the

                                         testimony  of  witnesses  to  establish  the allegations  in  the complaint.







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                         After said party has completed the presentation of the evidence, the

                                         case of the complainant shall be deemed submitted for resolution.


                                     b)  The student/s charged shall then proceed to submit documents and/or

                                         witnesses  in  their  defense.  After  said  party  has  completed  the

                                         presentation of evidence, the case for the defense shall be deemed

                                         submitted for resolution.

                                     c)  Where  an  “Agreed  Statement  of  Facts  and  Simplification  of  the

                                         Issues”  has  been  executed,  only  SUCH  evidence,  documentary  or

                                         testimonial,  as  are  pertinent  to  the  issues  agrees  upon  shall  be


                                         admitted in the hearings provided, that additional facts and/or issues

                                         may  be  considered  by  the  Disciplining Authority  if  the  same  will  be

                                         considered indispensable for arriving at a just equitable resolution of

                                         the case.

                              Evidence


                                 a)  The Disciplining Authority may admit and give probative value to evidence

                                     commonly accepted  by  reasonably  prudent  men  in  the  conduct  of  their

                                     affairs.

                                 b)  Documentary evidence may be received in the form of copies or excerpts

                                     if the original is not readily available. Upon request, the parties shall be

                                     given the opportunity to compare the copy with the original. If the original

                                     is in the official custody of a Public Officer, a certified copy thereof may be


                                     accepted.

                                 c)  Every party have the right to cross-examine witnesses presented against

                                     them and to submit to rebut their testimony.










                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 d)  The Disciplining Authority may take not of judicially cognizable technical

                                     or  scientific  facts  within  its  specialized  knowledge.  The  parties  shall  be


                                     notified and afforded the opportunity to contest said facts.

                              Decision

                                 a)  Every decision rendered by the Disciplining Authority shall be in writing

                                     and  shall  state  clearly  and  distinctly  the  facts  and  the  provision  of  this

                                     code  and  the  law  on  which  it  is  based.  The  Disciplining  Authority  shall

                                     decide each case within ten (10) days after the parties have submitted the

                                     same resolution.


                                 b)  The  decision  of  the  Committee  on  Student  Misdemeanor  where  the

                                     penalty imposed in EXCLUSION for not more than two (2) months shall

                                     be  final  end  executory.  Decisions  where  the  penalty  imposed  is

                                     EXCLUSION for more than two (2) months shall be final and executory if

                                     within ten (10) days from receipt of the decision, no appeal is submitted to


                                     the Board of Student Discipline.

                                 c)  The decisions  of  the Board  Student  Discipline  on  cases  appealed  from

                                     the  committee  on  Student  Misdemeanor  shall  be  final  and  executory.

                                     Other  decisions  of  the  Board  of  Student  Discipline  shall  be  final  and

                                     executory  except  where  the  penalty  imposed  is  EXLCUSION  for  more

                                     than one (1) semester, or EXPULSION, in which cases; the Disciplinary

                                     Authority shall elevate the case, together with the entire records, to the


                                     President for review.

                                 d)  The  decision  on  review  of  the  President  shall  be  final  and  executory

                                     fifteen (15) days after the receipt thereof by the party adversely affected,

                                     unless within that period, and administrative appeal to higher authorities

                                     or a petition for judicial review, if proper, has been perfected.




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                              Implementation/Execution of Decisions

                              A.  Decisions  rendered  by  the  Disciplining  Authorities  shall  be  provisionally


                                 implemented upon receipt thereof by the party adversely affected; provided,

                                 that  when  the  minimum  period  of  the  penalty  prescribed  for  the  offence

                                 charged under this code has elapsed, and the delay is not attributable to the

                                 student/s charged, the implementation of the penalty shall be suspended until

                                 after the final judgment.

                                 a)  Final decisions shall be executed as provided for in this code; provided,

                                     that the period during which the decision was provisionally implemented


                                     as provided for in the preceding section shall deducted in the imposition

                                     of the penalty.

                              Separability and Repealing Clause

                                 o  If any provisions or sections of this Code or the application thereof to any

                                     student are held invalid, the other provisions or sections of this Code and


                                     their  application  to  other  students  concerned  shall  not  be  affected.
                                     Pertinent provision in the previous “STUDENTS’ NORM OF CONDUCT”


                                     inconsistent  with  the provisions  herein  are  hereby  repealed  or  modified

                                     accordingly.

                              Use of Cell Phones Test Messaging Equipment

                                 o  The  University  as  a  matter  of  policy  shall  discourage  the  bringing  into

                                     classroom  cellphones,  and  text  messaging  equipment  in  order  not  to


                                     disturb  the  classroom  atmosphere  and  to  minimize  sending  of  text  and

                                     other secret messages that would encourage cheating in examinations.

                            ➢  Present legal document on Campus Journalism.








                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                                      REPUBLIC ACT NO. 7079

                     AN ACT PROVIDING FOR THE DEVELOPMENT AND PROMOTION OF CAMPUS


                                       JOURNALISM AND FOR OTHER PURPOSES.
                       Section 1. Title. – this Act shall be known and referred to as the “Campus Journalism Act


                       of 1991.”

                       Sec. 2. Declaration of Policy – it is the declared policy of the State to uphold and protect

                       the freedom of the press even at the campus level and to promote the development and

                       growth of campus journalism as a means of strengthening ethical values, encouraging

                       critical and creative thinking, and developing moral character and personal discipline of


                       the  Filipino  youth.  In  furtherance,  of  this  policy,  the  State  shall  undertake  various
                       programs and projects aimed at improving the journalistic skills of students’ concerned


                       and promoting responsible and free journalism.

                       Sec. 3. Definition of Terms

                              a)  School – an institution for learning in the elementary, secondary or tertiary


                                 level  comprised  of  the  studentry,  administration,  faculty,  and  non-faculty

                                 personnel;

                              b)  Student Publication – the issue of any printed material that is independently

                                 published by, and which meets the needs and interests of the studentry;

                              c)  Student Journalist – any bona fide student enrolled for the current semester

                                 or term who was passed or met the qualification and standards of the editorial

                                 board. He must likewise maintain a satisfactory academic standing.


                              d)  Editorial  Board  –  In  the  tertiary  level,  editorial  board shall  be composed of

                                 student journalists who have qualified in placement examinations. In the case

                                 of elementary and high school levels, the editorial board shall be composed

                                 of  a  duly  appointed  faculty  adviser,  the  editor  who  qualified  and  a

                                 representative of the Parents-Teachers’ Association, who will determine the




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 editorial policies to be implemented by the editor and staff members of the

                                 student publication concerned. At the tertiary level, the editorial board may


                                 include a publication adviser at the option of its member.
                              e)  Editorial  Policies  –  A  set  of  guidelines  by  which  a  student  publication  is


                                 operated  and  managed,  taking  into  account  pertinent  laws  as  well  as  the

                                 school  administration’s  policies.  Said  guidelines  shall  determine  the

                                 frequency  of  the  publication,  the  manner  of  selecting  articles  and  features

                                 and other similar matters.

                       Sec. 4.    Student Publication – A student publication is published by the student body


                                 through and editorial board and publication and publication staff composed of

                                 students selected but fair competitive examinations.

                                 Once the publication is established, its editorial board shall freely determine

                                 its editorial policies and manage the publication’s funds.

                       Sec. 5.   Funding  of  Student  Publication  –  funding  for  the  student  publication  may

                                 include  the  savings  of  the  respective  school’s  appropriations,  student


                                 subscriptions,  donations  and  other  sources  of  funds.  Chan  Robles  Virtual

                                 Law of Library

                                 In no instance shall the Department of Education, Culture and Sports or the

                                 school administration concerned withhold the release of funds sourced from

                                 the savings of the appropriation of the respective schools and other sources

                                 intended for the student publication. Subscription fees collected by the school


                                 administration  shall  be  released  automatically  to  the  student  Publication

                                 concerned.












                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                       Sec. 6.   Publication Adviser – The publication adviser shall be selected by the school

                                 administration from a list of recommendees submitted by the publication staff.


                                 The  function of the adviser shall be limited to one of technical guidance.

                       Sec. 7.    Security of Tenure – A member of the publication staff must maintain his or

                                 her status as a student in order to retain membership in the publication staff.

                                 A student shall not be expelled or suspended solely on the basis of articles

                                 he/she has written, or on the basis of the performance of his/her duties in the

                                 student publication.

                       Sec. 8.   Press  Conference  and  Training  Seminar  –  The  Department  of  Education,


                                 Culture  and  Sports  shall  sponsor  periodic  competitions,  press  conferences

                                 and training seminars in which student-editors/writers and teacher-adviser of

                                 student  publications  in  the  elementary,  secondary  and  tertiary  levels  shall

                                 participate.  Such  competitions,  conferences  and  seminars  shall  be  held  at

                                 institutional, divisional and regional levels, culminating with the holding of the


                                 annual national elementary, secondary or tertiary School Press Conferences

                                 in places of historical and/or cultural interests in the country.

                       Sec. 9.   Rules and Regulations – the Department of Education, Culture and Sports, in

                                 coordination with the officers of the national elementary, secondary or tertiary

                                 organizations or official adviser of student publications, together with student

                                 journalists  at  the  tertiary  level  and  existing  organizations  of  student

                                 journalists,  shall  promulgate  the  rules  and  regulations  necessary  for  the


                                 effective implementations of this Act.

                       Sec. 10.  Tax  Exemption  –  Pursuant  to  paragraph  4,  Section  4,  Article  XIV  of  the

                                 Constitution,  all  grants  endorsements,  donations  or  contributions  used

                                 actually, directly and exclusively for the promotion of campus journalism as

                                 provided for this Act shall be exempts from donor’s or gift tax.




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                       Sec. 11.   Appropriations – for the initial year of implementations, the sum of Five Million

                                 Pesos (5,000,000.00) is hereby authorized to be charged against the savings


                                 from the current appropriations of the Department of Education, Culture and

                                 Sports. Thereafter, SUCH amount as may be necessary shall be included in

                                 the General Appropriations Act.

                       Sec. 12.  Effectivity  –  this  act  shall  take  effect  after  fifteen  (15)  days  following  the

                                 completion  of  its  publication  in  the  Official  Gazette  or  in  at  least  two  (2)

                                 newspapers of general circulation.

                                                                         Approved: July 5, 1991


                            ➢  Present Institutional guidelines on student discipline.

                          See STUDENTS’ CODE OF CONDUCT OF THE Student’s Handbook


               2. IMPLEMENTATION

                            ➢  Present  checklist  of  requirements  for  recognition/accreditation  of  student
                                organizations.
                                See  checklist  of  requirements  for  recognition/accreditation  of  student
                                organizations

                            ➢  Present all duly approved Constitution and By Laws of Student Organizations.
                                See Constitution and By laws of Student Organizations

                            ➢  Present Sample Programs on Leadership Training including pictorials.
                                See sample program on Leadership Training

                            ➢  Present in flow chart form procedure for student grievances.

                            ➢  Present       list     of     current      recognized/accredited       student
                                organizations/clubs/societies/councils and groups.


                            Organization           Faculty          Faculty Adviser’s       No. of
                                                  Adviser/s            Major Field         Years as
                                                                                           Adviser

                         1.Central Student    Jelyn O. Digma/    Business Management      1
                         Government           Rose Ann R.        Hotel and Restaurant
                                              Tobias             Management






                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                         2. League of         Keno A.            Information Technology  1
                         Information          Villavicencio
                         Technology           Richard A.         Information Technology
                         Leaders              Rocillo
                         2. Young             Desiree Anne D.  Office Administration      1
                         Marketers Guild      Mendoza
                                              Lucky Cedrick D.  Business Management
                                              Guyamin
                         2. League of         Kristel Shane C.   Hotel and Restaurant     1
                         Hoteliers and        Paminter           Management
                         Restaurateurs        Rose Ann R.        Hotel and Restaurant
                                              Tobias             Management


                            ➢  Prepare list of co-curricular and extra-curricular activities conducted
                                See T3 Annal Report

               3. OUTCOMES

                            ➢  Cite  evidences/manifestations  that  quality  student  development  services  are
                                assured.

               4. BEST PRACTICES

                            ➢  Cite  as  many  best  practices  as  you  can  on  Parameter  C  (Student
                                Development).

                              ➢      (Student Development)

                                     1.  Student  organization  are  accredited  during  the  recognition  program.

                                         Requirement and procedure for student accreditation/recognition are

                                         disseminated  through  prints  and  non-print  forms  of  announcement.


                                         Monitoring  and  evaluation  of  student  activities  are  done  through

                                         submission of accomplishment reports and financial statements to the

                                         Head of the SOSCA.

                                     2.  Each student organization is guided by their own Constitution and By-

                                         laws.

                                     3.  Leadership  training  is  conducted  to  enhance  their  psychological


                                         growth towards socialized maturity.





                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     4.  Officers are provided to the different student organizations.

                                     5.  Students  are  given  the  opportunities  to  participate  to  various


                                         symposia.

                                     6.  The University ensures transparency to the development, revision of

                                         guidelines for the student council by involving the student leaders in

                                         the  recently  held  seminar-workshop  on  Review  and  Revision  of

                                         Student Affairs.

                                     7.  Committee on Student Misdemeanor and Board of Student Discipline

                                         are  established  to  conduct  investigation  on  cases  involving  student


                                         discipline. Mechanism to address student grievance is available.

                                     8.  Student  violation  are  carefully  investigated  by  the  Committee  of

                                         Misdemeanor and appropriate sanctions are given to those who will

                                         be proven guilty.






























                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




               PARAMETER D – INSTITUTIONAL STUDENT PROGRAMS AND SERVICES


               1. SYSTEM-INPUTS AND PROCESSES

                            ➢  Present institutional policies and guidelines on student recruitment, selection,
                                admission and retention

                              Policies and Guidelines for the Graduate and Distance Education Programs

                                     The  following  policies  apply  to  both  the  masters  and  doctorate  degree

                              programs  and  the  post  baccalaureate  courses  offered  by  the  University.  The

                              academic programs of the Open Learning College (OLC) shall also follow these

                              policies and guidelines, unless otherwise specified.


                              a)  Admission. Prospective graduate students shall apply for admission to the

                                 Graduate  School  (GS)  not  later  than  the  end  of  May  for  the  first  semester

                                 enrolment, June and the end of October for the second semester enrolment

                                 (November).

                                         Applicants seeking admission to the master’s degree programs must

                                 be  holders  of  bachelor’s  degree  and  with  a  GPA  of  at  least  2.25.  Those


                                 seeking  admission  to  the  doctorate  degree  programs  must  be  holders  of

                                 master’s  degree  and  the  GPA  of  at  least  1.5.  An  applicant  for  a  degree

                                 program different from his previous field of specialization shall be required by

                                 the  Screening  Committee  to  take  the  recommended  preparatory  courses

                                 during the first semester of residence.

                                         The admission of an applicant shall be determined upon submission


                                 of the following:

                                     1.  Duly  accomplished  application  form  for  admission  and  three  (3)

                                         copies of passport size picture;

                                     2.  Original  or  authenticated  official  transcript  of  records  bearing  the

                                         official seal(s) of the school (s) attended;




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     3.  Two  sealed  letters  of  recommendation  from  a  former  professor  and

                                         the  immediate  supervisor.  These  may  be  personally  delivered  or


                                         mailed to the GS-OLC;

                                     4.  Non-refundable  application  fee  of  P100.00  for  Filipino  citizens  or

                                         US$50.00  for  foreign  nationals.  (Figures  may  be  changed  without

                                         prior notice);

                                     5.  Approved permit to study (for employed teachers under DepEd and

                                         for CvSU faculty/staff only);

                                     6.  Photocopies of students visa and passport (for foreign nationals only);


                                         and

                                     7.  Certificate  of  English  Proficiency  from  the  Department  of  Language

                                         and  Mass  Communication  (DLMC),  College  of  Arts  and  Sciences

                                         (CAS). In addition, students coming from countries where English is

                                         not  the  medium  of  instruction  must  submit  a  certification  of  having


                                         obtained passing score of at least 500 TOEFL.

                                            The  applicant  shall  personally  submit  the  aforementioned

                                     requirements (1,2, 4-6) to GS-OLC to enable him to immediately take the

                                     written examination to satisfy the requirements in the Number 7 above.

                                            The GS-OLC and the department concerned reserve the right to

                                     require additional documents-information form an applicant when deemed

                                     necessary – All document shall become part of the permanent records of


                                     CvSU GS-OLC and shall not be returned to the applicants.

                                     1.  Admission  Status.  An  applicant  to  a  graduate  program  may  be

                                         admitted  on  either  regular  or  probationary  status.  Regular  status  is

                                         given  to  an  applicant  whose  academic  records  and  supporting

                                         documents indicate that he is qualified to undertake graduate study in




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                         his chosen field. Probationary status is given to an applicant whose

                                         academic records and academic documents indicate deficiencies but


                                         show potential for success in graduate studies.

                                     2.  Screening  Committee.  A  Screening  Committee  created  by  the

                                         Department of Chairperson shall be composed of three (3) graduate

                                         faculty members from the respective department offering the graduate

                                         program. The Department Chairperson shall act as the Chairman of

                                         the  Committee.  The  Department  concerned  shall  formulate  its  own

                                         screening procedure and criteria. All documents pertaining to request


                                         for admission shall be forwarded to the Committee for evaluation and

                                         recommendation. The decision of the Committee shall be forwarded

                                         to the Dean, GS-OLC, who, in turn, informs the applicant of the status

                                         of his admission.

                                     3.  Change of Status. A student with probationary status maybe granted


                                         regular  status  upon  completion  of  at  least  six  (6)  units  credited
                                         towards  a  maser’s/diploma  program  and  nine  (9)  units  to  doctorate


                                         program with a GPA of 2.00 or better. The change of status must be

                                         recommended by the GS-OLC Registrar and approved by the Dean of

                                         GS-OLC. The Secretary of GS-OLC shall notify the graduate student

                                         of  his  academic  status  immediately  after  completing  the  required

                                         number  of  units.  A  student  who  fails  to  comply  with  the  above


                                         requirement shall be informed that he is disqualified from the intended

                                         program of study.

                                     4.  Readmission. All former students who failed to register for more than

                                         a  year  without  approved  leave  of  absence  shalt  be  requir4ed  for

                                         readmission to the GS-OLC.




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                          b. Registration. Before a student can register, he must first present the Notice of

                          Admission and the Medical Certificate to the GS-OLC registrar. Likewise, a student


                          shall confer with his Registration Adviser concerning the subjects to be register.

                              1.  Registration  period  set  by  the  University.  Registration  of  regular  graduate

                                 students shall be done in the main campus.

                              2.  Before  registration,  a  faculty  member,  officially  recommended  by  the

                                 Department Chair and  approved by the GS-OC Dean, shall serve as the ad

                                 interim registration adviser until the student’s Advisory Committee shall have

                                 been officially formed.


                          c. Cross Registration. A CvSU graduate student planning to cross-register courses

                          with  other  institution  should  secure  a  written  permit  from  the  GS-OLC  Registrar.

                          Permit may be granted provided the subjects to be cross-enrolled are not offered by

                          GS-OLC during the term. Cross registered subjects shall be subject to validation of

                          the department concerned. Students shall be allowed to cross-register a maximum of


                          (6) units.

                                 A  cross  registrant  from  another  educational  institution  should  present  a

                          written permission from his school registrar to the GS-Registrar. The permit should

                          state subject(s) and the total number of units the student is allowed to cross-enroll

                          and that the University shall be the venue for the course(s) to be registered.

                                 For the courses with pre-requisites, the cross registrants shall be required to

                          present an authenticated proof of equivalency of course(s) and the description(s) of


                          the required course(s).

                          d. Advisory Committee. A graduate student, in the consultation with his od interim

                          Adviser and/or the Chairperson of the department where he intends to pursue the

                          graduate program, select his Adviser who shall serve as Chairman of the Advisory

                          Committee.




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 The graduate student shall nominate the Advisory Committee not later than

                          two months after his first registration. The committee shall be composed of three (3)

                          member  for  the  master’s  degree/diploma  course  and  four  (4)  for  the  doctorate


                          degree.

                              1.  For master’s degree students, two (2) members of the Advisory Committee

                                 must come from the department of the student’s major field and one (1) from

                                 the cognate field. In the case of post baccalaureate diploma, three (3) faculty

                                 members  from  the  selected  major  field/department  shall  compose  the

                                 Advisory Committee.


                              2.  For  doctorate  degree  students,  tree  (3)  of  the  committee  members  should

                                 come from his major department and one (1) from his cognate field.

                              3.  Membership in the Advisory Committee for doctorate degree programs shall

                                 be  limited  or graduate  faculty members who are  doctorate  degree holders.

                                 Advisory  Committee  for  MS/MA/Magr/MPS/Diploma  shall  be  holders  of  at

                                 least  master’s  degree.  Affiliate  professor  in  Learning  Center  may  serve  as


                                 members of the Advisory Committee.

                              4.  The Dean of the GS-OLC shall approve changes in the composition of the

                                 Advisory  Committee  upon  the  recommendation  of  the  Department

                                 Chairperson with the concurrence of the old and the new member(s) of the

                                 committee.

                          e. Plan of Course Work. Before the end of the first semester, a regular student in a

                          master’s  degree  program  in  a  post  baccalaureate  diploma  course  shall  prepare  a


                          plan of a course work in consultation with his Advisory Committee and in accordance

                          with the requirements of the selected degree program and the GS-OLC. A student on

                          probationary status shall prepare and work immediately after the change of status

                          from probationary to regular.




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 In the case of doctorate degree students, the plan of course work shall be

                          prepared after passing the qualifying examination,


                                 An approved composition of the Advisory Committee and the Plan of Course
                          Work shall be the requirement for a regular student’s registration for the succeeding


                          semester.

                                 Any  change  in  the  plan  of  course  work  must  be  recommended  by  the

                          members  of  the  Advisory  Committee,  the  Department  Chair  and  approved  by  the

                          Dean.

                          f. Course Work Requirements. For a master’s degree with thesis, a minimum of 36


                          units of course work and six (6) units of thesis are required, while for non-thesis a

                          minimum of 42 units or course work are required. For doctorate degree, a minimum

                          of 48 units of course work and 12 units of dissertation are required.

                                 Students  enrolled  in  a  post  baccalaureate  diploma  course  are  required  to

                          take a minimum of 45 units of course work.


                                 Graduate  students  are  also  required  to  take  six  (6)  of  non-credit  computer

                          courses except those who have already taken the prescribed computer courses prior

                          to their admission to GS-OLC, subject to validation of the Department of Computer

                          Studies, College of Engineering and Information Technology.

                                 A  graduate  student  register  for  a  non-credit  course  must  complete  all  the

                          requirements of the course as of this were taken for credit for which he must receive

                          a passing grade of 2.00 or better. The non-credit courses are assessed on a full-fee


                          basis.

                          g. Unit Load. A non-working student may enroll a maximum load of 12 credits units

                          if  classes  are  conducted  during  regular  days.  However,  for  Saturday/summer

                          classes, a graduate student may enroll a maximum load of nine (9) units  for non-

                          laboratory subjects and six (6) units subject with laboratory. CvSU full-time faculty




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                          members  and  staff  who  are  admitted  in  the  GS-OLC  shall  be  allowed  to  enroll  a

                          maximum of six (6) units per semester.


                          h. Advance or Transfer Credits. A student may apply to the GS-OLC for transfer

                          credits of academic work done in another institution only upon the recommendation

                          of the department where he is planning to specialize to the following condition:

                                 1.  Presentation of credential showing that he passed the courses registered

                                     in the institution equivalent to those offered in the College or Department

                                     from which credit is sought.

                                 2.  Subjects for consideration have not been credited for another degree, and


                                 3.  Passing  the  validating  examination  administered  by  the  Department

                                     concerned.  Validating  examination  shall  be  administered  by  the

                                     Department  concerned  during  the  first  year  of  the  student’s  residence.

                                     Results of the validating examination shall be submitted to GS-OLC not

                                     later than one week after the date of examination.


                                            A  maximum  of  nine  (9)  advance  or  transfer  credit  units  may  be

                                     granted to a graduate student towards a graduate. Degree.

                          i.  Admission  in  Fields  of  Specialization.    For  students  to  be  admitted  in  a

                          particular major field, a maximum of five (5) enrollees is required. Otherwise, they

                          shall be encouraged to select a more popular area of specialization.

                          j.  Changing  and/or  Adding  Subjects.  A  graduate  student  may  apply  for

                          changing/adding  of  course  (s)  within  one  week  after  the  opening  of  the  classes.


                          Changing and/or adding of subject(s) shall be done for valid reasons only, with the

                          consent  of  his  professor(s),  recommended  by  the  Adviser,  and  approved  by  the

                          Dean of GS-OLC.

                          k. Dropping of Subject. Dropping of subjects is not allowed after three-fourths of

                          the number of hours prescribed for the term has elapsed except for illness and other




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                          justifiable  reasons  such  as  a  transfer  of  residence  elsewhere,  locally  or  abroad.

                          Beyond  this  period,  a  student  shall  be  given  a  failing  mark  if  his  performance  is


                          below average or a numerical passing grade if the performance is satisfactory.

                                 A  student  who  intends  to  drop  a  course  should  accomplish  an  official

                          dropping form to be  noted by the Professor concerned, the Adviser, the Department

                          Chair  and  approved  by  the  Dean  of  the  GS-OLC.  Dropping  of  courses  shall  be

                          considered official only upon approval of the Dean of the GS-OLC.

                          l. Attendance. A graduate student shall be automatically dropped from the course

                          when his absences reached 20 percent of the total number of hours required for the

                          course. If majority of these absences are not excused and the student’s performance


                          is unsatisfactory, he shall be given a grade of 5.0 in the course. The professor shall

                          report  the  case  officially  in  writing  to  the  Dean  of  GS-OLC.  Time  due  to  late

                          enrollment shall be considered as absence from classes.

                          m. Residence Requirement and Time-Limit Rule. A minimum of four (4) semester

                          and  one  (1)  summer  is  required  for  a  master’s  degree  or  a  post  baccalaureate


                          diploma  course.  For  a  doctorate  degree,  a  minimum  of  six  (6)  semester  and  one

                          summer  is  required.  A  student  is  in  residence  when he  is  registered  for  a  course

                          work with the approval of his Advisory Committee.

                                 Work in absentia may be granted if a student will be conducting and/or writing

                          the manuscript of his thesis/dissertation with the approval of his Advisory Committee.

                          In such a case, the student must be duly registered in thesis/dissertation. A graduate


                          student  who  works  in  absentia  must  submit  periodic  progress  reports  to  the

                          Chairman of his Advisory Committee.

                                 The maximum period for completing master’s degree or a post baccalaureate

                          diploma course shall be five (5) years, and seven (7) years for the doctorate degree.

                          The  counting  of  years  starts  from  the  time  of  initial  enrollment  in  the  program,




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                          inclusive  of  the  Leave  of  Absence.  A  graduate  student  who  fails  to  complete  the

                          requirement  for  the  program  that  he  is  pursuing  within  the  time  limit  will  be


                          disqualified from the program but may apply for readmission to the Graduate School

                          or Open Learning College in another program (degree program or major field).

                          n. Leave of Absence. A students request for leave of absence must be approved by

                          the  Dean  of  the  GS-OLC  upon  endorsement  by  the  Chairman  of  the  Advisory

                          Committee  and  noted  by  the  Department  Chairperson.  The  request  should  state

                          reason(s) for which the leave is requested. An approved leave of absence shall be

                          counted toward the time limit.


                                 A graduate student with leave of absence exceeding two (2) years or stops

                          attending  classes  for  two  years  or  more  without  approved  leave  of  absence  but

                          within the time limit rule shall be readmitted in the same program only after passing

                          the validating examination in all subjects taken.

                          o. Honorable Dismissal.  A graduate student who desires to severe connection with


                          the University shall submit a written petition to the University Registrar, noted by the
                          Dean of the GS-OLC. If the request is granted, the student shall be given “Honorable


                          Dismissal” by the University Registrar.

                                 A  clearance  from  the  University  must  be  secured  before  a  certificate  of

                          honorable  dismissal  is  issued.  No  certification  of  “Honorable  Dismissal”  shall  be

                          granted  to  a  graduate  student  with  the  pending  case  (s)  of  violation  of  University

                          rules and regulations.


                          p.  Grade  Requirement  and  Retention.    In  order  to  qualify  for  the  general

                          comprehensive examination, a student must obtain a GPA of 2.00 or better for all the

                          courses taken. Courses listed under “others” shall be excluded from the computation

                          but the grades in these subjects must be passing.







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 Failure to pass a subject twice shall disqualify the student from the graduate

                          program.


                                 Similarly,  a  graduate student  must  maintain  a  GPA  of  2.00  or  better  every

                          term in order to qualify to continue with his program.

                          q. Grades and Grading System. The University shall adopt the numerical grading

                          system of “1.00” to “5.00”, where “1.00” is the highest grade and the “5.00” is a failing

                          grade. The system of grading is as follows:

                                 A grade of “Inc.” is given to a student with passing class standing but fails to

                          complete  other  course  requirements.  Removal  of  “Inc.”  grade  must  be  done  by


                          meeting all the requirements for the course within one year immediately following the
                          term in which the grade “Inc.” was incurred. If a student fails to remove the “Inc.”


                          grade within one (1) year, he shalt automatically be given a grade of “5.00” in the

                          subject.

                                 A  student,  who  incurred  an  incomplete  grade  under  a  professor  who  has


                          gone abroad for more than six (6) months or who has transferred or resigned, may

                          complete his-Inc. Grade under another professor of the same subject.

                          r. Changing of Degree Program/major and Minor Fields.  A student who plans to

                          change  his  graduate  program  should  apply  to  the  GS-OLC.  Credentials  of  the

                          applicant shall be forwarded to the Screening Committee of the department where he

                          is  planning  to  take  his  new  graduate  program.  A  change  in  a  student’s

                          major/minor/cognate  fields  must  be  endorsed  by  his  Adviser  and  the  Chair  of  the


                          Department where the student plans to take his new major/minor/cognate field, and

                          approved by Dean.

                          s. Qualifying Examination. Only regular doctorate degree students shall be allowed

                          to  take  the  written  qualifying  examination  after  earning  nine  units  of  the  required

                          courses.  The  examination  shall  be  administered  by  the  Advisory  Committee.  The




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                          result  of  the  examination  shall  be  the  basis  for  evaluating  the  students’  ability  to

                          pursue the doctorate degree and for determining a suitable program of course work


                          for him.

                                 The student shall submit his application for the qualifying examination to the

                          Dean,  GS-OLC  not  later  than  one  (1)  month  before  the  date  of  examination.  The

                          application  must  be  duly  recommended  by  Advisory  Committee  and  noted  by  the

                          Chair of the student’s major Department. Details of the qualifying examination shall

                          be left to the discretion of the Advisory Committee.

                                 To  pass  the  examination,  the  student  must  obtain  a  unanimous  “passing”


                          vote from the members of the Committee.

                                 The Chairman of the Advisory Committee shall submit to the Dean a report

                          on the result of the examination within one (1) week after the examination

                                 If the student fails the qualifying examination, an oral examination within one

                          (1)  week  after  the  first  examination  may  be  allowed  subject  to  the  unanimous


                          approval  of  the  Advisory  Committee.  If  the  student  fails  in  the  re-examination,  he

                          shall be permanently disqualified from the program.

                          t. General Comprehensive Examination. A graduate student who has completed

                          all the academic requirement prescribed in his approved plan of course work shall

                          apply  for  a  written  departmental  comprehensive  examination.  Application  for  the

                          comprehensive examination shall be submitted for the approval to the Dean of GS-

                          OLC,  not  later  than  one  month  before  the  date  of  examination.  This  shall  be


                          endorsed  by  the  Advisory  Committee  and  recommended  by  The  Department

                          Chairperson.

                                 The respective Department shall administer written and oral comprehensive

                          examinations.  A  written  examination  shall  be  given  for  each  area  (Core,  Major,







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                          Cognate courses) indicated in the graduate student’s plan of course work. A student

                          must pass the examination in each of the three areas.


                                 The Chairperson of the Department shall submit to the Dean of GS-OLC a

                          report on the result of the written examination two (2) weeks after the examination.

                                 A student shall be allowed to take the written comprehensive examination in

                          all or any of the three (3) areas only twice. The second examination must be taken

                          and passed within one (1) year after the first examination.

                                 Oral  examination  shall  be  given  after  passing  the  written  examination  the

                          details of the examination shall be left to the discretion of the Advisory Committee

                          and  an  external  expert.  An  unanimous  “passing”  vote  of  the  members  of  the


                          Committee is required in order to pass the oral examination.

                                     u.  Thesis/Dissertation.  A  graduate  student  is  ready  to  conduct  his

                          thesis/dissertation if the following requirements are satisfied:

                                 1.  Passed the general comprehensive examination; and


                                 2.  A  thesis/dissertation  outline  the  following  University  prescribed  is

                                     approved  and  recommended  by  the  Advisory  Committee  after  oral

                                     deliberations.  The  outline  shall  be  endorsed  by  the  Department  Chair,

                                     noted by the Director of Research, and submitted to the Dean of the GS-

                                     OLC. Copies of the approved outline shall be distributed to the members

                                     of the Advisory Committee and the Dean of the GS-OLC.

                                     Graduate  students  enrolled  in  the  doctorate  degree  or  master’s  degree


                              thesis/dissertation  are  expected  to  produce  the  following  output  in  accordance

                              with the number of units enrolled:

                              Units Enrolled                      Expected Output

                              Master’s Doctorate

                                       1       1 - 2       Approve thesis/dissertation outline




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                       2       3 - 5       Gathered data/conducted experiment

                                       3       6 - 8       Analyzed and interpreted data


                                       4       9 -10       Prepared 1” draft of the manuscript

                                       5      11-12        Passed final examination/reproduce

                                                                  final manuscript

                                     A graduate student who complies with the expected output shall be given

                              a grade of S (Satisfactory) while one who fails to accomplish the expected output

                              shall  be  given  a  grade  of  U  (Unsatisfactory).  The  Chairman  of  the  Advisory

                              Committee, in consultation with the other members, shall give the final numerical


                              grade for the thesis/dissertation upon approval of the manuscript.

                          v.  Final  Examination.  A  panel  of  Examiners  shall  administer  the  final  oral

                          examination on a graduate student’s thesis/dissertation. The student’s application for

                          final examination, duly recommended by the Advisory Committee and noted by the

                          Department Chair, shall be submitted for approval of the Dean of GS-OLC not later


                          than two (2) weeks before the actual date of the examination. The student must be

                          enrolled in his thesis/dissertation during the term at which the final examination takes

                          place. Final examination shall be conducted at the main campus.

                                 A candidate must provide a copy of the final draft of the thesis/dissertation

                          manuscript to each of the members of the panel of Examiners at least two (2) weeks

                          before the date of the final examination. The Chairman of the Panel of Examiners

                          shall submit on a prescribed form a report on the result of the examination to the GS-


                          OLC within three (3) days after the final examination.

                                 Panel  of  Examiners.  The  Chairman  and  the  Members  of  the  Panel  of

                          Examiners shall be chosen on the basis of their expertise and area of specialization.

                          The Department Chairperson shall appoint the Chairman and the members of the

                          panel.




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 The Panel shall include one external expert as a member and two graduate

                          faculty members.


                                 The  GS-OLC  Research  Coordinator  and  the  Chairman  of  the  Advisory

                          Committee shall sit in the oral defense but will not give grades to the student.

                                 The  expert,  whose  area  of  expertise  is  on  the  major  field  of  the  graduate

                          student, shall come from firms and other institutions outside the University.

                          w. Graduation. A graduate student who is a candidate for graduation shall furnish

                          the GS an abstract of his thesis/dissertation at least one week before the University

                          Academic Council meeting to decide graduation of students.


                                 Nine (9) properly bound copies of the manuscript must be submitted to the

                          GS not later than the following deadlines:

                              1.  For Summer Graduates – the day before the first day of regular registration

                                 for the succeeding first semester

                              2.  For  First  Semester  Graduates  –  the  day  before  the  first  day  of  regular


                                 registration for the succeeding second semester.

                              3.  For Second Semester Graduates  – the day before the Academic Council

                                 meeting to decide the graduation of students.

                                 A student who has completed all the academic requirements for a degree and

                          other requirements including clearance forms and graduation fees shall be included

                          in the list of graduating students. Candidates for graduation are required to attend

                          the  commencement  exercise.  Those  who  cannot  attend  because  of  valid  reasons


                          such as illness or a scheduled travel abroad must submit a request for graduation in

                          absentia to the Dean of GS.

                                 The following awards shall be given to deserving graduates:

                              1.  University State Award. This shall be awarded to a graduate with GPA of

                                 1.25 or better;




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                              2.  College State Award. This shall be given to a graduate of 1.50  to 1.26; and

                              3.  Best  Thesis/Dissertation  Award.  Recipient(s)  of  this  award  shall  be


                                 determined by a Search Committee headed by the Research Director.

                                Transcript of records can only be issued upon presentation of valid clearance

                            ➢  Present institutional policies and guidelines on wellness and healthy lifestyle.

                                       The CvSu Health Service is basically a supportive unit of University. It is


                                in charged with the delivery of the basic health services which are pro motive,

                                preventive  and  curative  and  to  some  extent  rehabilitative.  Its  vital  role  is

                                towards  the  achievements  of  delivering  quality,  affordable  and  accessible

                                health services with maximum enjoyment of good health to its clientele.

                                       Its services are also extensively utilized to the University for its Students


                                Practicum,  on  the  job  training  and  in  varying  degrees  for  health  manpower

                                development and research as well as for rural development program.

                              Mission:

                                     To  provide  the  highest  attained  patient  care  by  making  “the  right  to

                              health” a reality though:

                                 a)  Delivering quality, affordable and accessible health services

                                 b)  Arousing community health awareness


                                 c)  Promoting better health services in the work place

                                 d)  Mobilizing health resources

                              Vision:

                                     Health is a basic human right. A continuous set quality services must be

                              provided to assure reality of this right, not only to the academic community of the


                              University but also to the residents of Indang and nearby municipalities.

                              Objectives:





                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     In order to realize our vision and mission, we have the following general

                              and specific objectives.


                              General Objectives:

                                     a.  To  provide  the  best  possible  pro  motive,  preventive,  curative  and

                                         rehabilitative health services to the clients.

                                     b.  To deliver quality, affordable and accessible health services.

                              Specific Objectives:

                                 A.  To provide curative care in terms of the following:

                                    a.1  our  patient  medical  and  dental  consultation  including  minor  a  light


                                    major surgical and dental care

                                    a.2 in patient secondary treatment and confinement

                                    a.3 emergency care treatment

                                 B)  To engaged in preventive and pro motive health activities such as:

                                     b.1 pre-employment physical, dental and laboratory examination


                                     b.2  annual  physical,  dental  and  laboratory  examination  of  the  faculty

                                     members, staff and employees

                                     b.3 physical, dental and laboratory examination of all students

                                     b.4 annual medical examination of all food handlers and vendors within

                                     the University campus

                                     b.5 establishment of medical ancillary services which include laboratory,

                                     x-ray, pharmacy, ambulance and civic action services


                                     b.6 family planning, pre-natal, post-natal and well-baby clinic

                                     b.7 immunization program

                                     b.8  food,  water  and  environmental  sanitation  which  include  insect  and

                                     vermin control and waste disposal program.







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 C)    To  develop  advocacy  for  its  rural  and  development  program  for  the

                                 enhancement of health awareness of community through the following:


                                     c.1 conduct or attend different outreach lectures, conferences, seminars

                                     on health related issues in coordination with the different health agencies

                                     of the government.

                              Guideline on Medical and Dental Examination

                              Section 1. Student. All new students enrolling at the University are required to

                              undergo  physical  and  dental  examination  to  determine  the  fitness  to  perform

                              various school activities. These are normally schedule in April and May for first


                              semester  enrollment  and  in  September  and  October  for  second  semester

                              enrollment. They are required to undergo chest X-ray and bloody typing.

                                     Old  students  should  submit  the  results  of  medical/dental  examination

                              done in the first semester as requirement for the second semester enrollment.

                              The annual schedule of their examination shall be as follows:


                                            Sophomore      -      June to August 15

                                            Junior         -      August 16 to September 15

                                            Senior         -      September 16 to October 30

                                     If upon physical examination, the student is diagnosed to be:

                                     a.  Suffering  from  suspicious  disease,  a  special  laboratory  examination

                                         shall  be  required  or  referred  to  a  medical  specialist  for  further

                                         evaluation  of  his  health  status and  medical  certificate  is  required  to


                                         submit to determine their fitness to go on schooling.

                                     b.  Afflicted  with  a  communicable  disease  especially  Pulmonary

                                         Tuberculosis shall be advised not to enroll otherwise they can submit

                                         medical  certificate  coming  from  a  medical  specialist  indicating  that

                                         they are physically fit to study before they can enroll at the University.




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     The rates (subject to change without prior notice) for physical and dental

                              examinations for incoming freshmen shall be as follows:


                                     a. Physical Examination fee         -      100.00

                                     b. Dental Examination fee           -      100.00

                                     c. Blood Typing                     -        60.00

                                     d. Chest X-ray                      -      160.00

                                     Old students will be charged 1,800.00 as payment for physical and dental

                              examination is done outside the schedule dates. This fee is an addition to the

                              medical fee charged upon enrollment.


                                     Should  a  student  lose  his  or  her  medical  certificate  and  request  for

                              another medical and dental examination, the student has to pay 950.00 for the

                              issuance of another medical certificate.

                                     Should a student request for physical and/or dental examination for the

                              purpose  of  employment  and  training,  the  student  will  have  to  pay  P50.00  for


                              physical examination and medical certificate to be issued.

                              Section 2. University Personnel. Every year, all faculty members and staff are

                              required to undergo medical and laboratory check-up which include the following:

                                     1.  Routine Laboratory Tests

                                         CBC

                                         Urinalysis

                                         Fecalysis


                                         Chest X-ray

                                     2.  Special Laboratory Examination

                                         ECG

                                         Blood Chemistry

                                         Pap Smear (For Female Employees)




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                         Ultrasound  (whole  abdomen  for  both  male  and  female:  pelvic  for

                                         female and prostate for male)


                                     The  preceding  medical  and  laboratory  checkups/examination  are  70%

                              subsidized by the University.

                                     If upon examination, a faculty member/staff was diagnosed to be:

                                     1.  Suffering  from  suspicious  disease,  he/she  shall  be  required  to

                                         undergo  a  special  laboratory  or  diagnostic  examination  or  shall  be

                                         referred to a medical specialist for further evaluation.

                                     2.  Afflicted  with  communicable  disease,  he/shall  be  advised  to  take  a


                                         leave of absence for two months or until he gets well or until he/she

                                         submits/presents  a  medical  certificate  coming  from  a  medical

                                         specialist, if the case is proven otherwise.

                                     Should a faculty/staff request for physical examination for the purpose of

                              training,  scholarship,  etc.  That  requires  issuance  of  medical  certificate,  he  will


                              have to pay P50.00.

                              Section 3. University Applicants. All applicants of the university shall undergo

                              the following:

                                 1.  Physical  and  dental  check  to  be  done  by  the  University  Physician  and

                              University Dentist.

                                 2.  Laboratory examination such as:

                                            Chest X-ray


                                            Complete Blood Count and Blood Typing

                                            Urinalysis

                                            Drug Test (Shabu and Marijuana)

                                            Neuro-Psychiatric Exam

                                            Pregnancy Test (for Female applicants)




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     If an applicant is diagnosed to be suffering from a severe hypertension,

                              heart disease, communicable diseases and other debilitating disease, he will be


                              given medical certificate indicating that he is not fit to work, likewise, a pregnant
                                                       rd
                              applicant who is in her 3  trimester of pregnancy will be given similar medical

                              certificate.

                                     Physical examination fee of P100.00 shall be charged per applicant, while

                              laboratory examination fees for the following procedure shall be:

                                            Chest X-ray  -        P160.00

                                            Blood Typing  -       P60.00


                                     The Medical and Dental examination fees as well as the laboratory fees

                              to  be  collected  shall  be  deposited  in  Trust  fund  and  will  be  used  to  purchase

                              medical/dental supplies and equipment. Compensation and benefits or personnel

                              of the University clinic and other needs are subjects to accounting and auditing

                              rules and regulations.



                            ➢  Present  legal  documents  such  as  RA  7277;  RA  10121  and  other  related
                                documents.

                               (Please see exhibit of the Compilation of Legal Documents)

                            ➢  Present institutional policies and guidelines on sports development programs

                                       Sports  Council.  The  University  has  an  appointed  Director  for  Sports

                                and  Development  as  an  additional  member  of  the  Sports  Council  of  the

                                Institution.  As  stated  on  the  CvSU  Operational  Manual  of  Operation  (2009),


                                there shall be a Sports Council with Dean of the College of Sports, Physical

                                Education  and  Recreation  as  Chairman.  The  members  of  the  Council  shall

                                consist of the Chairpersons of Sports and Recreation Department, all Deans

                                and selected Director, Professor of the University.

                                       The duties and responsibilities of the Sports Council shall be as follows:




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                         a.  Formulate, recommend and implement policies and regulation of

                                            athletic sports;


                                         b.  Determine the privileges and benefits of varsity athletes, coaches

                                            and trainers following the approved guidelines set by the Council;

                                         c.  Investigate and recommend penalties for varsity athletes, coaches

                                            and  officials  which  can  adversely  affect  the  name  of  the

                                            University.

                                     The Sports Council shall hold at least one meeting every quarter at the

                              date and venue to be determined by the Council Members.


                              Sports Activities. The University is conducting several sports activities such as:

                                         a.  Activities under the Physical Education curricula

                                         b.  Fitness Exercises such as aerobics, zumba, etc.

                                         c.  University Intramural

                                         d.  Regional Sports Competition such as SCUAA/STRASUC


                              Guidelines on the Selection of CvSU Athletes:

                                         a.  Must be a bona fide college student of this University and officially

                                         enrolled  in  the  first  and  second  semester  of  the  current  academic

                                         year.

                                         b.  Must carry a minimum academic load of twelve (12) units in the

                                         First and Second Semester of the current year and must have passed

                                         the required percentage follows:


                                         Academic Loads                                Passing Percentage

                                            12      units                                      100%

                                            19-20  units                                       70%

                                            19-20  units                                       80%







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                         c.  High  school  graduates  enrolled  at  least  one  (1)  year

                                         vocational/technical course, carrying the required load for the course


                                         and  complying  with  the  required  passing  percentage  thereof  are

                                         qualified to participate in SCUAA Sports Competition.

                                         d.  Graduating college students with less than twelve (12) academic

                                         units in the current semester or term are eligible to participate in the

                                         university  game  provided  that  in  seven  (7)  years  maximum  playing

                                         period after graduating from high school  and passed all the subjects

                                         enrolled in the previous semester as required in his/her curriculum.


                                         e.  College  graduates  who  have  not  yet  completed  the  seven  (7)

                                         years  maximum playing  period  may be allowed  to  participate  in  the

                                         enrolled  in  another  undergraduate  course  in  the  same  institution

                                         provided that they can comply with the required minimum academic

                                         load and passing percentage for total academic load enrolled.


                                         f.  Athlete  can  participate  in  SCUAA  Sports  Competition  for  a

                                         maximum of seven (7) years from graduation in high school provided

                                         they are not more than twenty-five (25) years of age by March 31 of

                                         the current academic year.

                                         g.  Athletes  transferring  from  PRISSA,  SCUAA  and/or  LCUAA

                                         member-school  to  another  member-school  must  satisfy  the  one  (1)

                                         year residency requirement which shall be counted as playing years.


                                         h.  Athletes  playing  or  have  played  in  nationally  known  commercial

                                         leagues regular or Competitions. In the SCUAA Sports.

                                         i.  An  athlete  classified  as  member  of  the  national  team  under  the

                                         auspices of the PSC and NSA chosen athletes as representative of







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                         the  Philippines  in  the  international competition  of  the current school

                                         year are not qualified to participate in the SCUAA Sports Competition.


                                         j.  Athletes  classified  as  member  of  the  Armed  Forces  of  the

                                         Philippine  (AFP)  and  the  Philippine  National  Police  (PNP)  are

                                         disqualified to participate in the SCUAA Sports Competitions.

                                         k.  Athletes  who  won  in  the  CvSu  University  Games  should  be

                                         assessed  by  the  University  coach  of  a  particular  sort  event  if  the

                                         athletes  are  qualified  in  the  university  pool  of  varsity  athletes  as  a

                                         requirement to become a university athlete to compete in the SCUAA


                                         and other sports competitions.

                              Policy Guidelines on the Selection of Varsity Athletes

                                 a.  A  one-semester  residency  is  required  before  a  student  can  qualify  as

                                 varsity athlete.

                                 b.  Palarong  Pambansa  player/athletes  are  exempted  from  one-semester


                                 residency  recruitment  upon  submission  of  Certificate  of  Participation  in

                                 Palarong Pambansa from national coach.

                                 c.  All applicants must pass the try-out

                                 d.  Transferees from other universities/colleges who wish to apply as varsity

                                 athlete must submit recommendation letter from Sport Director/Trainer/Coach

                                 or other higher authorities from the previous university/college.

                                 e.  Freshmen and transferee must present certificate of good moral from the


                                 school last attended.

                                     To  maintain  standing  as  varsity  athletes,  the  students  must  not  have  a

                              failing grades.

               2. IMPLEMENTATION






                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                            ➢  Describe the institution’s admission and retention policies and how these are
                                disseminated.

                          Admission and Registration

                          1.  Admission of New Students

                                     All  applicants  for  the  degree  programs  shall  pay  a  P150.00  testing  fee

                              (may  be  changed  without  prior  notice)  entrance  examination  fee;  pass  the

                              entrance  examination  given  by  the  University  and  meet  the  following


                              qualifications:

                                 1.1     Graduate of any public or DepEd recognized private high school;

                                 1.2     Physically and mentally fits to study; and

                                 1.3     Possess  a  good  moral  character  as  certified  by  the  High  School

                                         Principal


                                     Individual  colleges  and  campuses  as  certified  may  institute  their  own

                              requirements  specific  to  their  programs  provided  that  these  requirements  are

                              endorsed by the University Administrative Council and approved by the Board of

                              Regents.

                          2.  Admission of Foreign Students

                                     Foreign students are required to:

                                         2.1.1  Submit  an  approved  permit  to  study  from  the  concerned


                                                embassy;

                                         2.1.2  Pay a non-refundable foreign student fee of P530.00;

                                         2.1.3  Submit  a  Certificate  of  English  Proficiency  from  the

                                                Department of Language and Humanities

                          3.  Admission of Transfer Students


                                     Transfer  students  from  other  schools  and  colleges/universities  are

                              required to comply with the following:





                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 3.1     Submit the following:

                                         3.1.1  Certified true copy of transcript of records;


                                         3.1.2  Honorable dismissal;

                                         3.1.3  Three (3) copies of “1x1” ID picture

                                         3.1.4  Certification of good moral character certified by the guidance

                                                counselor/dean from the last school attended;

                                 3.2     Must  have  passed  the  interview  conducted  by  the  Screening

                                         Committee  of  the  College  where  the  student  intends  to  enroll  the

                                         course.


                                     In  addition,  the  respective  colleges  may  require  a  background  (inquiry)

                              check on the student who request for transfer to the University.

                                     Students who qualify for transfer may apply with their respective College

                              Registrars  for  advanced  credit  for  equivalent  courses  upon  presentation  of

                              transcript of records and authenticated proof of equivalency of courses.


                          4.  Shifting to Other Programs

                                     Students  who  intend  to  shift  to  another  University  program  must

                              accomplish a prescribed form for the purpose to be approved by the Dean of the

                              College where they want to shift to, not later than ten (10) working day s before

                              the start of the regular registration period. A copy of the approved application for

                              shifting should be forwarded by the Dean concerned to the University Registrar’s

                              Office.


                                     Students  pursuing  degree  programs  may  be  allowed  to  shift  to  non-

                              degree programs upon approval of their application for shifting.

                                     Students pursuing non-degree program may be allowed to shift to degree

                              programs  offered  by  the  College  after  satisfying  the  following  requirements

                              except for ladderized programs:




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 4.1     GPA of 2.0 or better;

                                 4.2     Submission  of  approved  application  form  and  other  supporting


                                         documents; and

                                 4.3     Passing the required entrance examination.

                          5.  Cross Registration

                                     Cross-registrants from other educational institutions should have a written

                              permission from their school registrar to be presented to the CvSU Registrar. The

                              permit  shall  state  the  subject  (s)  and  the  total  number  of  units  the  student  is

                              allowed to cross-register and that the University shall be the venue for the course


                              to be registered.

                                     For courses with pre-requisites, the cross registrant shall be required to

                              present an authenticated proof of equivalency of course and description of the

                              required course.

                                     CvSU  students  who  are  planning  to  cross-register  courses  with  other


                              institutions  should  have  a  written  permit  from  their  College  and  University

                              Registrars.  Students  planning  to  cross-register  in  other  University  College  or

                              Campus shall be allowed only under the following conditions:

                                 5.1     The  course(s)  to  be  cross-registered  should  have  exactly  the  same

                                         description  as  the  one  being  offered  in  another  college  or  campus

                                         where the student plans to cross-register;

                                 5.2     Must have written permit from their respective College Registrars and


                                         finally  the University Registrar; and

                                 5.3     Students are allowed to cross-enroll a maximum of six (6) units only

                                         for the entire program.

                          6.  Late Registration







                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     The period for the late registration shall be seven school days after the

                              regular  registration  schedule.  No  late  registrants  will  be  entertained  after  this


                              period.

                                     Undergraduate degree and non-degree students who register during the

                              unauthorized period for late registration shall be charged a fine of P100.00 (may

                              be  changed  without  prior  notice),  regardless  of  the  number  of  days  their

                              registration is delayed and the number of units that a student is carrying during a

                              particular term.

                                     Any  student  whose  registration  has  been  approved  by  the  Registrar


                              during the registration period but has not settled at least the first installment of

                              his/her fees shall also be charged fine for late registration. The Cashier’s Office

                              indicates the fine in the registration form of the student upon payment of fees.

                                     No late registration shall be entertained for the summer program.

                                     Individual  colleges  and  campuses  may  propose  and  implement  other


                              academic policies consistent with the general guidelines on academic rules and

                              regulations and approved by the Board of Regents.

                          7.  General Enrollment Guidelines and Procedures
                                     Three months prior to each registration period, the University Registrar’s


                              Office  shall  outline  the  general  enrollment  guidelines  and  procedure  or  any

                              revision  thereof  and  present  these  to  the  University  Academic  Council  for

                              approval.  No  modification  of  the  approved  guidelines  the  procedures  shall  be


                              implemented unless approved by the Office of the Vice President for Academic

                              Affairs.

                          8.  Schedule of Payment

                                     All fees may be paid in cash or installment. The schedule of payment for

                              installment is as follows:




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 8.1     50% upon registration

                                 8.2     25% two weeks before the midterm examination


                                 8.3     25% two weeks before the final examination

                          9.  Refund of Fees

                                     Students who withdraw their registration from the University after a period

                              of not more than three weeks or fifteen days of regular classes shall be refunded

                              in full except the medical and dental fees. No refund shall be given to those who

                              withdraw after this period.

                              Retention Policies


                                     A.  Rules on Scholastic Delinquency

                                            The  CvSU  shall  promulgate  suitable  and  effective  guideline  on

                                     academic  deficiencies.  Any  student  whose  scholastic  performance  in

                                     subjects  enrolled  for  the  semester  is  “Incomplete  (Inc)”  or  below  the

                                     passing mark of “3.00” and/or who dropped the subjects for unjustifiable


                                     reasons shall be subjected to the rules on academic deficiencies below:

                                     1.  Types of Academic Deficiency

                                         1.1 Warning. Any student who, at the end of the semester is found to

                                            have  dropped  the  course  or  obtain  incomplete,  conditional  or

                                            failing grades or a combination thereof in 30%-50% of the enrolled

                                            subjects enrolled shall fall under this category. The student shall

                                            be  warned  by  the  Office  of  the  College/University  Registrar  to


                                            improve his/her academic performance.

                                         1.2 Probation. Any student who at the end of the semester is found to

                                            have  dropped  the  course  or  obtain  incomplete,  or  grade  below

                                            “3.00”  or  a  combination  thereof  in  51%  or  more  of  the  enrolled

                                            subjects shall be placed under probationary status. Academic load




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                            of students under this category for the succeeding semester shall

                                            be limited to 15 units only.


                                                   If  he/she  incurs  probationary  status  for  two  consecutive

                                            semesters,  he/she  shall  be  classified  under  the  disqualification

                                            status in the next semester.

                                                   Probationary status maybe removed by obtaining a grade

                                            of “3.00” in 75% of the enrolled subjects.

                                         1.3 Disqualification.  Any  student  who,  at  the  end  of  the  semester

                                            fails  75%  or  more  of  the  enrolled  subjects  shall  be  rendered


                                            ineligible  to enroll  for one  semester.  He/She shall  be allowed  to

                                            carry  an  academic  load  of  not  more  than  25  units  when  he/she

                                            enrolls in succeeding semester.

                                                   A  student  who  re-enrolls  in  the  university  after  a

                                            disqualification for a  semester (may) shall not incur failure in 50%


                                            of the enrolled subjects upon return. A disqualification of another

                                            semester will be melted out for obtaining the failing grades.
                                                   A  student  who  obtains  grades  of  “Inc”  or  “4.00”  a


                                            combination in 100% of subjects registered shall not be allowed to

                                            enroll  in  any  subject  in  the  succeeding  semester  but  shall  be

                                            advised  to  enroll  on  residency  to  complete  all  the  course

                                            requirements.


                                     2.  Student who has 21 units or fewer academic units remaining in their

                                         curriculum will be allowed to re-enroll despite reaching the academic

                                         deficiency limits.

                                     3.  No  readmission  of  disqualified  students  shall  be  considered  by  the

                                         Office of the University Registrar without favorable recommendation of




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                         the  Readmission  Committee  composed  of  the  College  Registrar  as

                                         chairman,  the  guidance  counselor,  the  chairman  of  the  department


                                         where they are enrolled and one faculty member designated by the

                                         College Dean concerned as members.

                                     4.  The  Office  of  the  University  Registrar  shall  notify  the  student  of  his

                                         academic  deficiency  status  every  end  of  the  semester  or  before

                                         enrollment.

                                     The Admission Policies are discussed during the campaign activities of

                              the Office of Student Affairs and Services while the retention policies are part of


                              the orientation programs held every start of the school semesters.


                            ➢  Present  the  summary  of  enrolment,  transferees  (incoming  and  outgoing),
                                course  shifters,  returning  students,  drop-outs  and  graduates  per  semester  in
                                the last 6 terms.
                                See Trece Enrollment History

                            ➢  Describe other Student Services.
                                See Annual Reports

                            ➢  Present the number of students per field of specialization (if applicable)
                                See Trece Enrollment History

                            ➢  Describe policies and guidelines on academic scholarships, grants and other
                                forms of financial assistance.

                            SCHOLARSHIP and FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE SERVICES

                                   One of the development targets of the University for 2009-2012 is to attract

                            the best and brightest students in the country.

                                   The  CvSU  continue  to  provide  quality  education  to  deserving  and

                            underprivileged  high  school  graduates  and  to  all  its  qualified  students.  The

                            Financial Assistance and Scholarship Programs of the Cavite State University is


                            designed  to  provide  the better  benefits  to  qualified  and  underprivileged  students

                            who meet the scholarship and financial assistance requirements of the University.





                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                            Incorporated in this program are other types of financial assistance to deserving

                            students.


                                     Objectives

                                            a.  to  attract  the  best  and  brightest  secondary  education

                                                graduated to study in CvSU; and

                                            b.  to provide the scholarship and financial assistance to qualified

                                                and underprivileged students.

                              Student Financial Assistance

                                         •  Included in this portion is the overall student financial assistance


                                            program of the University. Any revision thereof shall be approved

                                            by the Board of Regents.

                                         •  The  Financial  Assistance  Services  Unit  of  the  Office  of  Student

                                            Affairs  shall  be  responsible  for  the  implementation  of  the

                                            University Student Financial Assistance Program.


                                         •  Listed  are  the  current  types  of  scholarship/financial  assistance

                                            offered by the University.

                                     Other  types  of  financial  assistance  may  be  implemented  later  upon

                              approval by the Board of Regents.

                              a.     CvSU  State  Scholarship.  This  scholarship  is  awarded  to  financially


                                     deserving  students  who  excel  in  academic  performance.  The  grant  is

                                     classified as full and partial. In order to avail the full and partial grant, the

                                     students shall have a Grade Point Average (GPA) of 1.50 or better, and

                                     1.51 to 1.75 respectively.

                              b.     Honorific  or  Academic  Scholarship.    This  scholarship  is  awarded  to

                                     students whose Grade Point Average (GPA) is lower than 1.75 and with

                                     no failing or incomplete grade(s) in the preceding semester. The grant is




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     classified as full scholars with GPA of 1.50 or better and partial scholars

                                     with  GPA  of  1.75-1.51.  Valedictorians  and  salutatorians  are  considered


                                     entrance  scholars  and  are  entitled  full  scholarship.  Honor  graduated

                                     maybe  consider  partial  scholars  depending  on  the  class  size  of

                                     graduating class.

                              c.     Private Scholarships. This is granted to students who are selected and

                                     sponsored by private individuals and organizations. The continuance or

                                     the default of scholarship is at the discretion of the sponsor.

                              d.     Endowed Scholarship. This is a scholarship set up when donors provide


                                     grant  money  or  raise  a  certain  amount,  which  will  be  the  principal  of

                                     scholarship fund. The earning of the endowment the utilized to support

                                     scholarship grants. The fund is managed by the office in charge of the

                                     University Development Fund/Office of the Student Affairs.

                              e.     Student Assistantship. This is a grant available to students who desire


                                     to render service to the University and receive remuneration for services

                                     while studying. The allowable number of hours of work service shall be

                                     maximum of 100.

                              f.     Service  Scholarship.  This  is  a  program  which  provides  free  tuition  or

                                     tuition discount to students who have rendered service to the University

                                     as members of the varsity team. CvSu band and sociocultural, senior staff

                                     of  student  publication,  officer  of  the  University  Central  Student


                                     Government and first class ROTC Cadet Officers.

                              g.     Job Experience Program (formerly known as Work for Tuition). This

                                     is  a  form  of  student  assistance  extended  to  financially  handicapped

                                     students  so  they  can  enroll  in  a  particular  course  and  pay  the

                                     corresponding  school  fees  incurred  for  the  semester  through  work




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     services rendered to the University. The number of work service depends

                                     on the amount of fees discounted.


                              h.     Government  Scholarship.  This  is  a  scholarship  given  to  any  student

                                     under  the  Philippine  Veteran  Affairs  (PVA),  R.A.  7160,  PD  577,  DND-

                                     CHED-PASUC,  AFP-Educational  Benefit  System  and  other  similar

                                     recognized  government  scholarship  honored  by  the  University  upon

                                     presentation of the necessary credentials.

                              i.     CvSU Scholarship Privilege. This scholarship is awarded to employees

                                     of the University and their dependents provided that such employee have


                                     rendered  at  least  one  year  of  continuous  service  to  the  University,

                                     irrespective of their employment status.

                       •      In general, the criteria in the selection of financial awardees include: good moral

                              character; economic background of parents and guardians; willingness to work;

                              and academic performance. The University shall promulgate the details of criteria


                              and the mechanics of implementation and revise the same accordingly, as the

                              need arises.

                       •      The benefits to the awardees of the financial assistance program include: either

                              free tuition or discounts in tuition.

                       •      Monthly stipend; allowance per semester; book allowance and other. In addition,


                              some  types  of  financial  assistance  include  priority  booking  in  the  University

                              Dormitory.

                       •      The  responsibilities  of  the  recipients  include  maintaining  high  academic

                              standards; and also rendering some types of service work to the University. The

                              university shall issue from time to time, update guidelines on these aspects of the


                              program.






                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                       •      The  financial  assistance  is  automatically  terminated  if  a  student  recipient  is

                              involved in any misdemeanor in contravention of the University Student’s Norm


                              of  Conduct  or  any  other  university  policies,  rules  and  regulation.  In  addition,

                              student recipients who grades fall below the required academic requirement by

                              the type of financial assistance shall also forfeit the benefits and/or allowances.

                       Selection Criteria

                              This  section  will  discuss  the  requirements  and  procedure  for  each  type  of

                       scholarship.  There  will  be  three  (3)  kinds  of  applicants.  1.  Incoming  freshmen/new


                       students, 2. Old students 3. Graduate students:

                       A.     For Incoming Freshmen

                              a.     All applicant must submit the following:

                                     1.  Accomplished application form for scholarship;

                                     2.  Photocopy of Form 138 (Report Card);

                                     3.  Photocopy of the certification of good moral character issued by the


                                         school heads/guidance counselor;

                                     4.  Photocopy of checklist of course;

                                     5.  1 pc. 2x2 colored picture (any background color);

                                     6.  1 pc. short  ordinary folder;

                                     7.  Photocopy of registration form;

                                     8.  Specific Requirements:

                              b.     Photocopy of certification issued by the principal or guidance counselor


                                     that  the  applicant  is  a  high  school  valedictorian  or  salutatorian  with  at

                                     least 30 graduating students;

                                            (For Entrance Scholarship Applicants only)










                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                              c.     Photocopy  of  the  combined  annual  family  income  not  exceeding  P

                                     137,000.00  or  affidavit  of  non-filling  of  tax  from  the  Bureau  of  Internal


                                     Revenue (BIR);

                                            (For  CvSu  State  Scholarship  and  Job  Experience  Program

                                            applicants only)

                              d.     Photocopy of birth certificate;

                                            (For  CvSu  Scholarship  Privilege  and  RA  7160  (dependents  of

                                            barangay officials, applicants only)

                              e.     Photocopy  of  Certification  of  Employment/Service  Record  of  the


                                     parent/spouse from the University Personnel;

                                            (For CvSu Scholarship Privilege applicants only)

                              f.     Photocopy  of  certification  as  Barangay  Officials/SK  Officials  from  the

                                     Department of Interior and Local Government;

                                     (For RA 7160 (dependents of barangay officials and SK     officials


                              applicants only)

                       I.     The  applicants  for  CvSu  State  Scholarship  should  pass  the  examination  to

                              qualify  for  said  scholarship.  The  examination  is  administered  by  the  Guidance

                              Services Unit of OSA.

                       II.    The  applicant  for  CvSu  State  Scholarship  and  Job  Experience  Program  shall

                              undergo thorough evaluation and interview which will be conducted by the Dean

                              of Student Affairs and the Head of Scholarship/Financial Assistance Service Unit


                       B. For Old Students

                       a.     The applicants must submit the following:

                                     a.     Accomplished application form for scholarship;

                                     b.     Photocopy  of  certification  of  grades  in  the  preceding  semester

                                            from the Office of the University Registrar;




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     c.     Photocopy of the certification of good moral character issued by

                                            the college guidance counselor/college registrar;


                                     d.     Photocopy of checklist of course;

                                     e.     Photocopy of pre-registration form;

                                     f.     1 pc. 2x2 colored picture (any background color);

                                     g.     1 pcs. short ordinary folder;

                                     h.     Specific Requirements;

                       b.     Photocopy of the combined annual family income not exceeding P137,000.00 or

                              affidavit of non-filling of tax from the Bureau of Internal Revenue (BIR);


                                     (For Job Experience Program applicants only)

                       c.     Photocopy of birth certificate;

                                     (For CvSU Scholars only)

                       d.     Photocopy of Certification of Employment/Service Record of the parent/spouse

                              from the University Personnel;


                                     (For CvSu Scholarship Privilege applicants only)

                       e.     Photocopy of certification as Barangay Officials/SK Officials from the Department

                                         of Interior and Local Government;

                                     (For  RA  7160  (dependents  of  barangay  officials  and  SK  officials

                              applicants only)

                       B. For Graduate Students

                              The applicants must submit the following:


                              1.     Accomplished application form for scholarship;

                              2.     Photocopy of Transcript of Records;

                              3.     Photocopy of birth certificate (if unmarried);

                              4.     Photocopy of marriage contract;

                              5.     Photocopy of checklist of course;




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                              6.     1 pc. 2x2 colored picture (any background color)

                              7.     1 pc. short ordinary folder;


                              8.     Photocopy  of  Certification  of  Employment  of  the  employee  form  the

                                     Human Resource Management Office Director.


                            ➢  Describe fund generation scheme for scholarships and grants.

                                     The office of Student Affairs also aims generate funds for students who


                              wants to be scholar through linkages of the agencies having the following types

                              of  scholarship  programs:  CvSu  State  Scholarship,  Academic  Scholarship,

                              Entrance/Honorific, Students Assistantship, Job Experience Program, Employee

                              Dependent, Service Scholarship, RA 7160, PVAO Government, PD 577, DOST,

                              DND  CHED  PASUC,  Cong.  BoyingRemulla  Scholarship,  Cavite  Provincial


                              Scholarship, KGMA Scholarship in the province of Cavite.

                                     The  Office  of  Student  Affairs  also  have  linkages  through  Private

                              Scholarship programs such as: Hawwel Chemical, Inc. Indang Community Group

                              of Northern California, Mrs. Netia Vida Obong and Teofilo Vida Jr. Scholarship.

                              PAGCOR, JR Remulla Scholarship Foundation, Jollibee Food Corp. Scholarship

                              Foundation,  Phil.  Rural  Reconstruction  Movement  (PRRM),  Gen.  Mission


                              Scholarship Grant, Rotary Club of Tagaytay and PoncianoTuafio Scholarship.

                            ➢  List of scholarship grants/financial assistance available.


                              Number of Scholarship/            No. of Student-       Amount of Grant per
                                                                  Recipients
                                  Grant/Assistance                                   Student per Academic
                                                                                              Term

                         1.Academic Scholars                 166                   Various


                         2.Tulong Dunong                     10                     6,000

                         3.TES/ESGPPA/4Ps                    96                    20,000





                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE






               3. OUTCOMES

                            ➢  Cite  evidences/manifestations  that  institutional  programs  and  services  help
                                develop students’ potentials.

                              a.  The  different  scholarships  and  financial  assistance  of  the  University  gave

                                 opportunities to indigent but deserving students to avail affordable yet quality

                                 college  education.  The  scholarship  programs  available  include  entrance


                                 scholarship,  academic  scholarship,  CvSU  state  scholarship,  service

                                 scholarship, employee dependent or CvSU scholarship privilege, government

                                 and private scholarship. Meanwhile, financial assistance programs are also

                                 available such Job Experience program and student assistantship program.

                                 Even  the  graduate  students  can  benefit  from  the  said  financial  assistance.


                                 Some  MS  Biology  students  are  scholars  under  the  CvSu  scholarship.

                                 Moreover,  students  under  scholarship  programs  prove  that  they  stood  out

                                 amount the other students, thus they are motivated to challenge themselves

                                 to reach higher goals in life.

                              b.  The  CvSU  Health  Service  is  responsible  in  delivering  the  basic  health

                                 services  such  as  diagnostic,  test,  first  aid,  prevention  and  prophylaxis  and

                                 physical and dental exams. Both freshmen and old students are required to


                                 undergo medical and well-being of students. Hence, the physical and dental

                                 health of every student is an integral component of learning, growing, thriving

                                 and succeeding to their chosen endeavor.

                              c.  The  culture  and  arts  programs  of  the  University  through  the  different  non-

                                 academic student organizations (socio-cultural organization) are of great help


                                 to students by providing the opportunities to showcase and share their artistic

                                 talents. These include the CvSU Choral Ensembles, PandayangSining, Prime





                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 Moverz and others. Their different activities help them to promote their self-

                                 esteem,  develop  their  creativity,  improve  emotional  expression  and


                                 developed good camaraderie and social harmony to others.

                                     The student offices for culture and arts, sports development and student

                              publication are provided by the University. If facilitates the use of the University

                              resources and empower them in their provision of service. This serves as venue

                              for meeting, planning and the conduct of their own student activities.

               4. BEST PRACTICES

                            ➢  Cite as many best practices as you can on Parameter D (Institutional Student
                                Programs and Services).

                              a.  The University offers several types of scholarship and financial assistances

                                 where deserving students, particularly from low income family can avail it to


                                 enroll and pursue their education

                              b.  Policies  on  admission,  selection  and  retention  guidelines,  scholarship  and

                                 financial  assistance,  student  activities  and  organization  membership  and

                                 student norm of conduct are disseminated through orientation programs, print

                                 material and using the university website.

                              c.  Tracer study on graduates is conducted

                              d.  Retention policies on courses with board/licensure examination are approved


                                 by BOR/BOT.

                              e.  Operators of the food outlets within the University secured Sanitary Permits

                                 and Health Certificate from the local government. University Personnel are in-

                                 charged to check and maintain the cleanliness of the vicinity around the food

                                 outlets.


                              f.  The University Infirmary are administered by all licensed medical, dental and

                                 allied professionals.





                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     Student  records  (health  records,  guidance  records  and  admission

                                records) are filed and well-stored.





















































                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




               PARAMETER E – RESEARCH, MONITORING AND EVALUATION


               1. SYSTEM-INPUTS AND PROCESSES

                            ➢  Present  institutional  policies  on  research  program  on  student  affairs  and
                                services.

                                       The  Research,  Monitoring  and  Evaluation  of  Student  Services

                                (RMESS) shall serve as feedback mechanism on the effectiveness of Student

                                Affairs and Services and shall serve as evaluation tool to evaluate curricular

                                programs through the conduct of graduate tracer studies. Research results and

                                outputs shall be disseminated and utilized in improving curricular and student


                                services programs of the university.

                                Section 1. Monitoring and evaluation of delivery student services Routine and

                                periodic  monitoring  and  evaluation  shall  be  conducted  by  RMESS  in  the

                                following student services:

                                     1.1.1  Admission Services


                                                   Admission  services  shall  be  evaluated  based  on  client

                                            satisfaction  ratings  on  personnel  student  recruitment,  selection

                                            and admission;

                                     1.1.2  Orientation and Information

                                                   Monitoring  and  evaluation  of  regular  comprehensive

                                            orientation program shall be conducted. Information service shall

                                            be evaluated based on the availability/accessibility of information


                                            materials on education, career, personal and social concerns.

                                 1.2 Guidance and Counseling

                                            The guidance and counseling service shall be evaluated based on

                                     the following:

                                     1.2.1  Personnel qualifications




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     1.2.2  Facilities

                                     1.2.3  Information and Inventory


                                     1.2.4  Individual and group counseling

                                     1.2.5  Appraisal and testing

                                     1.2.6  Placement and follow up

                                     1.2.7  Referral

                                     1.2.8  Client satisfaction rating

                                 1.3 Financial Assistance and Scholarship

                                            Quarterly report on financial assistance and scholarship shall be


                                     made  available.  Comparative  data  on  financial  assistance  and

                                     scholarship grants for last five years shall be made.

                                 1.4 Job Placement

                                            Evaluating of job placement service shall be based on continuous

                                     active  networking  with  schools  and  communities,  alumni  and  other


                                     concerned agencies for career and job placement students. Annual report

                                     on job placement of graduates shall be made available.

                                 1.5 Student Publication

                                            Student  publication  shall  be  evaluated  based  on  compliance  to

                                     Journalism. Act, adherence to editorial policies, number of released made

                                     per semester and client satisfaction ratings.

                                 1.6 Student Organizations


                                            A system of recognition, accreditation, monitoring and evaluation

                                     shall be implemented on the following:

                                            1.7.1.  Central Student Government

                                            1.7.2.  Student Council

                                            1.7.3.  Academic and non-academic organizations




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                 1.7 NSTP (CWTS, ROTC) and community service

                                            NSTP  programs  shall  be  evaluated  based  on  its  compliance  to


                                     implementing  rules  and  guidelines  of  NSTP  and  impact  assessment

                                     ratings of extension projects.

                                 1.8 Registration

                                            Clientele  satisfaction  ratings  shall  be  considered  in  evaluating

                                     registration services.

                                 1.9 Library Services

                                            Monitoring  and  evaluation  of  library  services  shall  be  based  on


                                     library  acquisition,  number  of  library  users,  compliance  to  accreditation

                                     requirements and clientele satisfaction ratings.

                                 1.10 Laboratory

                                            Availability of required laboratories per curricular program shall be

                                     determined. Client satisfaction ratings on the use of laboratories shall be


                                     measured.

                                 1.11 Health and Medical Services

                                            Health  and  medical  services  shall  be  evaluated  based  on

                                     available facilities and client satisfaction ratings.

                                 1.12 Culture and Arts Program

                                            The  culture  and  arts  program  shall  be  evaluated  based  on  the

                                     number and quality of performances as evaluated by their audience. Each


                                     performing  group  shall  undergo  accreditation  by  OSAS  as  another

                                     measure of their performance.

                                 1.13 Sports and Wellness

                                            Sports  and  wellness  program  shall  be  evaluated  based  on  the

                                     number  and  type  of  sports  activities,  degree  of  participation,  relevance




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE




                                     and  impact  of  policies  on  wellness  and  healthy  lifestyle,  available

                                     mechanism to promote national, sectoral and cultural sports activities.


                                 1.14 Safety and Security

                                            Safety  and  security  services  shall  be  evaluated  based  on

                                     qualifications  of  security  personnel,  interventions  for  crime  prevention,

                                     observance of cleanliness and orderliness, safety and security measures

                                     imposed, reports on number and degree of student violations.

                                 1.15 Student Housing

                                            A  classification  system  to  facilitate  endorsement  of  dormitories


                                     and boarding houses outside the University shall be implemented. Criteria

                                     for classification and evaluation of dormitories shall be based on building

                                     and facility requirements for boarding houses and dormitories.

                                 1.16 Food Services

                                            Periodic  Inspection  of  the  safety  and  sanitation  of  food  service


                                     establishments shall be conducted. Acceptability and availability of food

                                     choices and price shall be monitored and evaluated.

                                 1.17 Multi-faith

                                            Multi-faith  shall  be  evaluated  based  on  the  number  of  clients

                                     served and client satisfaction ratings.

                              Section 4.1.  Implementation of Institutional Graduate Trace Studies

                              Section 4.2.  Conduct of other relevant and responsive researches on student


                                            affairs and services.



               2. IMPLEMENTATION

                            ➢  Present completed researches on student affairs and services.

                                See Researches on Student Affairs and Services




                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE





                            ➢  Cite evidences that research results and outputs are disseminated and utilized.

                                     Results  on  the  evaluation  of  the  adequacy  of  CvSU  Student  Services

                              were  disseminated  to  the  different  units  to  give  them  an  idea  on  what

                              interventions and appropriate strategies they can do to further improve the quality

                              of services rendered to the students. A cover letter was attached to the summary

                              of  the  evaluation  and  a  receiving  copy  was  secured  to  make  sure  that  the


                              respective unit acknowledged the said results.


               3. OUTCOMES

                            ➢  Present evidences that research outputs are presented and published.
                                See Researches on Student Affairs and Services


               4. BEST PRACTICES

                            ➢  Cite as many best practices as you can on Parameter E (Research, Monitoring
                                and Evaluation).

                              a)  There  is  a  regular  monitoring  and  evaluation  of  student  services  in  the

                                 University.

                              b)  The  results  of  the  evaluation  of  the  student  services  are  disseminated  to

                                 concerned offices to be used as basis for the  improvement of their student

                                 services.




















                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page><page Index="99"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMANCE PROFILE









               5. EXTENT  of  COMPLIANCE  with  the  Team  Recommendations  for  Area  IV  –  Support  to
                  Students in the last
                                 Survey Visit.

                            ➢  Present the status of Compliance Matrix of Area IV focusing on  interventions
                                done on the recommendations.

                                Duly Accomplished Self-Survey Instrument

                            ➢  Present the Summary of Findings and Recommendations for Area IV (Support
                                                                                  st
                                                                                             nd
                                                                                                        rd
                                to Students) during the __________((Preliminary, 1  Survey, 2  Survey, 3
                                           th
                                Survey, or 4  Survey) in terms of:

                                1. Strengths
                                2. Areas Needing Improvement
                                3. Recommendations

                                4. Present the Summary of Ratings on the quantitative assessment on Area IV.













































                     Area IV: Support to Students]]></page></pages></Search>