<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Search><pages Count="251"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                    AREA IV: SUPPORT TO STUDENTS












                                       PARAMETER E.



                 RESEARCH, MONITORING AND



                                          EVALUATION












                              SYSTEM-INPUTS AND



                                          PROCESSES

















              S.1.   The institution has a research


                             program on student affairs and

                             services.

















                      Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="17"/><page Index="18"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[SOCIAL MEDIA, LEARNING STYLES AND ACADEMIC PERFORMANCE OF STUDENTS:
               BASIS  FOR ENHANCEMENT OF GUIDANCE AND COUNSELING PROGRAM AT CAVITE
                                                 STATE  UNIVERSITY

                                                 Charise Mae D. Galve
                                       Master of Education Major in Guidance and
                                    Counseling  Cavite State University-Main Campus
                                                    November, 2019





                                                      ABSTRACT

                   The  world  today  is  celebrating  the  improvements  in  communication  technology  which  has

           broadened  the  scope  of  communication  through  Information  and  Communication  Technologies

           (ICTs).  Modern Technology in communication no doubt has turned the entire world into a “Global

           village”  (Asemah and Edegoh, 2012). ). Hence, this research was done to find out the social media,

           learning  styles  and  academic  performance  among  the  students  of T3  campuses  of  Cavite  State


           University,  namely, Trece Martires City, Tanza and General Trias in order to establish a basis for

           enhancement  of     guidance  and  counseling  program..  The  descriptive-comparative  method  of

           research  was  utilized  that  investigated  and  described  the  relationship  between  variables  in  their

           natural setting without  manipulation.

                   Results of the study showed that in general, majority of students used Facebook (81.7 %),

           YouTube (50.7 %), and Google+ (26.0 %) while the use of Blogspot and Wordress or Joomla was


           only  one. The mean and standard deviation of not using Google + (M=2.05, SD = 0.024) and using

           Google+   (M=1.91, SD =0.039).The computed t-value was 3.056 with a p-value of 0.002 which is

           significant at

           0.05 level. This suggests that using Google+ as a social media platform has a significant effect on


           the  academic performance of the student.

                   The  findings  also  showed  the  significant  difference  of  Academic  Performance  of  the
                   participants
           and their Learning Styles using F-test, the computed value was 3.190 and with the p-value of 0.005,

           significant at 0.05 level.




            Keywords: Social Media, Learning Styles, Academic Performance, Guidance and
            Counseling]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






                                                               ISSN: 2591-7064
                                                               Vol. 3, No. 2A, Feb. 2019




















































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                      Page 1 of 663
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






























































                                                        Funded by
                                  Joint Multidisciplinary Research Conferences  Joint
                                     Multidisciplinary Research Conferences Plus
                                         Multidisciplinary Research Festivals


                                                       Available at
                                             www.ascendensasia.com/ojs
                                            www.aaresearchindex.com/ojs


                                                       Published by
                                               Ascendens Asia Pte.Ltd.





                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts


                  Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts

                  Volume 3                                                              Number 2A




                  February 2019


                  Research               Advocacy               for          Community

                  Empowerment              (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary

                  Research Poster  Exhibition Abstract Proceedings

































                  ISSN: 2591-7064


                  Recommended Citation

                  (February 2019) "Research Advocacy for Community Empowerment (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary
                  Research Poster Exhibition Abstract Proceedings," Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts, Vol.3, No.2A. Available at: "http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA".



                  The Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts (AAJMRA) is a collection of abstracts of research
                  papers presented during Multidisciplinary Research Fests (MRFs) mainly organised by Ascendens Asia Singapore as well
                  as other research conferences in collaboration with various institutions and learned societies. MRFs provide  opportunities
                  for collaboration with a common prime objective of creating platforms for students, faculty, staff, and  researchers-alike
                  from  different  institutions  to  interrelate/interact  with  their  counterparts.  MRFs,  are  expected  to  aide  and  promote
                  personality development and critical thinking as participants engage themselves in constructive discussions  with other
                  participating researchers.

                  AAJMRAs are made available complimentary and for open access by Ascendens Asia Singapore. For more information,
                  please contact publications@ascendensasia.com.




                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts



                  Copyright &


                  Copyright© 2019
                  Copyright  for  the  texts  which  include  all  issues  of  Ascendens  Asia  Journal  of  Multidisciplinary  Research
                  Disclaimer                                                                 individuals;
                  Abstracts are held by the AAMJRA, except if otherwise noted. The compilation as a whole is Copyright©  by
                  AAMJRA,  all  rights  reserved.  Items  published  by  AAMJRA  may  be  generously  shared  among
                  however, they may NOT be republished in any medium without express written consent  from the author(s)
                  and advance notification of the AAMJRA Editorial Board. For permission to reprint  articles published in the
                  AAMJRA, please contact the Editorial Board at  publications@ascendensasia.com.

                  Disclaimer
                  Facts and opinions published in Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts  (AAMJRA)
                  express solely the opinions of the respective authors. Authors are responsible for their citing  of sources and the
                  accuracy of their references and bibliographies. The editors cannot be held responsible  for any lack or possible
                  violations of third parties' rights. Interested parties may also directly contact  authors to request for full copies
                  of the journal proceedings.































































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                       Page 16 of
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA                                  632]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                  Collaborative  Learning and Skills Development of Grade 10 Students:  Basis for  Achievement
                  in Mathematics                                                                    60
                  Adrian Ramos, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LIPAC1-0085

                  Collaborative Learning: A Strategy in Reducing the Academic Anxiety among 8th Grade
                  Learners                                                                          61
                  Diana Hinahon & Patrick Sulibaga, Naic NHS
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0983
                  Collaborative Learning: Its Effect to the Performance in Mathematics of Grade 9 Students   62
                  Cleo Mae Castaneda, Linga National High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LAGUNA-0130
                  Collaborative Mind Mapping in Enhancing Pupils' Academic Achievement in Science 6   63
                  Arcedel Pagana, Department of Education - Tayabas
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-TAYABA-0003

                  Collaborative Professional Learning through Lesson Study: A tool to Improve Science 9
                  Classroom Instruction                                                             64
                  Lorna Gayla, Looc Integrated School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CALAMB-0428
                  Collaborative Reading Enhancement Activities Towards Excellence                   65
                  Amelia Panganiban, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0514

                  Collaborative Strategy in Teaching Filipino in Lemery Senior High School (Kolaboratibong
                  Estratehiya Sa Pagtuturo Ng Asignaturang Filipino Sa Lemery Senior High School)  Jennifer   66
                  Mendoza, Lemery Senior High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANP-0961
                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      67
                  Norielyn Bernarte & Rosabel Berania, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529

                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      68
                  Norielyn Bernarte, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529
                  Collaborative  Use of  Technological Resources in Teaching Mathematics for Public
                  Elementary Schools Municipality of Amadeo                                         69
                  Clarice A. Sarmiento
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0635

                  Collaborative-Programmed-Discovery   Method:   An   Intervention   to   Improve   the
                  Mathematics Performance of Grade Ix Students of Jose Rizal National High School   70
                  Earl Abad, Teacher
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-COTABP-0001
                  College and Career Readiness of Senior High School: Basis for Comprehensive Guidance
                  Program                                                                           71
                  Junrey Villa, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-GENSAN-0007

                  College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records: Bases of Student
                  Academic Performance in a State University                                        72
                  Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059






                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                       2
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                                College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records:
                                   Bases of Student Academic Performance in a State University

                                         Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece


                                                        Abstract


                  INTRODUCTION
                  An  entrance  examination  is  an  examination  that  many  educational  institutions  use  to  select  students  for
                  admission. These  exams may  be administered at  any level  of  education,  from primary to  higher  education,
                  although  they  are  more  common  at  higher  levels.  It  was  in  the  school  year  1997-1998  when  the  school
                  decided to use the standardized test of the CEM. After a few administrations, it was found out that none  was
                  able to pass the test or hardly reached an expected score. Due to fear that only a few will be qualified  to enroll
                  in  college  which  may  lead  to  bankruptcy,  the  school  decided  to  stop  the  administration  of  the    said
                  standardized test by the CEM and returned to using the teacher-made test.

                  METHODS
                  The  study  used  correlational  research  method.  The  method  was  used  to  investigate  the  extent  to  which
                  variations in one factor such as the first year college academic performance correlate with variations in  one
                  or more other factors such as college entrance exam results and high school scholastic records based  on the
                  correlation  coefficient.  The  primary  data  were  obtained  through  the  entrance  exam  results,  high    school
                  scholastic records, and college academic grades from the Office of the Campus Registrar.

                  RESULTS
                  College entrance exam results of students have fairly satisfactory results. Participant's high school  scholastic
                  records and academic performance in college are satisfactory.  There is a significant difference  between the
                  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  in  students'  academic  performance  in
                  college. The F-ratio of 46.36 is greater than the F critical value for .05 level of 3.01. The  computed F-ratio
                  being  greater  than  the  tabulated  F-ratio  means  that  the  null  hypothesis  is  rejected.    Rejecting  the  null
                  hypothesis further proves that college entrance exam results and high school scholastic  records are significant
                  to student's academic performance in college.

                  DISCUSSIONS
                  The  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  are  significant  to  student's  academic
                  performance in college. According to the Campus Registrar, high school records could be a determinant  of
                  college  entrance  exam  since  the  students  had  their  high  school  for  four  years  and  the  entrance  exam
                  measures  their  gained  knowledge  from  their  previous  education.  It  may  also  the  reason  why  the  college
                  entrance exam could also be a determinant of first-year college grades since they are in the adjustment  period
                  from at least four years in high school.

                  KEYWORDS: entrance exam, scholastic record, academic performance

                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059
























                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                      72
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                    AREA IV: SUPPORT TO STUDENTS












                                       PARAMETER E.



                 RESEARCH, MONITORING AND



                                          EVALUATION












                              SYSTEM-INPUTS AND



                                          PROCESSES

















              S.2.   There is mechanism for


                             monitoring and evaluation of

                             SAS programs.

















                      Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[1                                  Republic of the Philippines
           2                           CAVITE STATE UNIVERSITY
           3                      TanzaǀTrece Martires Cityǀ Gen. Trias City Campus
           4                           414-3979   ǀ(0977)8033809   ǀ509-4148
           5                                       www.cvsu.edu.ph
           6
           7                           TRECE MARTIRES CITY CAMPUS


           8      MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF KEY OFFICIALS HELD AT READING ROOM, CvSU
           9                   TRECE MARTIRES CITY CAMPUS ON 01 AUGUST  2019



          10   I. CALL TO ORDER AND ATTENDANCE
          11          The OSAS Head, Ms. Lilian O. Sidamon, formally called to order the meeting of the
          12   Department at 1:30 pm. A quorum was declared with one (1) Curriculum Development & (3)
          13   Instruction Heads, Guidance Coordinator, Registrar, Campus Nurse and (4) Student
          14   Organization heads.
          15
          16   Lilian O. Sidamon            Presiding Officer
          17   Vienna Mi A. Feranil
          18   Cristza de Ocampo-Manlapig
          19   Keno A. Villavicencio
          20   Arlene, Estrada
          21   Gideon Luke Ty
          22   Gwena Rochelle G. Lontoc
          23   Mary Ann L. Anonas
          24   Robert O. Peligrino
          25   Joseph Fortaleza
          26   Junie T. Gaspar
          27   Prince Julius Elsisura
          28
          29   II. AGENDA OF THE MEETING
          30          The OSAS Coordinator presented the agenda of the meeting as follows:
          31
          32          Dissemination of Evaluation of Adequacy and Efficiency of Student
          33          Services and Facilities
          34
                      Discuss the results Adequacy of Student Services in terms of Admission Services,
          35
                      Registration/Enrolment Services, Orientation Program, Security Service, Library
          36
                      Services, Laboratory Facilities, Comfort Rooms, Dressing Areas, Drinking Water,
          37
                      Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-Visual Facilities,
          38
                      Handwashing  areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen, Sports and Physical
          39
                      Fitness  Services, Student Publication, Student Organizations, Alumni Associations,
          40
                      NSTP,  Printing Services and Facilities and Dormitory
          41
                      Discuss the results Efficiency of Student Services in terms of Admission Services,
          42
                      Registration/Enrolment Services, Orientation Program, Security Service, Library
          43
                      Services, Laboratory Facilities, Comfort Rooms, Dressing Areas, Drinking Water,
          44
                      Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-Visual Facilities,
          45
                      Handwashing  areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen, Sports and Physical
          46
                      Fitness  Services, Student Publication, Student Organizations, Alumni Associations,
          47
                      NSTP,  Printing Services and Facilities and Dormitory]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[48          Other Matters
          49
          50       A. Dissemination of Evaluation of Adequacy and Efficiency of Student Services
          51          and Facilities
          52
          53              Ms.  Sidamon  discussed  the  contents  of  the  survey  on  Evaluation  of  Adequacy
          54       and  Efficiency  of  student  Services  and  Facilities.  It  is  a  five-point  questionnaire  on
          55       adequacy  ranging  from:  more  than  adequate,  moderately  adequate,  fairly  adequate
          56       slightly adequate and inadequate. Efficiency ranges from more than efficient, moderately
          57       efficient, fairly  efficient, slightly  efficient  and  in  efficient.  The  survey  questionnaire  was
          58       given to 5 students per section across courses.

          59       B.  Discuss  the  results  Adequacy  of  Student  Services  in  terms  of
          60          Admission  Services,  Registration/Enrolment  Services,  Orientation
          61          Program,  Security  Service,  Library  Services,  Laboratory  Facilities,
          62          Comfort  Rooms,  Dressing  Areas,  Drinking  Water,  Guidance  and
          63          Counseling,  Assembly  Facilities,  Audio-Visual  Facilities,  Handwashing
          64          areas,  Health  Services,  Food  Services/Canteen,  Sports  and  Physical
          65          Fitness  Services,  Student  Publication,  Student  Organizations,  Alumni
          66          Associations,     NSTP,     Printing   Services     and    Facilities   and
          67          DormitoryDiscuss the BSBM and BSHRM/BSHM Program Outcomes
          68
          69              Ms. Sidamon discussed that among the facilities and services provided by Cvsu
          70       Trece, the orientation program gave a very adequate feedback from students while there
          71       is  only  fairly  adequate  feedback  on  lacking facilities  like  laboratories  and  audio  visual
          72       facilities. While all other services and facilities have moderate adequacy feedback.
          73
          74       C.  Discuss  the  results  Efficiency  of  Student  Services  in  terms  of  Admission
          75          Services,  Registration/Enrolment  Services,  Orientation  Program,  Security
          76          Service,  Library  Services,  Laboratory  Facilities,  Comfort  Rooms,  Dressing
          77          Areas, Drinking Water, Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-
          78
                      Visual Facilities, Handwashing areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen,
          79          Sports  and  Physical  Fitness  Services,  Student  Publication,  Student
          80          Organizations, Alumni Associations, NSTP, Printing Services and Facilities and
          81
                      Dormitory
          82
          83
                              Ms.  Sidamon  discussed  that  among  the  facilities  and  services  provided  by
          84          Cvsu  Trece,  the  orientation  program  gave  the  highest  mean  with  moderately
          85
                      adequate  feedback  from  students  while  there  is  only  fairly  adequate  feedback  on
          86
                      lacking facilities like laboratories and audio visual facilities. While all other services
          87
                      and facilities have moderate adequacy feedback.
          88
          89
                   D. Other Matters
          90
          91
                              Ms. Sidamon discussed that having the aforementioned results the campus
          92
                      should focus on items with only fair adequacy and efficiency feedback such as the
          93
                      creation  and  improvement  of  laboratories.  This  should  be  recommended  by  the
          94
                      campus Budget Officer to be given allocation in the next year’s PPMP. She also said
          95
                      that a very adequate and efficient feedback should be aimed on the following year’s
          96
                      survey.
          97]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[98   III. ADJOURNMENT OF MEETING
          99          There being no other matters to discuss, the meeting was adjourned at 3:30pm.

        100    Prepared by:                                             Attested by:


        102
        103    LILIAN O. SIDAMON                                       VIENNA MI A. FERANIL
        104    OSAS Coordinator                                    Curriculum Development & Instruction Head
                                                                        Trece Campus Coordinator]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                    AREA IV: SUPPORT TO STUDENTS












                                       PARAMETER E.



                 RESEARCH, MONITORING AND



                                          EVALUATION












                              SYSTEM-INPUTS AND



                                          PROCESSES

















              S.3.   Monitoring and evaluation


                             instruments are available.




















                      Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                    AREA IV: SUPPORT TO STUDENTS












                                       PARAMETER E.



                 RESEARCH, MONITORING AND



                                          EVALUATION












                              SYSTEM-INPUTS AND



                                          PROCESSES

















              S.4.   There is adequate funding for the


                             conduct of SAS researches and

                             monitoring and evaluation.

















                      Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="99"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="100"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="101"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="102"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="103"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="104"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="105"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="106"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="107"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                    AREA IV: SUPPORT TO STUDENTS












                                       PARAMETER E.



                 RESEARCH, MONITORING AND



                                          EVALUATION












                                   IMPLEMENTATION

















              I.1.           Researches on student affairs


                             and services are conducted.

























                      Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="108"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="109"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="110"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="111"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="112"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="113"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="114"><![CDATA[SOCIAL MEDIA, LEARNING STYLES AND ACADEMIC PERFORMANCE OF STUDENTS:
               BASIS  FOR ENHANCEMENT OF GUIDANCE AND COUNSELING PROGRAM AT CAVITE
                                                 STATE  UNIVERSITY

                                                 Charise Mae D. Galve
                                       Master of Education Major in Guidance and
                                    Counseling  Cavite State University-Main Campus
                                                    November, 2019





                                                      ABSTRACT

                   The  world  today  is  celebrating  the  improvements  in  communication  technology  which  has

           broadened  the  scope  of  communication  through  Information  and  Communication  Technologies

           (ICTs).  Modern Technology in communication no doubt has turned the entire world into a “Global

           village”  (Asemah and Edegoh, 2012). ). Hence, this research was done to find out the social media,

           learning  styles  and  academic  performance  among  the  students  of T3  campuses  of  Cavite  State


           University,  namely, Trece Martires City, Tanza and General Trias in order to establish a basis for

           enhancement  of     guidance  and  counseling  program..  The  descriptive-comparative  method  of

           research  was  utilized  that  investigated  and  described  the  relationship  between  variables  in  their

           natural setting without  manipulation.

                   Results of the study showed that in general, majority of students used Facebook (81.7 %),

           YouTube (50.7 %), and Google+ (26.0 %) while the use of Blogspot and Wordress or Joomla was


           only  one. The mean and standard deviation of not using Google + (M=2.05, SD = 0.024) and using

           Google+   (M=1.91, SD =0.039).The computed t-value was 3.056 with a p-value of 0.002 which is

           significant at

           0.05 level. This suggests that using Google+ as a social media platform has a significant effect on


           the  academic performance of the student.

                   The  findings  also  showed  the  significant  difference  of  Academic  Performance  of  the
                   participants
           and their Learning Styles using F-test, the computed value was 3.190 and with the p-value of 0.005,

           significant at 0.05 level.




            Keywords: Social Media, Learning Styles, Academic Performance, Guidance and
            Counseling]]></page><page Index="115"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






                                                               ISSN: 2591-7064
                                                               Vol. 3, No. 2A, Feb. 2019




















































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                      Page 1 of 663
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="116"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






























































                                                        Funded by
                                  Joint Multidisciplinary Research Conferences  Joint
                                     Multidisciplinary Research Conferences Plus
                                         Multidisciplinary Research Festivals


                                                       Available at
                                             www.ascendensasia.com/ojs
                                            www.aaresearchindex.com/ojs


                                                       Published by
                                               Ascendens Asia Pte.Ltd.





                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="117"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts


                  Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts

                  Volume 3                                                              Number 2A




                  February 2019


                  Research               Advocacy               for          Community

                  Empowerment              (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary

                  Research Poster  Exhibition Abstract Proceedings

































                  ISSN: 2591-7064


                  Recommended Citation

                  (February 2019) "Research Advocacy for Community Empowerment (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary
                  Research Poster Exhibition Abstract Proceedings," Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts, Vol.3, No.2A. Available at: "http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA".



                  The Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts (AAJMRA) is a collection of abstracts of research
                  papers presented during Multidisciplinary Research Fests (MRFs) mainly organised by Ascendens Asia Singapore as well
                  as other research conferences in collaboration with various institutions and learned societies. MRFs provide  opportunities
                  for collaboration with a common prime objective of creating platforms for students, faculty, staff, and  researchers-alike
                  from  different  institutions  to  interrelate/interact  with  their  counterparts.  MRFs,  are  expected  to  aide  and  promote
                  personality development and critical thinking as participants engage themselves in constructive discussions  with other
                  participating researchers.

                  AAJMRAs are made available complimentary and for open access by Ascendens Asia Singapore. For more information,
                  please contact publications@ascendensasia.com.




                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="118"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts



                  Copyright &


                  Copyright© 2019
                  Copyright  for  the  texts  which  include  all  issues  of  Ascendens  Asia  Journal  of  Multidisciplinary  Research
                  Disclaimer                                                                 individuals;
                  Abstracts are held by the AAMJRA, except if otherwise noted. The compilation as a whole is Copyright©  by
                  AAMJRA,  all  rights  reserved.  Items  published  by  AAMJRA  may  be  generously  shared  among
                  however, they may NOT be republished in any medium without express written consent  from the author(s)
                  and advance notification of the AAMJRA Editorial Board. For permission to reprint  articles published in the
                  AAMJRA, please contact the Editorial Board at  publications@ascendensasia.com.

                  Disclaimer
                  Facts and opinions published in Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts  (AAMJRA)
                  express solely the opinions of the respective authors. Authors are responsible for their citing  of sources and the
                  accuracy of their references and bibliographies. The editors cannot be held responsible  for any lack or possible
                  violations of third parties' rights. Interested parties may also directly contact  authors to request for full copies
                  of the journal proceedings.































































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                       Page 13 of
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA                                  632]]></page><page Index="119"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                  Collaborative  Learning and Skills Development of Grade 10 Students:  Basis for  Achievement
                  in Mathematics                                                                    60
                  Adrian Ramos, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LIPAC1-0085

                  Collaborative Learning: A Strategy in Reducing the Academic Anxiety among 8th Grade
                  Learners                                                                          61
                  Diana Hinahon & Patrick Sulibaga, Naic NHS
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0983
                  Collaborative Learning: Its Effect to the Performance in Mathematics of Grade 9 Students   62
                  Cleo Mae Castaneda, Linga National High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LAGUNA-0130
                  Collaborative Mind Mapping in Enhancing Pupils' Academic Achievement in Science 6   63
                  Arcedel Pagana, Department of Education - Tayabas
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-TAYABA-0003

                  Collaborative Professional Learning through Lesson Study: A tool to Improve Science 9
                  Classroom Instruction                                                             64
                  Lorna Gayla, Looc Integrated School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CALAMB-0428
                  Collaborative Reading Enhancement Activities Towards Excellence                   65
                  Amelia Panganiban, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0514

                  Collaborative Strategy in Teaching Filipino in Lemery Senior High School (Kolaboratibong
                  Estratehiya Sa Pagtuturo Ng Asignaturang Filipino Sa Lemery Senior High School)  Jennifer   66
                  Mendoza, Lemery Senior High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANP-0961
                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      67
                  Norielyn Bernarte & Rosabel Berania, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529

                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      68
                  Norielyn Bernarte, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529
                  Collaborative  Use of  Technological Resources in Teaching Mathematics for Public
                  Elementary Schools Municipality of Amadeo                                         69
                  Clarice A. Sarmiento
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0635

                  Collaborative-Programmed-Discovery   Method:   An   Intervention   to   Improve   the
                  Mathematics Performance of Grade Ix Students of Jose Rizal National High School   70
                  Earl Abad, Teacher
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-COTABP-0001
                  College and Career Readiness of Senior High School: Basis for Comprehensive Guidance
                  Program                                                                           71
                  Junrey Villa, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-GENSAN-0007

                  College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records: Bases of Student
                  Academic Performance in a State University                                        72
                  Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059






                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                       2
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="120"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                                College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records:
                                   Bases of Student Academic Performance in a State University

                                         Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece


                                                        Abstract


                  INTRODUCTION
                  An  entrance  examination  is  an  examination  that  many  educational  institutions  use  to  select  students  for
                  admission. These  exams may  be administered at  any level  of  education,  from primary to  higher  education,
                  although  they  are  more  common  at  higher  levels.  It  was  in  the  school  year  1997-1998  when  the  school
                  decided to use the standardized test of the CEM. After a few administrations, it was found out that none  was
                  able to pass the test or hardly reached an expected score. Due to fear that only a few will be qualified  to enroll
                  in  college  which  may  lead  to  bankruptcy,  the  school  decided  to  stop  the  administration  of  the    said
                  standardized test by the CEM and returned to using the teacher-made test.

                  METHODS
                  The  study  used  correlational  research  method.  The  method  was  used  to  investigate  the  extent  to  which
                  variations in one factor such as the first year college academic performance correlate with variations in  one
                  or more other factors such as college entrance exam results and high school scholastic records based  on the
                  correlation  coefficient.  The  primary  data  were  obtained  through  the  entrance  exam  results,  high    school
                  scholastic records, and college academic grades from the Office of the Campus Registrar.

                  RESULTS
                  College entrance exam results of students have fairly satisfactory results. Participant's high school  scholastic
                  records and academic performance in college are satisfactory.  There is a significant difference  between the
                  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  in  students'  academic  performance  in
                  college. The F-ratio of 46.36 is greater than the F critical value for .05 level of 3.01. The  computed F-ratio
                  being  greater  than  the  tabulated  F-ratio  means  that  the  null  hypothesis  is  rejected.    Rejecting  the  null
                  hypothesis further proves that college entrance exam results and high school scholastic  records are significant
                  to student's academic performance in college.

                  DISCUSSIONS
                  The  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  are  significant  to  student's  academic
                  performance in college. According to the Campus Registrar, high school records could be a determinant  of
                  college  entrance  exam  since  the  students  had  their  high  school  for  four  years  and  the  entrance  exam
                  measures  their  gained  knowledge  from  their  previous  education.  It  may  also  the  reason  why  the  college
                  entrance exam could also be a determinant of first-year college grades since they are in the adjustment  period
                  from at least four years in high school.

                  KEYWORDS: entrance exam, scholastic record, academic performance

                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059
























                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                      72
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="121"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="122"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="123"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="124"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="125"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="126"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="127"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="128"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="129"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="130"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                    AREA IV: SUPPORT TO STUDENTS












                                       PARAMETER E.



                 RESEARCH, MONITORING AND



                                          EVALUATION












                                   IMPLEMENTATION

















              I.2.           Research results and outputs are


                             disseminated and utilized.

























                      Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="131"><![CDATA[1                                  Republic of the Philippines
           2                           CAVITE STATE UNIVERSITY
           3                      TanzaǀTrece Martires Cityǀ Gen. Trias City Campus
           4                           414-3979   ǀ(0977)8033809   ǀ509-4148
           5                                       www.cvsu.edu.ph
           6
           7                           TRECE MARTIRES CITY CAMPUS


           8      MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF KEY OFFICIALS HELD AT READING ROOM, CvSU
           9                   TRECE MARTIRES CITY CAMPUS ON 01 AUGUST  2019



          10   I. CALL TO ORDER AND ATTENDANCE
          11          The OSAS Head, Ms. Lilian O. Sidamon, formally called to order the meeting of the
          12   Department at 1:30 pm. A quorum was declared with one (1) Curriculum Development & (3)
          13   Instruction Heads, Guidance Coordinator, Registrar, Campus Nurse and (4) Student
          14   Organization heads.
          15
          16   Lilian O. Sidamon            Presiding Officer
          17   Vienna Mi A. Feranil
          18   Cristza de Ocampo-Manlapig
          19   Keno A. Villavicencio
          20   Arlene, Estrada
          21   Gideon Luke Ty
          22   Gwena Rochelle G. Lontoc
          23   Mary Ann L. Anonas
          24   Robert O. Peligrino
          25   Joseph Fortaleza
          26   Junie T. Gaspar
          27   Prince Julius Elsisura
          28
          29   II. AGENDA OF THE MEETING
          30          The OSAS Coordinator presented the agenda of the meeting as follows:
          31
          32          Dissemination of Evaluation of Adequacy and Efficiency of Student
          33          Services and Facilities
          34
                      Discuss the results Adequacy of Student Services in terms of Admission Services,
          35
                      Registration/Enrolment Services, Orientation Program, Security Service, Library
          36
                      Services, Laboratory Facilities, Comfort Rooms, Dressing Areas, Drinking Water,
          37
                      Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-Visual Facilities,
          38
                      Handwashing  areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen, Sports and Physical
          39
                      Fitness  Services, Student Publication, Student Organizations, Alumni Associations,
          40
                      NSTP,  Printing Services and Facilities and Dormitory
          41
                      Discuss the results Efficiency of Student Services in terms of Admission Services,
          42
                      Registration/Enrolment Services, Orientation Program, Security Service, Library
          43
                      Services, Laboratory Facilities, Comfort Rooms, Dressing Areas, Drinking Water,
          44
                      Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-Visual Facilities,
          45
                      Handwashing  areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen, Sports and Physical
          46
                      Fitness  Services, Student Publication, Student Organizations, Alumni Associations,
          47
                      NSTP,  Printing Services and Facilities and Dormitory]]></page><page Index="132"><![CDATA[48          Other Matters
          49
          50       A. Dissemination of Evaluation of Adequacy and Efficiency of Student Services
          51          and Facilities
          52
          53              Ms.  Sidamon  discussed  the  contents  of  the  survey  on  Evaluation  of  Adequacy
          54       and  Efficiency  of  student  Services  and  Facilities.  It  is  a  five-point  questionnaire  on
          55       adequacy  ranging  from:  more  than  adequate,  moderately  adequate,  fairly  adequate
          56       slightly adequate and inadequate. Efficiency ranges from more than efficient, moderately
          57       efficient, fairly  efficient, slightly  efficient  and  in  efficient.  The  survey  questionnaire  was
          58       given to 5 students per section across courses.

          59       B.  Discuss  the  results  Adequacy  of  Student  Services  in  terms  of
          60          Admission  Services,  Registration/Enrolment  Services,  Orientation
          61          Program,  Security  Service,  Library  Services,  Laboratory  Facilities,
          62          Comfort  Rooms,  Dressing  Areas,  Drinking  Water,  Guidance  and
          63          Counseling,  Assembly  Facilities,  Audio-Visual  Facilities,  Handwashing
          64          areas,  Health  Services,  Food  Services/Canteen,  Sports  and  Physical
          65          Fitness  Services,  Student  Publication,  Student  Organizations,  Alumni
          66          Associations,     NSTP,     Printing   Services     and    Facilities   and
          67          DormitoryDiscuss the BSBM and BSHRM/BSHM Program Outcomes
          68
          69              Ms. Sidamon discussed that among the facilities and services provided by Cvsu
          70       Trece, the orientation program gave a very adequate feedback from students while there
          71       is  only  fairly  adequate  feedback  on  lacking facilities  like  laboratories  and  audio  visual
          72       facilities. While all other services and facilities have moderate adequacy feedback.
          73
          74       C.  Discuss  the  results  Efficiency  of  Student  Services  in  terms  of  Admission
          75          Services,  Registration/Enrolment  Services,  Orientation  Program,  Security
          76          Service,  Library  Services,  Laboratory  Facilities,  Comfort  Rooms,  Dressing
          77          Areas, Drinking Water, Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-
          78
                      Visual Facilities, Handwashing areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen,
          79          Sports  and  Physical  Fitness  Services,  Student  Publication,  Student
          80          Organizations, Alumni Associations, NSTP, Printing Services and Facilities and
          81
                      Dormitory
          82
          83
                              Ms.  Sidamon  discussed  that  among  the  facilities  and  services  provided  by
          84          Cvsu  Trece,  the  orientation  program  gave  the  highest  mean  with  moderately
          85
                      adequate  feedback  from  students  while  there  is  only  fairly  adequate  feedback  on
          86
                      lacking facilities like laboratories and audio visual facilities. While all other services
          87
                      and facilities have moderate adequacy feedback.
          88
          89
                   D. Other Matters
          90
          91
                              Ms. Sidamon discussed that having the aforementioned results the campus
          92
                      should focus on items with only fair adequacy and efficiency feedback such as the
          93
                      creation  and  improvement  of  laboratories.  This  should  be  recommended  by  the
          94
                      campus Budget Officer to be given allocation in the next year’s PPMP. She also said
          95
                      that a very adequate and efficient feedback should be aimed on the following year’s
          96
                      survey.
          97]]></page><page Index="133"><![CDATA[98   III. ADJOURNMENT OF MEETING
          99          There being no other matters to discuss, the meeting was adjourned at 3:30pm.

        100    Prepared by:                                             Attested by:


        102
        103    LILIAN O. SIDAMON                                       VIENNA MI A. FERANIL
        104    OSAS Coordinator                                    Curriculum Development & Instruction Head
                                                                        Trece Campus Coordinator]]></page><page Index="134"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="135"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="136"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="137"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="138"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="139"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="140"><![CDATA[SOCIAL MEDIA, LEARNING STYLES AND ACADEMIC PERFORMANCE OF STUDENTS:
               BASIS  FOR ENHANCEMENT OF GUIDANCE AND COUNSELING PROGRAM AT CAVITE
                                                 STATE  UNIVERSITY

                                                 Charise Mae D. Galve
                                       Master of Education Major in Guidance and
                                    Counseling  Cavite State University-Main Campus
                                                    November, 2019





                                                      ABSTRACT

                   The  world  today  is  celebrating  the  improvements  in  communication  technology  which  has

           broadened  the  scope  of  communication  through  Information  and  Communication  Technologies

           (ICTs).  Modern Technology in communication no doubt has turned the entire world into a “Global

           village”  (Asemah and Edegoh, 2012). ). Hence, this research was done to find out the social media,

           learning  styles  and  academic  performance  among  the  students  of T3  campuses  of  Cavite  State


           University,  namely, Trece Martires City, Tanza and General Trias in order to establish a basis for

           enhancement  of     guidance  and  counseling  program..  The  descriptive-comparative  method  of

           research  was  utilized  that  investigated  and  described  the  relationship  between  variables  in  their

           natural setting without  manipulation.

                   Results of the study showed that in general, majority of students used Facebook (81.7 %),

           YouTube (50.7 %), and Google+ (26.0 %) while the use of Blogspot and Wordress or Joomla was


           only  one. The mean and standard deviation of not using Google + (M=2.05, SD = 0.024) and using

           Google+   (M=1.91, SD =0.039).The computed t-value was 3.056 with a p-value of 0.002 which is

           significant at

           0.05 level. This suggests that using Google+ as a social media platform has a significant effect on


           the  academic performance of the student.

                   The  findings  also  showed  the  significant  difference  of  Academic  Performance  of  the
                   participants
           and their Learning Styles using F-test, the computed value was 3.190 and with the p-value of 0.005,

           significant at 0.05 level.




            Keywords: Social Media, Learning Styles, Academic Performance, Guidance and
            Counseling]]></page><page Index="141"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






                                                               ISSN: 2591-7064
                                                               Vol. 3, No. 2A, Feb. 2019




















































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                      Page 1 of 663
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="142"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






























































                                                        Funded by
                                  Joint Multidisciplinary Research Conferences  Joint
                                     Multidisciplinary Research Conferences Plus
                                         Multidisciplinary Research Festivals


                                                       Available at
                                             www.ascendensasia.com/ojs
                                            www.aaresearchindex.com/ojs


                                                       Published by
                                               Ascendens Asia Pte.Ltd.





                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="143"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts


                  Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts

                  Volume 3                                                              Number 2A




                  February 2019


                  Research               Advocacy               for          Community

                  Empowerment              (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary

                  Research Poster  Exhibition Abstract Proceedings

































                  ISSN: 2591-7064


                  Recommended Citation

                  (February 2019) "Research Advocacy for Community Empowerment (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary
                  Research Poster Exhibition Abstract Proceedings," Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts, Vol.3, No.2A. Available at: "http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA".



                  The Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts (AAJMRA) is a collection of abstracts of research
                  papers presented during Multidisciplinary Research Fests (MRFs) mainly organised by Ascendens Asia Singapore as well
                  as other research conferences in collaboration with various institutions and learned societies. MRFs provide  opportunities
                  for collaboration with a common prime objective of creating platforms for students, faculty, staff, and  researchers-alike
                  from  different  institutions  to  interrelate/interact  with  their  counterparts.  MRFs,  are  expected  to  aide  and  promote
                  personality development and critical thinking as participants engage themselves in constructive discussions  with other
                  participating researchers.

                  AAJMRAs are made available complimentary and for open access by Ascendens Asia Singapore. For more information,
                  please contact publications@ascendensasia.com.




                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="144"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts



                  Copyright &


                  Copyright© 2019
                  Copyright  for  the  texts  which  include  all  issues  of  Ascendens  Asia  Journal  of  Multidisciplinary  Research
                  Disclaimer                                                                 individuals;
                  Abstracts are held by the AAMJRA, except if otherwise noted. The compilation as a whole is Copyright©  by
                  AAMJRA,  all  rights  reserved.  Items  published  by  AAMJRA  may  be  generously  shared  among
                  however, they may NOT be republished in any medium without express written consent  from the author(s)
                  and advance notification of the AAMJRA Editorial Board. For permission to reprint  articles published in the
                  AAMJRA, please contact the Editorial Board at  publications@ascendensasia.com.

                  Disclaimer
                  Facts and opinions published in Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts  (AAMJRA)
                  express solely the opinions of the respective authors. Authors are responsible for their citing  of sources and the
                  accuracy of their references and bibliographies. The editors cannot be held responsible  for any lack or possible
                  violations of third parties' rights. Interested parties may also directly contact  authors to request for full copies
                  of the journal proceedings.































































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                       Page 15 of
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA                                  632]]></page><page Index="145"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                  Collaborative  Learning and Skills Development of Grade 10 Students:  Basis for  Achievement
                  in Mathematics                                                                    60
                  Adrian Ramos, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LIPAC1-0085

                  Collaborative Learning: A Strategy in Reducing the Academic Anxiety among 8th Grade
                  Learners                                                                          61
                  Diana Hinahon & Patrick Sulibaga, Naic NHS
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0983
                  Collaborative Learning: Its Effect to the Performance in Mathematics of Grade 9 Students   62
                  Cleo Mae Castaneda, Linga National High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LAGUNA-0130
                  Collaborative Mind Mapping in Enhancing Pupils' Academic Achievement in Science 6   63
                  Arcedel Pagana, Department of Education - Tayabas
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-TAYABA-0003

                  Collaborative Professional Learning through Lesson Study: A tool to Improve Science 9
                  Classroom Instruction                                                             64
                  Lorna Gayla, Looc Integrated School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CALAMB-0428
                  Collaborative Reading Enhancement Activities Towards Excellence                   65
                  Amelia Panganiban, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0514

                  Collaborative Strategy in Teaching Filipino in Lemery Senior High School (Kolaboratibong
                  Estratehiya Sa Pagtuturo Ng Asignaturang Filipino Sa Lemery Senior High School)  Jennifer   66
                  Mendoza, Lemery Senior High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANP-0961
                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      67
                  Norielyn Bernarte & Rosabel Berania, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529

                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      68
                  Norielyn Bernarte, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529
                  Collaborative  Use of  Technological Resources in Teaching Mathematics for Public
                  Elementary Schools Municipality of Amadeo                                         69
                  Clarice A. Sarmiento
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0635

                  Collaborative-Programmed-Discovery   Method:   An   Intervention   to   Improve   the
                  Mathematics Performance of Grade Ix Students of Jose Rizal National High School   70
                  Earl Abad, Teacher
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-COTABP-0001
                  College and Career Readiness of Senior High School: Basis for Comprehensive Guidance
                  Program                                                                           71
                  Junrey Villa, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-GENSAN-0007

                  College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records: Bases of Student
                  Academic Performance in a State University                                        72
                  Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059






                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                       2
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="146"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                                College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records:
                                   Bases of Student Academic Performance in a State University

                                         Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece


                                                        Abstract


                  INTRODUCTION
                  An  entrance  examination  is  an  examination  that  many  educational  institutions  use  to  select  students  for
                  admission. These  exams may  be administered at  any level  of  education,  from primary to  higher  education,
                  although  they  are  more  common  at  higher  levels.  It  was  in  the  school  year  1997-1998  when  the  school
                  decided to use the standardized test of the CEM. After a few administrations, it was found out that none  was
                  able to pass the test or hardly reached an expected score. Due to fear that only a few will be qualified  to enroll
                  in  college  which  may  lead  to  bankruptcy,  the  school  decided  to  stop  the  administration  of  the    said
                  standardized test by the CEM and returned to using the teacher-made test.

                  METHODS
                  The  study  used  correlational  research  method.  The  method  was  used  to  investigate  the  extent  to  which
                  variations in one factor such as the first year college academic performance correlate with variations in  one
                  or more other factors such as college entrance exam results and high school scholastic records based  on the
                  correlation  coefficient.  The  primary  data  were  obtained  through  the  entrance  exam  results,  high    school
                  scholastic records, and college academic grades from the Office of the Campus Registrar.

                  RESULTS
                  College entrance exam results of students have fairly satisfactory results. Participant's high school  scholastic
                  records and academic performance in college are satisfactory.  There is a significant difference  between the
                  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  in  students'  academic  performance  in
                  college. The F-ratio of 46.36 is greater than the F critical value for .05 level of 3.01. The  computed F-ratio
                  being  greater  than  the  tabulated  F-ratio  means  that  the  null  hypothesis  is  rejected.    Rejecting  the  null
                  hypothesis further proves that college entrance exam results and high school scholastic  records are significant
                  to student's academic performance in college.

                  DISCUSSIONS
                  The  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  are  significant  to  student's  academic
                  performance in college. According to the Campus Registrar, high school records could be a determinant  of
                  college  entrance  exam  since  the  students  had  their  high  school  for  four  years  and  the  entrance  exam
                  measures  their  gained  knowledge  from  their  previous  education.  It  may  also  the  reason  why  the  college
                  entrance exam could also be a determinant of first-year college grades since they are in the adjustment  period
                  from at least four years in high school.

                  KEYWORDS: entrance exam, scholastic record, academic performance

                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059
























                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                      72
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="147"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="148"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="149"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="150"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="151"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="152"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="153"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="154"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="155"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="156"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                    AREA IV: SUPPORT TO STUDENTS












                                       PARAMETER E.



                 RESEARCH, MONITORING AND



                                          EVALUATION












                                   IMPLEMENTATION

















              I.3.           Regular monitoring and


                             evaluation on the implementation


                             of student services are


                             conducted.

















                      Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="157"><![CDATA[1                                  Republic of the Philippines
           2                           CAVITE STATE UNIVERSITY
           3                      TanzaǀTrece Martires Cityǀ Gen. Trias City Campus
           4                           414-3979   ǀ(0977)8033809   ǀ509-4148
           5                                       www.cvsu.edu.ph
           6
           7                           TRECE MARTIRES CITY CAMPUS


           8      MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF KEY OFFICIALS HELD AT READING ROOM, CvSU
           9                   TRECE MARTIRES CITY CAMPUS ON 01 AUGUST  2019



          10   I. CALL TO ORDER AND ATTENDANCE
          11          The OSAS Head, Ms. Lilian O. Sidamon, formally called to order the meeting of the
          12   Department at 1:30 pm. A quorum was declared with one (1) Curriculum Development & (3)
          13   Instruction Heads, Guidance Coordinator, Registrar, Campus Nurse and (4) Student
          14   Organization heads.
          15
          16   Lilian O. Sidamon            Presiding Officer
          17   Vienna Mi A. Feranil
          18   Cristza de Ocampo-Manlapig
          19   Keno A. Villavicencio
          20   Arlene, Estrada
          21   Gideon Luke Ty
          22   Gwena Rochelle G. Lontoc
          23   Mary Ann L. Anonas
          24   Robert O. Peligrino
          25   Joseph Fortaleza
          26   Junie T. Gaspar
          27   Prince Julius Elsisura
          28
          29   II. AGENDA OF THE MEETING
          30          The OSAS Coordinator presented the agenda of the meeting as follows:
          31
          32          Dissemination of Evaluation of Adequacy and Efficiency of Student
          33          Services and Facilities
          34
                      Discuss the results Adequacy of Student Services in terms of Admission Services,
          35
                      Registration/Enrolment Services, Orientation Program, Security Service, Library
          36
                      Services, Laboratory Facilities, Comfort Rooms, Dressing Areas, Drinking Water,
          37
                      Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-Visual Facilities,
          38
                      Handwashing  areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen, Sports and Physical
          39
                      Fitness  Services, Student Publication, Student Organizations, Alumni Associations,
          40
                      NSTP,  Printing Services and Facilities and Dormitory
          41
                      Discuss the results Efficiency of Student Services in terms of Admission Services,
          42
                      Registration/Enrolment Services, Orientation Program, Security Service, Library
          43
                      Services, Laboratory Facilities, Comfort Rooms, Dressing Areas, Drinking Water,
          44
                      Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-Visual Facilities,
          45
                      Handwashing  areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen, Sports and Physical
          46
                      Fitness  Services, Student Publication, Student Organizations, Alumni Associations,
          47
                      NSTP,  Printing Services and Facilities and Dormitory]]></page><page Index="158"><![CDATA[48          Other Matters
          49
          50       A. Dissemination of Evaluation of Adequacy and Efficiency of Student Services
          51          and Facilities
          52
          53              Ms.  Sidamon  discussed  the  contents  of  the  survey  on  Evaluation  of  Adequacy
          54       and  Efficiency  of  student  Services  and  Facilities.  It  is  a  five-point  questionnaire  on
          55       adequacy  ranging  from:  more  than  adequate,  moderately  adequate,  fairly  adequate
          56       slightly adequate and inadequate. Efficiency ranges from more than efficient, moderately
          57       efficient, fairly  efficient, slightly  efficient  and  in  efficient.  The  survey  questionnaire  was
          58       given to 5 students per section across courses.

          59       B.  Discuss  the  results  Adequacy  of  Student  Services  in  terms  of
          60          Admission  Services,  Registration/Enrolment  Services,  Orientation
          61          Program,  Security  Service,  Library  Services,  Laboratory  Facilities,
          62          Comfort  Rooms,  Dressing  Areas,  Drinking  Water,  Guidance  and
          63          Counseling,  Assembly  Facilities,  Audio-Visual  Facilities,  Handwashing
          64          areas,  Health  Services,  Food  Services/Canteen,  Sports  and  Physical
          65          Fitness  Services,  Student  Publication,  Student  Organizations,  Alumni
          66          Associations,     NSTP,     Printing   Services     and    Facilities   and
          67          DormitoryDiscuss the BSBM and BSHRM/BSHM Program Outcomes
          68
          69              Ms. Sidamon discussed that among the facilities and services provided by Cvsu
          70       Trece, the orientation program gave a very adequate feedback from students while there
          71       is  only  fairly  adequate  feedback  on  lacking facilities  like  laboratories  and  audio  visual
          72       facilities. While all other services and facilities have moderate adequacy feedback.
          73
          74       C.  Discuss  the  results  Efficiency  of  Student  Services  in  terms  of  Admission
          75          Services,  Registration/Enrolment  Services,  Orientation  Program,  Security
          76          Service,  Library  Services,  Laboratory  Facilities,  Comfort  Rooms,  Dressing
          77          Areas, Drinking Water, Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-
          78
                      Visual Facilities, Handwashing areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen,
          79          Sports  and  Physical  Fitness  Services,  Student  Publication,  Student
          80          Organizations, Alumni Associations, NSTP, Printing Services and Facilities and
          81
                      Dormitory
          82
          83
                              Ms.  Sidamon  discussed  that  among  the  facilities  and  services  provided  by
          84          Cvsu  Trece,  the  orientation  program  gave  the  highest  mean  with  moderately
          85
                      adequate  feedback  from  students  while  there  is  only  fairly  adequate  feedback  on
          86
                      lacking facilities like laboratories and audio visual facilities. While all other services
          87
                      and facilities have moderate adequacy feedback.
          88
          89
                   D. Other Matters
          90
          91
                              Ms. Sidamon discussed that having the aforementioned results the campus
          92
                      should focus on items with only fair adequacy and efficiency feedback such as the
          93
                      creation  and  improvement  of  laboratories.  This  should  be  recommended  by  the
          94
                      campus Budget Officer to be given allocation in the next year’s PPMP. She also said
          95
                      that a very adequate and efficient feedback should be aimed on the following year’s
          96
                      survey.
          97]]></page><page Index="159"><![CDATA[98   III. ADJOURNMENT OF MEETING
          99          There being no other matters to discuss, the meeting was adjourned at 3:30pm.

        100    Prepared by:                                             Attested by:


        102
        103    LILIAN O. SIDAMON                                       VIENNA MI A. FERANIL
        104    OSAS Coordinator                                    Curriculum Development & Instruction Head
                                                                        Trece Campus Coordinator]]></page><page Index="160"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="161"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="162"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="163"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="164"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="165"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="166"><![CDATA[SOCIAL MEDIA, LEARNING STYLES AND ACADEMIC PERFORMANCE OF STUDENTS:
               BASIS  FOR ENHANCEMENT OF GUIDANCE AND COUNSELING PROGRAM AT CAVITE
                                                 STATE  UNIVERSITY

                                                 Charise Mae D. Galve
                                       Master of Education Major in Guidance and
                                    Counseling  Cavite State University-Main Campus
                                                    November, 2019





                                                      ABSTRACT

                   The  world  today  is  celebrating  the  improvements  in  communication  technology  which  has

           broadened  the  scope  of  communication  through  Information  and  Communication  Technologies

           (ICTs).  Modern Technology in communication no doubt has turned the entire world into a “Global

           village”  (Asemah and Edegoh, 2012). ). Hence, this research was done to find out the social media,

           learning  styles  and  academic  performance  among  the  students  of T3  campuses  of  Cavite  State


           University,  namely, Trece Martires City, Tanza and General Trias in order to establish a basis for

           enhancement  of     guidance  and  counseling  program..  The  descriptive-comparative  method  of

           research  was  utilized  that  investigated  and  described  the  relationship  between  variables  in  their

           natural setting without  manipulation.

                   Results of the study showed that in general, majority of students used Facebook (81.7 %),

           YouTube (50.7 %), and Google+ (26.0 %) while the use of Blogspot and Wordress or Joomla was


           only  one. The mean and standard deviation of not using Google + (M=2.05, SD = 0.024) and using

           Google+   (M=1.91, SD =0.039).The computed t-value was 3.056 with a p-value of 0.002 which is

           significant at

           0.05 level. This suggests that using Google+ as a social media platform has a significant effect on


           the  academic performance of the student.

                   The  findings  also  showed  the  significant  difference  of  Academic  Performance  of  the
                   participants
           and their Learning Styles using F-test, the computed value was 3.190 and with the p-value of 0.005,

           significant at 0.05 level.




            Keywords: Social Media, Learning Styles, Academic Performance, Guidance and
            Counseling]]></page><page Index="167"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






                                                               ISSN: 2591-7064
                                                               Vol. 3, No. 2A, Feb. 2019




















































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                      Page 1 of 663
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="168"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






























































                                                        Funded by
                                  Joint Multidisciplinary Research Conferences  Joint
                                     Multidisciplinary Research Conferences Plus
                                         Multidisciplinary Research Festivals


                                                       Available at
                                             www.ascendensasia.com/ojs
                                            www.aaresearchindex.com/ojs


                                                       Published by
                                               Ascendens Asia Pte.Ltd.





                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="169"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts


                  Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts

                  Volume 3                                                              Number 2A




                  February 2019


                  Research               Advocacy               for          Community

                  Empowerment              (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary

                  Research Poster  Exhibition Abstract Proceedings

































                  ISSN: 2591-7064


                  Recommended Citation

                  (February 2019) "Research Advocacy for Community Empowerment (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary
                  Research Poster Exhibition Abstract Proceedings," Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts, Vol.3, No.2A. Available at: "http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA".



                  The Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts (AAJMRA) is a collection of abstracts of research
                  papers presented during Multidisciplinary Research Fests (MRFs) mainly organised by Ascendens Asia Singapore as well
                  as other research conferences in collaboration with various institutions and learned societies. MRFs provide  opportunities
                  for collaboration with a common prime objective of creating platforms for students, faculty, staff, and  researchers-alike
                  from  different  institutions  to  interrelate/interact  with  their  counterparts.  MRFs,  are  expected  to  aide  and  promote
                  personality development and critical thinking as participants engage themselves in constructive discussions  with other
                  participating researchers.

                  AAJMRAs are made available complimentary and for open access by Ascendens Asia Singapore. For more information,
                  please contact publications@ascendensasia.com.




                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="170"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts



                  Copyright &


                  Copyright© 2019
                  Copyright  for  the  texts  which  include  all  issues  of  Ascendens  Asia  Journal  of  Multidisciplinary  Research
                  Disclaimer                                                                 individuals;
                  Abstracts are held by the AAMJRA, except if otherwise noted. The compilation as a whole is Copyright©  by
                  AAMJRA,  all  rights  reserved.  Items  published  by  AAMJRA  may  be  generously  shared  among
                  however, they may NOT be republished in any medium without express written consent  from the author(s)
                  and advance notification of the AAMJRA Editorial Board. For permission to reprint  articles published in the
                  AAMJRA, please contact the Editorial Board at  publications@ascendensasia.com.

                  Disclaimer
                  Facts and opinions published in Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts  (AAMJRA)
                  express solely the opinions of the respective authors. Authors are responsible for their citing  of sources and the
                  accuracy of their references and bibliographies. The editors cannot be held responsible  for any lack or possible
                  violations of third parties' rights. Interested parties may also directly contact  authors to request for full copies
                  of the journal proceedings.































































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                       Page 15 of
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA                                  632]]></page><page Index="171"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                  Collaborative  Learning and Skills Development of Grade 10 Students:  Basis for  Achievement
                  in Mathematics                                                                    60
                  Adrian Ramos, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LIPAC1-0085

                  Collaborative Learning: A Strategy in Reducing the Academic Anxiety among 8th Grade
                  Learners                                                                          61
                  Diana Hinahon & Patrick Sulibaga, Naic NHS
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0983
                  Collaborative Learning: Its Effect to the Performance in Mathematics of Grade 9 Students   62
                  Cleo Mae Castaneda, Linga National High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LAGUNA-0130
                  Collaborative Mind Mapping in Enhancing Pupils' Academic Achievement in Science 6   63
                  Arcedel Pagana, Department of Education - Tayabas
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-TAYABA-0003

                  Collaborative Professional Learning through Lesson Study: A tool to Improve Science 9
                  Classroom Instruction                                                             64
                  Lorna Gayla, Looc Integrated School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CALAMB-0428
                  Collaborative Reading Enhancement Activities Towards Excellence                   65
                  Amelia Panganiban, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0514

                  Collaborative Strategy in Teaching Filipino in Lemery Senior High School (Kolaboratibong
                  Estratehiya Sa Pagtuturo Ng Asignaturang Filipino Sa Lemery Senior High School)  Jennifer   66
                  Mendoza, Lemery Senior High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANP-0961
                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      67
                  Norielyn Bernarte & Rosabel Berania, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529

                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      68
                  Norielyn Bernarte, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529
                  Collaborative  Use of  Technological Resources in Teaching Mathematics for Public
                  Elementary Schools Municipality of Amadeo                                         69
                  Clarice A. Sarmiento
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0635

                  Collaborative-Programmed-Discovery   Method:   An   Intervention   to   Improve   the
                  Mathematics Performance of Grade Ix Students of Jose Rizal National High School   70
                  Earl Abad, Teacher
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-COTABP-0001
                  College and Career Readiness of Senior High School: Basis for Comprehensive Guidance
                  Program                                                                           71
                  Junrey Villa, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-GENSAN-0007

                  College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records: Bases of Student
                  Academic Performance in a State University                                        72
                  Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059






                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                       2
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="172"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                                College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records:
                                   Bases of Student Academic Performance in a State University

                                         Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece


                                                        Abstract


                  INTRODUCTION
                  An  entrance  examination  is  an  examination  that  many  educational  institutions  use  to  select  students  for
                  admission. These  exams may  be administered at  any level  of  education,  from primary to  higher  education,
                  although  they  are  more  common  at  higher  levels.  It  was  in  the  school  year  1997-1998  when  the  school
                  decided to use the standardized test of the CEM. After a few administrations, it was found out that none  was
                  able to pass the test or hardly reached an expected score. Due to fear that only a few will be qualified  to enroll
                  in  college  which  may  lead  to  bankruptcy,  the  school  decided  to  stop  the  administration  of  the    said
                  standardized test by the CEM and returned to using the teacher-made test.

                  METHODS
                  The  study  used  correlational  research  method.  The  method  was  used  to  investigate  the  extent  to  which
                  variations in one factor such as the first year college academic performance correlate with variations in  one
                  or more other factors such as college entrance exam results and high school scholastic records based  on the
                  correlation  coefficient.  The  primary  data  were  obtained  through  the  entrance  exam  results,  high    school
                  scholastic records, and college academic grades from the Office of the Campus Registrar.

                  RESULTS
                  College entrance exam results of students have fairly satisfactory results. Participant's high school  scholastic
                  records and academic performance in college are satisfactory.  There is a significant difference  between the
                  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  in  students'  academic  performance  in
                  college. The F-ratio of 46.36 is greater than the F critical value for .05 level of 3.01. The  computed F-ratio
                  being  greater  than  the  tabulated  F-ratio  means  that  the  null  hypothesis  is  rejected.    Rejecting  the  null
                  hypothesis further proves that college entrance exam results and high school scholastic  records are significant
                  to student's academic performance in college.

                  DISCUSSIONS
                  The  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  are  significant  to  student's  academic
                  performance in college. According to the Campus Registrar, high school records could be a determinant  of
                  college  entrance  exam  since  the  students  had  their  high  school  for  four  years  and  the  entrance  exam
                  measures  their  gained  knowledge  from  their  previous  education.  It  may  also  the  reason  why  the  college
                  entrance exam could also be a determinant of first-year college grades since they are in the adjustment  period
                  from at least four years in high school.

                  KEYWORDS: entrance exam, scholastic record, academic performance

                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059
























                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                      72
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="173"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="174"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="175"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="176"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="177"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="178"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="179"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="180"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="181"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="182"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                    AREA IV: SUPPORT TO STUDENTS












                                       PARAMETER E.



                 RESEARCH, MONITORING AND



                                          EVALUATION












                                   IMPLEMENTATION





















              I.4.           Monitoring and evaluation


                             instruments are developed,


                             reviewed, and continuously


                             improved.












                      Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="183"><![CDATA[1                                  Republic of the Philippines
           2                           CAVITE STATE UNIVERSITY
           3                      TanzaǀTrece Martires Cityǀ Gen. Trias City Campus
           4                           414-3979   ǀ(0977)8033809   ǀ509-4148
           5                                       www.cvsu.edu.ph
           6
           7                           TRECE MARTIRES CITY CAMPUS


           8      MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF KEY OFFICIALS HELD AT READING ROOM, CvSU
           9                   TRECE MARTIRES CITY CAMPUS ON 01 AUGUST  2019



          10   I. CALL TO ORDER AND ATTENDANCE
          11          The OSAS Head, Ms. Lilian O. Sidamon, formally called to order the meeting of the
          12   Department at 1:30 pm. A quorum was declared with one (1) Curriculum Development & (3)
          13   Instruction Heads, Guidance Coordinator, Registrar, Campus Nurse and (4) Student
          14   Organization heads.
          15
          16   Lilian O. Sidamon            Presiding Officer
          17   Vienna Mi A. Feranil
          18   Cristza de Ocampo-Manlapig
          19   Keno A. Villavicencio
          20   Arlene, Estrada
          21   Gideon Luke Ty
          22   Gwena Rochelle G. Lontoc
          23   Mary Ann L. Anonas
          24   Robert O. Peligrino
          25   Joseph Fortaleza
          26   Junie T. Gaspar
          27   Prince Julius Elsisura
          28
          29   II. AGENDA OF THE MEETING
          30          The OSAS Coordinator presented the agenda of the meeting as follows:
          31
          32          Dissemination of Evaluation of Adequacy and Efficiency of Student
          33          Services and Facilities
          34
                      Discuss the results Adequacy of Student Services in terms of Admission Services,
          35
                      Registration/Enrolment Services, Orientation Program, Security Service, Library
          36
                      Services, Laboratory Facilities, Comfort Rooms, Dressing Areas, Drinking Water,
          37
                      Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-Visual Facilities,
          38
                      Handwashing  areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen, Sports and Physical
          39
                      Fitness  Services, Student Publication, Student Organizations, Alumni Associations,
          40
                      NSTP,  Printing Services and Facilities and Dormitory
          41
                      Discuss the results Efficiency of Student Services in terms of Admission Services,
          42
                      Registration/Enrolment Services, Orientation Program, Security Service, Library
          43
                      Services, Laboratory Facilities, Comfort Rooms, Dressing Areas, Drinking Water,
          44
                      Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-Visual Facilities,
          45
                      Handwashing  areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen, Sports and Physical
          46
                      Fitness  Services, Student Publication, Student Organizations, Alumni Associations,
          47
                      NSTP,  Printing Services and Facilities and Dormitory]]></page><page Index="184"><![CDATA[48          Other Matters
          49
          50       A. Dissemination of Evaluation of Adequacy and Efficiency of Student Services
          51          and Facilities
          52
          53              Ms.  Sidamon  discussed  the  contents  of  the  survey  on  Evaluation  of  Adequacy
          54       and  Efficiency  of  student  Services  and  Facilities.  It  is  a  five-point  questionnaire  on
          55       adequacy  ranging  from:  more  than  adequate,  moderately  adequate,  fairly  adequate
          56       slightly adequate and inadequate. Efficiency ranges from more than efficient, moderately
          57       efficient, fairly  efficient, slightly  efficient  and  in  efficient.  The  survey  questionnaire  was
          58       given to 5 students per section across courses.

          59       B.  Discuss  the  results  Adequacy  of  Student  Services  in  terms  of
          60          Admission  Services,  Registration/Enrolment  Services,  Orientation
          61          Program,  Security  Service,  Library  Services,  Laboratory  Facilities,
          62          Comfort  Rooms,  Dressing  Areas,  Drinking  Water,  Guidance  and
          63          Counseling,  Assembly  Facilities,  Audio-Visual  Facilities,  Handwashing
          64          areas,  Health  Services,  Food  Services/Canteen,  Sports  and  Physical
          65          Fitness  Services,  Student  Publication,  Student  Organizations,  Alumni
          66          Associations,     NSTP,     Printing   Services     and    Facilities   and
          67          DormitoryDiscuss the BSBM and BSHRM/BSHM Program Outcomes
          68
          69              Ms. Sidamon discussed that among the facilities and services provided by Cvsu
          70       Trece, the orientation program gave a very adequate feedback from students while there
          71       is  only  fairly  adequate  feedback  on  lacking facilities  like  laboratories  and  audio  visual
          72       facilities. While all other services and facilities have moderate adequacy feedback.
          73
          74       C.  Discuss  the  results  Efficiency  of  Student  Services  in  terms  of  Admission
          75          Services,  Registration/Enrolment  Services,  Orientation  Program,  Security
          76          Service,  Library  Services,  Laboratory  Facilities,  Comfort  Rooms,  Dressing
          77          Areas, Drinking Water, Guidance and Counseling, Assembly Facilities, Audio-
          78
                      Visual Facilities, Handwashing areas, Health Services, Food Services/Canteen,
          79          Sports  and  Physical  Fitness  Services,  Student  Publication,  Student
          80          Organizations, Alumni Associations, NSTP, Printing Services and Facilities and
          81
                      Dormitory
          82
          83
                              Ms.  Sidamon  discussed  that  among  the  facilities  and  services  provided  by
          84          Cvsu  Trece,  the  orientation  program  gave  the  highest  mean  with  moderately
          85
                      adequate  feedback  from  students  while  there  is  only  fairly  adequate  feedback  on
          86
                      lacking facilities like laboratories and audio visual facilities. While all other services
          87
                      and facilities have moderate adequacy feedback.
          88
          89
                   D. Other Matters
          90
          91
                              Ms. Sidamon discussed that having the aforementioned results the campus
          92
                      should focus on items with only fair adequacy and efficiency feedback such as the
          93
                      creation  and  improvement  of  laboratories.  This  should  be  recommended  by  the
          94
                      campus Budget Officer to be given allocation in the next year’s PPMP. She also said
          95
                      that a very adequate and efficient feedback should be aimed on the following year’s
          96
                      survey.
          97]]></page><page Index="185"><![CDATA[98   III. ADJOURNMENT OF MEETING
          99          There being no other matters to discuss, the meeting was adjourned at 3:30pm.

        100    Prepared by:                                             Attested by:


        102
        103    LILIAN O. SIDAMON                                       VIENNA MI A. FERANIL
        104    OSAS Coordinator                                    Curriculum Development & Instruction Head
                                                                        Trece Campus Coordinator]]></page><page Index="186"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="187"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="188"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="189"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="190"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="191"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="192"><![CDATA[SOCIAL MEDIA, LEARNING STYLES AND ACADEMIC PERFORMANCE OF STUDENTS:
               BASIS  FOR ENHANCEMENT OF GUIDANCE AND COUNSELING PROGRAM AT CAVITE
                                                 STATE  UNIVERSITY

                                                 Charise Mae D. Galve
                                       Master of Education Major in Guidance and
                                    Counseling  Cavite State University-Main Campus
                                                    November, 2019





                                                      ABSTRACT

                   The  world  today  is  celebrating  the  improvements  in  communication  technology  which  has

           broadened  the  scope  of  communication  through  Information  and  Communication  Technologies

           (ICTs).  Modern Technology in communication no doubt has turned the entire world into a “Global

           village”  (Asemah and Edegoh, 2012). ). Hence, this research was done to find out the social media,

           learning  styles  and  academic  performance  among  the  students  of T3  campuses  of  Cavite  State


           University,  namely, Trece Martires City, Tanza and General Trias in order to establish a basis for

           enhancement  of     guidance  and  counseling  program..  The  descriptive-comparative  method  of

           research  was  utilized  that  investigated  and  described  the  relationship  between  variables  in  their

           natural setting without  manipulation.

                   Results of the study showed that in general, majority of students used Facebook (81.7 %),

           YouTube (50.7 %), and Google+ (26.0 %) while the use of Blogspot and Wordress or Joomla was


           only  one. The mean and standard deviation of not using Google + (M=2.05, SD = 0.024) and using

           Google+   (M=1.91, SD =0.039).The computed t-value was 3.056 with a p-value of 0.002 which is

           significant at

           0.05 level. This suggests that using Google+ as a social media platform has a significant effect on


           the  academic performance of the student.

                   The  findings  also  showed  the  significant  difference  of  Academic  Performance  of  the
                   participants
           and their Learning Styles using F-test, the computed value was 3.190 and with the p-value of 0.005,

           significant at 0.05 level.




            Keywords: Social Media, Learning Styles, Academic Performance, Guidance and
            Counseling]]></page><page Index="193"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






                                                               ISSN: 2591-7064
                                                               Vol. 3, No. 2A, Feb. 2019




















































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                      Page 1 of 663
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="194"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






























































                                                        Funded by
                                  Joint Multidisciplinary Research Conferences  Joint
                                     Multidisciplinary Research Conferences Plus
                                         Multidisciplinary Research Festivals


                                                       Available at
                                             www.ascendensasia.com/ojs
                                            www.aaresearchindex.com/ojs


                                                       Published by
                                               Ascendens Asia Pte.Ltd.





                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="195"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts


                  Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts

                  Volume 3                                                              Number 2A




                  February 2019


                  Research               Advocacy               for          Community

                  Empowerment              (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary

                  Research Poster  Exhibition Abstract Proceedings

































                  ISSN: 2591-7064


                  Recommended Citation

                  (February 2019) "Research Advocacy for Community Empowerment (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary
                  Research Poster Exhibition Abstract Proceedings," Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts, Vol.3, No.2A. Available at: "http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA".



                  The Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts (AAJMRA) is a collection of abstracts of research
                  papers presented during Multidisciplinary Research Fests (MRFs) mainly organised by Ascendens Asia Singapore as well
                  as other research conferences in collaboration with various institutions and learned societies. MRFs provide  opportunities
                  for collaboration with a common prime objective of creating platforms for students, faculty, staff, and  researchers-alike
                  from  different  institutions  to  interrelate/interact  with  their  counterparts.  MRFs,  are  expected  to  aide  and  promote
                  personality development and critical thinking as participants engage themselves in constructive discussions  with other
                  participating researchers.

                  AAJMRAs are made available complimentary and for open access by Ascendens Asia Singapore. For more information,
                  please contact publications@ascendensasia.com.




                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="196"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts



                  Copyright &


                  Copyright© 2019
                  Copyright  for  the  texts  which  include  all  issues  of  Ascendens  Asia  Journal  of  Multidisciplinary  Research
                  Disclaimer                                                                 individuals;
                  Abstracts are held by the AAMJRA, except if otherwise noted. The compilation as a whole is Copyright©  by
                  AAMJRA,  all  rights  reserved.  Items  published  by  AAMJRA  may  be  generously  shared  among
                  however, they may NOT be republished in any medium without express written consent  from the author(s)
                  and advance notification of the AAMJRA Editorial Board. For permission to reprint  articles published in the
                  AAMJRA, please contact the Editorial Board at  publications@ascendensasia.com.

                  Disclaimer
                  Facts and opinions published in Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts  (AAMJRA)
                  express solely the opinions of the respective authors. Authors are responsible for their citing  of sources and the
                  accuracy of their references and bibliographies. The editors cannot be held responsible  for any lack or possible
                  violations of third parties' rights. Interested parties may also directly contact  authors to request for full copies
                  of the journal proceedings.































































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                       Page 15 of
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA                                  632]]></page><page Index="197"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                  Collaborative  Learning and Skills Development of Grade 10 Students:  Basis for  Achievement
                  in Mathematics                                                                    60
                  Adrian Ramos, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LIPAC1-0085

                  Collaborative Learning: A Strategy in Reducing the Academic Anxiety among 8th Grade
                  Learners                                                                          61
                  Diana Hinahon & Patrick Sulibaga, Naic NHS
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0983
                  Collaborative Learning: Its Effect to the Performance in Mathematics of Grade 9 Students   62
                  Cleo Mae Castaneda, Linga National High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LAGUNA-0130
                  Collaborative Mind Mapping in Enhancing Pupils' Academic Achievement in Science 6   63
                  Arcedel Pagana, Department of Education - Tayabas
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-TAYABA-0003

                  Collaborative Professional Learning through Lesson Study: A tool to Improve Science 9
                  Classroom Instruction                                                             64
                  Lorna Gayla, Looc Integrated School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CALAMB-0428
                  Collaborative Reading Enhancement Activities Towards Excellence                   65
                  Amelia Panganiban, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0514

                  Collaborative Strategy in Teaching Filipino in Lemery Senior High School (Kolaboratibong
                  Estratehiya Sa Pagtuturo Ng Asignaturang Filipino Sa Lemery Senior High School)  Jennifer   66
                  Mendoza, Lemery Senior High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANP-0961
                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      67
                  Norielyn Bernarte & Rosabel Berania, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529

                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      68
                  Norielyn Bernarte, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529
                  Collaborative  Use of  Technological Resources in Teaching Mathematics for Public
                  Elementary Schools Municipality of Amadeo                                         69
                  Clarice A. Sarmiento
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0635

                  Collaborative-Programmed-Discovery   Method:   An   Intervention   to   Improve   the
                  Mathematics Performance of Grade Ix Students of Jose Rizal National High School   70
                  Earl Abad, Teacher
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-COTABP-0001
                  College and Career Readiness of Senior High School: Basis for Comprehensive Guidance
                  Program                                                                           71
                  Junrey Villa, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-GENSAN-0007

                  College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records: Bases of Student
                  Academic Performance in a State University                                        72
                  Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059






                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                       2
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="198"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                                College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records:
                                   Bases of Student Academic Performance in a State University

                                         Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece


                                                        Abstract


                  INTRODUCTION
                  An  entrance  examination  is  an  examination  that  many  educational  institutions  use  to  select  students  for
                  admission. These  exams may  be administered at  any level  of  education,  from primary to  higher  education,
                  although  they  are  more  common  at  higher  levels.  It  was  in  the  school  year  1997-1998  when  the  school
                  decided to use the standardized test of the CEM. After a few administrations, it was found out that none  was
                  able to pass the test or hardly reached an expected score. Due to fear that only a few will be qualified  to enroll
                  in  college  which  may  lead  to  bankruptcy,  the  school  decided  to  stop  the  administration  of  the    said
                  standardized test by the CEM and returned to using the teacher-made test.

                  METHODS
                  The  study  used  correlational  research  method.  The  method  was  used  to  investigate  the  extent  to  which
                  variations in one factor such as the first year college academic performance correlate with variations in  one
                  or more other factors such as college entrance exam results and high school scholastic records based  on the
                  correlation  coefficient.  The  primary  data  were  obtained  through  the  entrance  exam  results,  high    school
                  scholastic records, and college academic grades from the Office of the Campus Registrar.

                  RESULTS
                  College entrance exam results of students have fairly satisfactory results. Participant's high school  scholastic
                  records and academic performance in college are satisfactory.  There is a significant difference  between the
                  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  in  students'  academic  performance  in
                  college. The F-ratio of 46.36 is greater than the F critical value for .05 level of 3.01. The  computed F-ratio
                  being  greater  than  the  tabulated  F-ratio  means  that  the  null  hypothesis  is  rejected.    Rejecting  the  null
                  hypothesis further proves that college entrance exam results and high school scholastic  records are significant
                  to student's academic performance in college.

                  DISCUSSIONS
                  The  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  are  significant  to  student's  academic
                  performance in college. According to the Campus Registrar, high school records could be a determinant  of
                  college  entrance  exam  since  the  students  had  their  high  school  for  four  years  and  the  entrance  exam
                  measures  their  gained  knowledge  from  their  previous  education.  It  may  also  the  reason  why  the  college
                  entrance exam could also be a determinant of first-year college grades since they are in the adjustment  period
                  from at least four years in high school.

                  KEYWORDS: entrance exam, scholastic record, academic performance

                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059
























                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                      72
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="199"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="200"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="201"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="202"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="203"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="204"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="205"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="206"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="207"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="208"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                    AREA IV: SUPPORT TO STUDENTS












                                       PARAMETER E.



                 RESEARCH, MONITORING AND



                                          EVALUATION












                                   IMPLEMENTATION





















              I.5.           Reports are filed and submitted


                             regularly to CHEDRO




















                      Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="209"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="210"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="211"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="212"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="213"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="214"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="215"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="216"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="217"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="218"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="219"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="220"><![CDATA[BS INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY
                    AREA IV: SUPPORT TO STUDENTS












                                       PARAMETER E.



                 RESEARCH, MONITORING AND



                                          EVALUATION












                                           OUTCOME/S

















              O.1.   Research outputs are presented


                             and published.

























                      Cavite State University- Trece Martires City Campus]]></page><page Index="221"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






                                                               ISSN: 2591-7064
                                                               Vol. 3, No. 2A, Feb. 2019




















































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                      Page 1 of 663
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="222"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts






























































                                                        Funded by
                                  Joint Multidisciplinary Research Conferences  Joint
                                     Multidisciplinary Research Conferences Plus
                                         Multidisciplinary Research Festivals


                                                       Available at
                                             www.ascendensasia.com/ojs
                                            www.aaresearchindex.com/ojs


                                                       Published by
                                               Ascendens Asia Pte.Ltd.





                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="223"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts


                  Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts

                  Volume 3                                                              Number 2A




                  February 2019


                  Research               Advocacy               for          Community

                  Empowerment              (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary

                  Research Poster  Exhibition Abstract Proceedings

































                  ISSN: 2591-7064


                  Recommended Citation

                  (February 2019) "Research Advocacy for Community Empowerment (RACE) 2019: A Multidisciplinary
                  Research Poster Exhibition Abstract Proceedings," Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research
                  Abstracts, Vol.3, No.2A. Available at: "http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA".



                  The Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts (AAJMRA) is a collection of abstracts of research
                  papers presented during Multidisciplinary Research Fests (MRFs) mainly organised by Ascendens Asia Singapore as well
                  as other research conferences in collaboration with various institutions and learned societies. MRFs provide  opportunities
                  for collaboration with a common prime objective of creating platforms for students, faculty, staff, and  researchers-alike
                  from  different  institutions  to  interrelate/interact  with  their  counterparts.  MRFs,  are  expected  to  aide  and  promote
                  personality development and critical thinking as participants engage themselves in constructive discussions  with other
                  participating researchers.

                  AAJMRAs are made available complimentary and for open access by Ascendens Asia Singapore. For more information,
                  please contact publications@ascendensasia.com.




                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="224"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts



                  Copyright &


                  Copyright© 2019
                  Copyright  for  the  texts  which  include  all  issues  of  Ascendens  Asia  Journal  of  Multidisciplinary  Research
                  Disclaimer                                                                 individuals;
                  Abstracts are held by the AAMJRA, except if otherwise noted. The compilation as a whole is Copyright©  by
                  AAMJRA,  all  rights  reserved.  Items  published  by  AAMJRA  may  be  generously  shared  among
                  however, they may NOT be republished in any medium without express written consent  from the author(s)
                  and advance notification of the AAMJRA Editorial Board. For permission to reprint  articles published in the
                  AAMJRA, please contact the Editorial Board at  publications@ascendensasia.com.

                  Disclaimer
                  Facts and opinions published in Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts  (AAMJRA)
                  express solely the opinions of the respective authors. Authors are responsible for their citing  of sources and the
                  accuracy of their references and bibliographies. The editors cannot be held responsible  for any lack or possible
                  violations of third parties' rights. Interested parties may also directly contact  authors to request for full copies
                  of the journal proceedings.































































                  AAJMRA: Vol. 3, No. 2, February 2019                                       Page 6 of
                  http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA                                  632]]></page><page Index="225"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                  Collaborative  Learning and Skills Development of Grade 10 Students:  Basis for  Achievement
                  in Mathematics                                                                    60
                  Adrian Ramos, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LIPAC1-0085

                  Collaborative Learning: A Strategy in Reducing the Academic Anxiety among 8th Grade
                  Learners                                                                          61
                  Diana Hinahon & Patrick Sulibaga, Naic NHS
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0983
                  Collaborative Learning: Its Effect to the Performance in Mathematics of Grade 9 Students   62
                  Cleo Mae Castaneda, Linga National High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-LAGUNA-0130
                  Collaborative Mind Mapping in Enhancing Pupils' Academic Achievement in Science 6   63
                  Arcedel Pagana, Department of Education - Tayabas
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-TAYABA-0003

                  Collaborative Professional Learning through Lesson Study: A tool to Improve Science 9
                  Classroom Instruction                                                             64
                  Lorna Gayla, Looc Integrated School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CALAMB-0428
                  Collaborative Reading Enhancement Activities Towards Excellence                   65
                  Amelia Panganiban, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0514

                  Collaborative Strategy in Teaching Filipino in Lemery Senior High School (Kolaboratibong
                  Estratehiya Sa Pagtuturo Ng Asignaturang Filipino Sa Lemery Senior High School)  Jennifer   66
                  Mendoza, Lemery Senior High School
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANP-0961
                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      67
                  Norielyn Bernarte & Rosabel Berania, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529

                  Collaborative Teaching Strategies: as Tools for Enhancing the Performance of Grade IV
                  Pupils in Mathematics at Paaralang Elementarya Ng Calubcub 1                      68
                  Norielyn Bernarte, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-BATANC-0528/ R04A-BATANC-0529
                  Collaborative  Use of  Technological Resources in Teaching Mathematics for Public
                  Elementary Schools Municipality of Amadeo                                         69
                  Clarice A. Sarmiento
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0635

                  Collaborative-Programmed-Discovery   Method:   An   Intervention   to   Improve   the
                  Mathematics Performance of Grade Ix Students of Jose Rizal National High School   70
                  Earl Abad, Teacher
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-COTABP-0001
                  College and Career Readiness of Senior High School: Basis for Comprehensive Guidance
                  Program                                                                           71
                  Junrey Villa, Department of Education
                  SUBMISSION ID: R012-GENSAN-0007

                  College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records: Bases of Student
                  Academic Performance in a State University                                        72
                  Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece
                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059






                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                       2
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="226"><![CDATA[Ascendens Asia Journal of Multidisciplinary Research Abstracts

                                College Entrance Exam Result and High School Scholastic Records:
                                   Bases of Student Academic Performance in a State University

                                         Vienna Mi Feranil, Cavite State University - Trece


                                                        Abstract


                  INTRODUCTION
                  An  entrance  examination  is  an  examination  that  many  educational  institutions  use  to  select  students  for
                  admission. These  exams may  be administered at  any level  of  education,  from primary to  higher  education,
                  although  they  are  more  common  at  higher  levels.  It  was  in  the  school  year  1997-1998  when  the  school
                  decided to use the standardized test of the CEM. After a few administrations, it was found out that none  was
                  able to pass the test or hardly reached an expected score. Due to fear that only a few will be qualified  to enroll
                  in  college  which  may  lead  to  bankruptcy,  the  school  decided  to  stop  the  administration  of  the    said
                  standardized test by the CEM and returned to using the teacher-made test.

                  METHODS
                  The  study  used  correlational  research  method.  The  method  was  used  to  investigate  the  extent  to  which
                  variations in one factor such as the first year college academic performance correlate with variations in  one
                  or more other factors such as college entrance exam results and high school scholastic records based  on the
                  correlation  coefficient.  The  primary  data  were  obtained  through  the  entrance  exam  results,  high    school
                  scholastic records, and college academic grades from the Office of the Campus Registrar.

                  RESULTS
                  College entrance exam results of students have fairly satisfactory results. Participant's high school  scholastic
                  records and academic performance in college are satisfactory.  There is a significant difference  between the
                  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  in  students'  academic  performance  in
                  college. The F-ratio of 46.36 is greater than the F critical value for .05 level of 3.01. The  computed F-ratio
                  being  greater  than  the  tabulated  F-ratio  means  that  the  null  hypothesis  is  rejected.    Rejecting  the  null
                  hypothesis further proves that college entrance exam results and high school scholastic  records are significant
                  to student's academic performance in college.

                  DISCUSSIONS
                  The  college  entrance  exam  results  and  high  school  scholastic  records  are  significant  to  student's  academic
                  performance in college. According to the Campus Registrar, high school records could be a determinant  of
                  college  entrance  exam  since  the  students  had  their  high  school  for  four  years  and  the  entrance  exam
                  measures  their  gained  knowledge  from  their  previous  education.  It  may  also  the  reason  why  the  college
                  entrance exam could also be a determinant of first-year college grades since they are in the adjustment  period
                  from at least four years in high school.

                  KEYWORDS: entrance exam, scholastic record, academic performance

                  SUBMISSION ID: R04A-CAVITP-0059
























                                                 Vol. 3, No. 2B, February 2019                      72
                                           http://aaresearchindex.com/ojs/index.php/AAJMRA]]></page><page Index="227"><![CDATA[SOCIAL MEDIA, LEARNING STYLES AND ACADEMIC PERFORMANCE OF STUDENTS:
               BASIS  FOR ENHANCEMENT OF GUIDANCE AND COUNSELING PROGRAM AT CAVITE
                                                 STATE  UNIVERSITY

                                                 Charise Mae D. Galve
                                       Master of Education Major in Guidance and
                                    Counseling  Cavite State University-Main Campus
                                                    November, 2019





                                                      ABSTRACT

                   The  world  today  is  celebrating  the  improvements  in  communication  technology  which  has

           broadened  the  scope  of  communication  through  Information  and  Communication  Technologies

           (ICTs).  Modern Technology in communication no doubt has turned the entire world into a “Global

           village”  (Asemah and Edegoh, 2012). ). Hence, this research was done to find out the social media,

           learning  styles  and  academic  performance  among  the  students  of T3  campuses  of  Cavite  State


           University,  namely, Trece Martires City, Tanza and General Trias in order to establish a basis for

           enhancement  of     guidance  and  counseling  program..  The  descriptive-comparative  method  of

           research  was  utilized  that  investigated  and  described  the  relationship  between  variables  in  their

           natural setting without  manipulation.

                   Results of the study showed that in general, majority of students used Facebook (81.7 %),

           YouTube (50.7 %), and Google+ (26.0 %) while the use of Blogspot and Wordress or Joomla was


           only  one. The mean and standard deviation of not using Google + (M=2.05, SD = 0.024) and using

           Google+   (M=1.91, SD =0.039).The computed t-value was 3.056 with a p-value of 0.002 which is

           significant at

           0.05 level. This suggests that using Google+ as a social media platform has a significant effect on


           the  academic performance of the student.

                   The  findings  also  showed  the  significant  difference  of  Academic  Performance  of  the
                   participants
           and their Learning Styles using F-test, the computed value was 3.190 and with the p-value of 0.005,

           significant at 0.05 level.




            Keywords: Social Media, Learning Styles, Academic Performance, Guidance and
            Counseling]]></page><page Index="228"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="229"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="230"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="231"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="232"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="233"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="234"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="235"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="236"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="237"/><page Index="238"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="239"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="240"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="241"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="242"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="243"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="244"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="245"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="246"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="247"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="248"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="249"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="250"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="251"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>
